[
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "If you were to see people touching a bronze statue’s shoes, the building Sever Hall, and the color crimson, you would realize you were at what university hosting this Certamen competition?",
    "answer": "HARVARD (UNIVERSITY)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, whose shoe people touch, is the mascot of Harvard?",
    "answer": "JOHN HARVARD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This tournament’s opening meeting at Sever Hall featured a wonderful talk by what Professor? Moderator should say: “Subsequent questions will count for points. Good luck and have fun!”",
    "answer": "NAOMI (A.) WEISS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, whose “maiden’s song” for Juno won honor for the collēgium scrībārum histriōnumque, wrote plays like Ajax Mastigophorus and a Saturnian-meter translation of Homer’s Odyssey?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS ANDRONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin term for Livius’ position in Rome as a teacher of Latin and Greek.",
    "answer": "GRAMMATICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In whose entourage was Livius brought to Rome following the end of the war between Rome and Tarentum in 272 B.C.?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS SALINATOR(’S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who recounted how he hid among seals with his men to capture Proteus, the sea god who told him about the fates of the other Greek leaders and how he could safely return to Sparta?",
    "answer": "MENELAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Proteus helped Menelaus capture him?",
    "answer": "EIDOTHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Proteus lived on Pharos, an island off the coast of what modern day country?",
    "answer": "EGYPT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "A future participle agreeing with the subject, a relative clause after a verb like mittō, an accusative gerundive with ad, and a simple ut clause are all ways to express what concept in Latin?",
    "answer": "PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a relative clause of purpose, say in Latin “He sent an ambassador to look at the enemies’ camp.”",
    "answer": "LĒGĀTUM MĪSIT QUĪ HOSTIUM CASTRA SPECTĀRET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence adapted from Livy, which uses a surprising tense for an ut purpose clause: “Dictātor, nē frūstrā creātus esset, in pāce aliquid facere cupiēbat.”",
    "answer": "SOMETHING IN PEACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At what Thracian city, named after the husband of Vibia Sabina, did a group of dispossessed Goths in the late 4th century win a deadly battle against the emperor Valens?",
    "answer": "(H)ADRIANOPLE / (H)ADRIANOPOLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor defeated Maximinus Daza, sometimes called Daia, at Adrianople in 313 A.D., only to lose to Constantine there about a decade later?",
    "answer": "(VALERIUS LICINIANUS) LICINIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Goths had initially fled from their homes due to the raids of what tribe?",
    "answer": "HUNS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word, in various forms, fills in the blanks in these phrases: “caelī ēnārrant [blank] Deī”; “ad maiōrem Deī [blank]”; “sīc trānsit [blank] mundī.”",
    "answer": "GLŌRIA / GLŌRIAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Catholic religious order has the motto “ad maiōrem Deī glōriam”?",
    "answer": "JESUIT(S) // SOCIETY OF JESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the four-word Latin name of the hymn whose name means “glory to God in the highest.”",
    "answer": "GLŌRIA IN EXCELSĪS DEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Caesar’s phrase “cīvitās maximam habet opīniōnem virtūtis” — along with “vacātiō labōrum,” “dēsīderium ōtiī,” and “amor pācis” — shows what genitive use often contrasted with subjective?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE (GENITIVE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in the phrases “ubinam gentium sumus?” and “parum ōtī”?",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE (GENITIVE) // (GENITIVE) OF THE WHOLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in Horace’s lines “magnī formīca labōris ōre trahit quodcumque potest”?",
    "answer": "(GENITIVE OF) {DESCRIPTION / QUALITY}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, whose rivers Asterion, Cephissus, and Inachus were periodically dry for not choosing Poseidon over Hera as the patron, sent champions against Thebes and had kings including Perseus?",
    "answer": "ARGOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What famous Argive city did Perseus found after trading Argos for Tiryns?",
    "answer": "MYCENAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What descendant of Io, fleeing his brother, came from Egypt to claim his right to the Argive throne?",
    "answer": "DANAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A foundation of stones called the statūmen and a nine-inch layer of concrete called the rūdus were both used to make what sort of object, examples of which include the Aemilia and Salāria?",
    "answer": "ROAD(S) / VIA(E)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the final layer of the road, which was a six-inch bedding of fine concrete?",
    "answer": "NUCLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What curbstones were used to set bounds on the road on both sides?",
    "answer": "UMBŌNĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author destroyed his signet ring and removed Nero from his will before his suicide, though he had been the emperor’s arbiter elegantiae and used his experience with debauchery to write the Satyricōn?",
    "answer": "PETRONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who is the protagonist of the Satyricōn, traveling with Ascyltos and Giton?",
    "answer": "ENCOLPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The devolution of the relationship between Petronius and Nero took place over only a few years. In what year had Nero elevated Petronius to the consulship?",
    "answer": "62 A.D."
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What conflict saw brothers nicknamed the “Thunderbolts of War” die near the Baetis River in the same year that the so-called “Sword of War” recaptured Syracuse — 211 B.C.?",
    "answer": "SECOND PUNIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle did these “Thunderbolts of War” — the Scipio brothers — win in Spain a year after the Battle of Cannae?",
    "answer": "DERTOSA / IBERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what year did Fabius Maximus Cunctator, the so-called “Shield of War,” recapture Tarentum?",
    "answer": "209 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What people, who later lost a battle at Silva Malitiōsa, attended a festival of Neptune or Consus in a newly-founded city, enabling their Roman hosts to seize their women for themselves?",
    "answer": "SABINES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the capital city of the Sabines, the birthplace of Romulus’s successor?",
    "answer": "CURES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Sabine chief managed to seize the Capitoline citadel in 460 B.C., though he was quickly dislodged by Gaius Claudius and Publius Valerius?",
    "answer": "(APPIUS) HERDONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin verb, with what meaning, is at the root of a word describing a pause in the middle of a poetic foot, as well as the words “scissors,” “cement,” and “precision”?",
    "answer": "CAEDŌ – TO CUT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of caedō is a tool used for carving material such as wood?",
    "answer": "CHISEL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The pause in the middle of a foot is a caesura. In hexameter poetry, a pause between the fourth and fifth feet is a “bucolic diaeresis.” From what Latin words with what meanings is “bucolic” derived? BŌS – COW and COLŌ – CULTIVATE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words testis, virga, pollex, vīmen, and pollen, which is being described here? Index est quī crīmina aliōrum in iūdiciō dēmōnstrat.",
    "answer": "TESTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words latex, virga, pollex, vīmen, and pollen, which two are most closely synonymous? VIRGA and VĪMEN",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words latex, pollex, discrīmen, and pollen, which is most synonymous with perīculum?",
    "answer": "DISCRĪMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Either by pretending to be a priestess of Hyperborean Artemis, or by rejuvenating her father-in-law Aeson, what woman’s trickery caused Pelias to die and Jason to become king of Iolcus?",
    "answer": "MEDEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In some sources, Aeson is forced to kill himself by drinking the poisonous blood of what animal?",
    "answer": "BULL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Medea, out of jealousy, murdered what daughter of Creon after Jason said he would marry her?",
    "answer": "GLAUCE / CREUSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet, central to the pagans’ talks in Macrobius’s Sāturnālia, accidentally appealed to Christians by showing a child ushering in a golden age in the 4th poem, known as “Messianic,” of his Eclogues?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) VERGIL(IUS MARO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Vergil was born near what town, whose status as a victim of Augustus’s land confiscations is alluded to in the Eclogues?",
    "answer": "MANTUA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet makes an appearance in Poem 10 of the Eclogues, which puts the pastoral landscape in dialogue with the world of elegy?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) CORNELIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Ovid’s Metamorphoses, the story of what river-goddess is told within the tale of Persephone, since she saw the Underworld during her flight from Greece to Sicily to escape the clutches of Alpheus?",
    "answer": "ARETHUSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Arethusa’s story in the Metamorphoses is the culmination of a large series of nested narratives, since the story of Persephone is in turn narrated by the Muses during their contest with what mortals?",
    "answer": "PIERIDES // DAUGHTERS OF PIERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Continuing this story-ception, the contest with the Pierides is narrated to Minerva by one of the Muses shortly after escaping the clutches of what evil Thracian king, who tried to rape them?",
    "answer": "PYRENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Like Galba, what aged emperor gave the Praetorians only low pay and harsh discipline when Laetus and Eclectus raised him to power, kicking off an auction for the throne and a Year of the Five Emperors?",
    "answer": "PERTINAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman had worked alongside Laetus and Eclectus to kill Commodus?",
    "answer": "MARCIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What rogue Praetorian Prefect had promised the soldiers that Galba would give them a donative, making it all the more disappointing when he refused?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) NYMPHIDIUS SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What genre, whose first Roman practitioners actually wrote in Greek, was pioneered in Latin prose with a seven-book work by Cato the Elder and arguably reached its peak with Tacitus’s Annālēs?",
    "answer": "HISTORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work by Tacitus is his only non-historical work and is structured as a Ciceronian dialogue?",
    "answer": "DIALOGUS DĒ ŌRĀTŌRIBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who got his name because one of his ancestors had been a painter, was the first Roman to write history?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) FABIUS PICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Please translate this sentence from Latin into English: “Vergilius tam aeger est ut nōn possit librum perficere.”",
    "answer": "VERGIL IS SO ILL THAT HE CANNOT COMPLETE THE BOOK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Latin into English: “Lēgāmus opus Ovidiī in quō loquitur dē mūtātīs fōrmīs.”",
    "answer": "TALKS ABOUT CHANGED FORMS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Latin into English: “Cum Nerōnem laudāvisset, Lūcānus tamen coniūrātiōnis particeps esse cōnstituit.”",
    "answer": "PARTICIPANT IN THE CONSPIRACY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What one-syllable Latin conjunction, which is sometimes joined with modo in a proviso clause, surprisingly always takes the present indicative when it has the meaning “while”?",
    "answer": "DUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What tense and mood would follow dum if it translated “for” in the sentence “The soldier was waiting for his commander to arrive”?",
    "answer": "IMPERFECT SUBJUNCTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When dum is followed by a past tense indicative, as in Vergil’s line “dulcēs exuviae, dum fāta deusque sinēbat,” it can loosely be translated as “while,” but what is the more precise sense? You can either give a different translation or explain verbally how it differs from dum with the present.",
    "answer": "ROUND TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage about the First Punic War, which I will read twice, then answer in Latin the question that follows. Cum Poenī cōnsulem prohibērent in Siciliam trānsīre, is sparsit rūmōrem, quasi sibi bellum gerere nōn iam licēret, et classem retrō ēgit. Dīgressīs deinde Poenīs, quī profectiōnī ēius crēdiderant, nāvēs Siciliae appulit. The question: Quī crēdulī erant et dīgressī sunt?",
    "answer": "POENĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cūr cōnsul in Siciliam transīre nōn poterat?",
    "answer": "NOT ACCEPT SOMETHING WITH CUM]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid in rūmōre dictum est?",
    "answer": "CŌNSULĪ BELLUM GERERE NŌN IAM {LICĒRE / LICET}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lines consisting entirely of spondees and a line addressing Titus Tatius in excessive alliteration show what author’s willingness to experiment with the brand-new dactylic hexameter in his Annālēs?",
    "answer": "ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sound did Ennius express with the onomatopoeia “taratantara”?",
    "answer": "A TRUMPET BLARING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name either of the two comedies by Ennius, one about a wrestler and another about an innkeeper’s wife. CAUPUNCULA or PANCRATIASTĒS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "How many words in the following English sentence are derived from Latin? “While avidly watching birds outside the national convention, I saw several ospreys.”",
    "answer": "FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Provide the ultimate Latin root of two English words from the above sentence. For words formed from more than one Latin root, you only need to provide one.",
    "answer": "SEE BELOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Provide the rest.",
    "answer": "OSPREYS – {AVIS / PRAEDA / ŌS / FRANGŌ}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who installed reflective marble in his palace shortly after Lappius Maximus barely ended the revolt of Saturninus, though this did not save him from a stab in the groin by his butler Stephanus?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What famous generalissimo was the father of Domitian’s wife?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) DOMITIUS CORBULO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Saturninus had tried to induce what German tribe to rebel and invade Roman borders?",
    "answer": "CHATTI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman remained with her father until he passed at Colonus, before returning to her home where she tried to bury her cursed brother Polynices in defiance of the decree of Creon?",
    "answer": "ANTIGONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What fiancé of Antigone, a son of Creon, committed suicide upon learning of her death?",
    "answer": "HAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Colonus was a suburb of what city, whose king secured the burial of the Seven Against Thebes?",
    "answer": "ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The Halieutica is a minor work of what author, who gave voice to Briseis and other women, addressed Corinna in his Amōrēs, and wrote a 15-book epic poem called Metamorphōsēs?",
    "answer": "OVID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After being banished by Augustus, Ovid spent the last years of his life in what city, where he composed his Tristia and Epistulae ex Pontō?",
    "answer": "TOMI(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What minor work of Ovid, named after a bird, wishes several hundred terrible mythological punishments on an unnamed enemy?",
    "answer": "ĪBIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two states are the only ones with one-word Latin mottos, one of which is a first-person verb meaning “I direct” and the other of which is a comparative adjective meaning “higher”? MAINE and NEW YORK",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "There are three states with a four-word Latin motto. Identify one of them and give the motto.",
    "answer": "ASPERA // VERMONT – STĒLLA QUĀRTA DECIMA FULGEAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "There are two states with a six-word Latin motto. Identify one of them and give the motto.",
    "answer": "MASSACHUSETTS – ĒNSE PETIT PLACIDAM SUB LĪBERTĀTE QUIĒTEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Polybius, famous paintings were used as gaming tables after what city, which raised Critolaus as its dictator, was sacked by Lucius Mummius in 146 B.C.?",
    "answer": "CORINTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Roman general, fresh off victories against Andriscus in 148 B.C., left Macedonia in order to deal with Critolaus?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS CAECILIUS) METELLUS MACEDONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Livy, what Corinthian noble fled to Italy early in Rome’s history, and had a son whose name reflected the Etruscan city he settled in?",
    "answer": "DEMARATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Nereus alone knew how to find what wedding gift of Gaea, a place defended by the serpent Ladon, tended to by a few sisters, and breached by either Atlas or Heracles during a labor?",
    "answer": "GARDEN OF THE HESPERIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sometimes the location of the Hesperides was near what tribe that lived in the far, far north?",
    "answer": "HYPERBOREANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On his way to the Hesperides, Heracles had killed what king of Egypt who tried sacrificing him, alongside other strangers, to Zeus?",
    "answer": "BUSIRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city acted as the eastern terminus of the via Egnātia, was split into two by a strait called “Bosporus,” and was the capital of the Eastern Roman Empire before it was renamed “Istanbul”?",
    "answer": "BYZANTIUM / CONSTANTINOPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the ancient name for the body of water that bordered Constantinople to the north.",
    "answer": "PONTUS EUXĪNUS // EUXINE SEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the ancient name for the Sea of Marmara, which bordered Constantinople to the south.",
    "answer": "PROPONTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Exiled for killing his half-brother Phocus, who went to Phthia, where he became king, welcomed men like Phoenix and Patroclus, and let them accompany his son by Thetis, Achilles?",
    "answer": "PELEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After moving to Phthia, Peleus had to get purified again for killing his father-in-law, and sought out what king of Iolcus, who had previously been an Argonaut alongside Peleus in defiance of his father?",
    "answer": "ACASTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the reasons for why either Phoenix or Patroclus came to Phthia. or PATROCLUS HAD KILLED A BOY (CLITONYMUS OVER A DICE GAME)",
    "answer": "PHOENIX HAD SLEPT WITH HIS FATHER’S CONCUBINE AND GOT IN TROUBLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to a Roman poet, the existence of what objects removes any fear of death, accounts for free will through clīnāmen, forms the core of Epicureanism, and explains the rērum nātūra scientifically?",
    "answer": "ATOMS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Lucretius’s work, what deity personifies Nature’s generative force and the Epicurean ideal of ataraxy, or undisturbedness?",
    "answer": "VENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What English word is often used to translate the idea of clīnāmen, as seen in the title of a book by Stephen Greenblatt on the history of Lucretius’s rediscovery by Poggio Bracciolini?",
    "answer": "SWERVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: “If I had come home, I would have seen you.” For this sentence, both verbs should be pluperfect subjunctive.",
    "answer": "SĪ DOMUM VĒNISSEM, TĒ VĪDISSEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in Latin: “Would I see you tomorrow if I were to come again?”",
    "answer": "VIDEAMNE TĒ CRAS SĪ ITERUM VENIAM?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Finally, say in Latin: “If only I were able to run for ten hours to see you!”",
    "answer": "UTINAM POSSEM DECEM HORĀS CURRERE {UT TĒ VIDĒREM // AD TĒ VIDENDUM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Members of what people swore an oath in a linen-covered tent before joining battle at Aquilonia in 293 B.C., the last battle of a three-war conflict that also saw a defeat at Caudine Forks?",
    "answer": "SAMNITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though his epitaph claims that he took Samnium and subdued all Lucania, what early member of the Scipio family suffered a defeat at the hands of the Samnites at Camerinum?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS CORNELIUS SCIPIO SCAPULA) BARBATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In the middle of the Second Samnite War, Fabius Rullianus also broke Etruscan power at what lake in 310 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(LAKE) VADIMO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What part of the body — on which a pecten might be employed to make it cōmptus, often in the hands of an ornātrīx — was known in Latin as crīnēs or capillī?",
    "answer": "HAIR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What celestial phenomenon is etymologically described as “hairy,” though it is related to a third word for “hair”?",
    "answer": "COMET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How would a person’s hair look if they are described with the phrase crīnibus passīs?",
    "answer": "DISHEVELED / SCATTERED / IN DISARRAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device is found in the phrases “ex oculīs fūgit ceu fūmus in aurās,” “eam agnōvī obscūram, quālem quī per nūbila surgere lūnam videt,” and other phrases with sīcut or quasi?",
    "answer": "SIMILE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Opposing speeches by Caesar and Cato the Younger frame the second half of what work, which details the battle of Pistoria as part of its monographic treatment of a 63 B.C. conspiracy against the Republic?",
    "answer": "(SALLUST’S) BELLUM CATILĪNAE // DĒ CATILĪNAE CONIŪRĀTIŌNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Sallust, left unfinished at his death, was a history beginning at 78 BC?",
    "answer": "HISTORIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The first Latin historical monograph may have been a work by Coelius Antipater on what conflict, which later received a 17-book epic poetic treatment?",
    "answer": "SECOND PUNIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hecate’s appearance on earth was often accompanied by what animals — which the queen Hecuba transformed into — though the most famous examples of these beasts were Orthrus and Cerberus?",
    "answer": "HELL-HOUND / DOG"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "The expression “a sop for Cerberus” stems from a scene in the Aeneid where what mythological figure throws a honey-cake to the guard dog?",
    "answer": "SIBYL (OF CUMAE) // DEIPHOBE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hecuba’s transformation into a fiery-eyed dog happened because she murdered what king of the Thracian Chersonese for revenge?",
    "answer": "POLYM(N)ESTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Shortly before his death, who chose Rufinus as Eastern Praetorian Prefect and Stilicho as the Western one, so that his sons Honorius and Arcadius would have guides in a now-divided empire?",
    "answer": "THEODOSIUS {I // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before attempts at peace broke down, what man was chosen by Honorius to succeed Stilicho as magister utrīusque mīlitiae, while his brother-in-law Athaulf also received a prize position?",
    "answer": "ALARIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Arcadius held real power during much of the reign of Theodosius II, her brother?",
    "answer": "PULCHERIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into idiomatic Latin without using nōn or any such adverb: “Alexander’s soldiers said that they would not follow him.” [pause] To do this, you should use a verb for “denied.”",
    "answer": "MĪLITĒS ALEXANDRĪ NEGĀVĒRUNT SĒ EUM SECŪTŪROS (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into good Latin: “Alexander said that the soldiers who were remaining would receive rewards.”",
    "answer": "ALEXANDER DĪXIT (EŌS) MĪLITĒS QUĪ (RĒ)MĀNĒRENT PRAEMIA ACCEPTŪRŌS (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Now translate: “Hannibal thought that he ought to be praised a little less than Alexander and Pyrrhus.”",
    "answer": "ROUND THREE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In the Aeneid, who prays to a tearful Hercules before hurling his spear at Turnus, unaware that he would shortly be killed and stripped of his sword-belt far from his father Evander?",
    "answer": "PALLAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What crime decorated Pallas’s sword-belt?",
    "answer": "THE DANAIDS MURDERING THEIR HUSBANDS (ON THEIR WEDDING NIGHT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pallas had originally planned to fight what son of Mezentius?",
    "answer": "LAUSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Menedemus forcing himself into a life of torment, a man disguising himself as the titular eunuch, and the successes of the parasite Phormio appear in the six palliātae of what comic playwright?",
    "answer": "TERENCE // (PUBLIUS) TERENTIUS (AFER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What about Terence’s biography suggested to critics that his plays were actually by Scipio Aemilianus?",
    "answer": "HE WAS A FREED SLAVE // HE WAS FROM CARTHAGE AND HAD TO LEARN LATIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to legend, Terence had to present his first comedy for approval to what other comic playwright, the author of Plocium?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the following four words: sospes, incolumis, tūtus, salvus?",
    "answer": "SAFE / UNHARMED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we get the word tūtus?",
    "answer": "TUEOR – {WATCH (OVER) // PROTECT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the more standard past participle of tueor?",
    "answer": "TUITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The lēx Ovīnia gave holders of what office the duty of revising senatorial lists, though one of its most famous holders in 312 B.C. used it to build an eponymous road and aqueduct during an 18-month term?",
    "answer": "CENSOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The censorial elections were typically held by what assembly, which allotted a total of 193 votes among the citizens of Rome?",
    "answer": "COMITIA CENTURIĀTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What dictator authored a law requiring one censor to be plebeian in 339 B.C., just two years before becoming the first plebeian to hold the praetorship?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) PUBLILIUS PHILO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "From what author do we get the quotes “pulvis et umbra sumus,” “sapere audē” “aurea mediocritās,” and “dulce et decōrum est prō patriā morī”?",
    "answer": "HORACE // (QUINTUS) HORATIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What words complete the Horatian quote “quandōque bonus [blank]”?",
    "answer": "DORMĪTAT HOMĒRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two-word phrase of Horace looks back to the good old days — those days being 42 B.C., when Munatius Plancus was consul?",
    "answer": "CŌNSULE PLANCŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Plans for Roman borders along the Elbe and Vistula rivers had to be scuttled after what disaster, called the clādēs Variāna by an emperor who bashed his head against the wall and probably cursed Arminius?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) TEUTOBURG FOREST // TEUTOBERGER WALD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What blundering oaf of a general walked into this disastrous trap and gave his name to the disaster?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) QUINCTILIUS VARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Arminius, the warlord who engineered this stunning reverse for the Romans, was the head honcho of what tribe?",
    "answer": "CHERUSCI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who punished Glaucus the horsekeeper by having his mares devour him, Tyndareus for neglecting her rites, Helios for revealing her affair, and Anchises for boasting of her love for him?",
    "answer": "APHRODITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Glaucus was the father by Eurynome of what mythological hero?",
    "answer": "BELLEROPHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom did Aphrodite cause Helios to fall in love with as punishment, though her father Orchamus did not allow the union?",
    "answer": "LEUCOTHOE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb is at the ultimate root of “squat,” which initially referred to “forcing” down your body’s weight and thus comes through the compound cōgō?",
    "answer": "AGŌ [PROMPT ON “CŌGŌ” BEFORE IT IS READ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word is at the ultimate root of “squad,” as well as “square”?",
    "answer": "QUATTUOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we get “squash?” The “s” comes from the prefix ex-, which intensifies this verb.",
    "answer": "QUATIŌ / QUATERE = (TO / I) SHAKE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into alliterative Latin using a passive periphrastic: “Sextus must follow the seven allies.”",
    "answer": "SEXTŌ SEPTEM SOCIĪ SEQUENDĪ SUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into alliterative Latin using a gerund: “We will be able to gain the reward by fighting.”",
    "answer": "POTERIMUS PRAEMIŌ POTĪRĪ PUGNANDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into alliterative Latin using a gerund: “A desire to run quickly to Corinth has seized Crassus.”",
    "answer": "{CUPĪDŌ / CUPIDITĀS} CELERITER CORINTHUM CURRENDĪ CRASSUM CĒPIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What figure in Latin literature, who “first captured” a “wretched” poet with her ocellī, may have had the real name Hostia and was the chief subject of the Monobiblos by Propertius?",
    "answer": "CYNTHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Propertius declared himself the Roman version of what author from Cyrene, whose Aetia also inspired Catullus’s “Lock of Berenice”?",
    "answer": "CALLIMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In poem sixteen of the Monobiblos, what type of object bewails its sorrowful fate at the hands of Cynthia in a reverse paraclausithyron?",
    "answer": "DOOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The words “Ollus Quiris lētō datus…” preceded what sort of event, which featured a special lectus, actors wearing imāginēs, a dēsignātor who organized it, and a laudātiō fūnebris?",
    "answer": "FUNERAL (PROCESSION) // FŪNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin word for the act performed when a Roman died at home, where the eldest son bent over the body and called the father by name.",
    "answer": "CONCLĀMĀTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the aptly named sort of funeral performed for very young children?",
    "answer": "FŪNUS ACERBUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When she objected to her son’s divorce of Octavia, who was invited onto a boat set up to collapse, an act which not even Burrus and Seneca could explain away on her son Nero’s behalf?",
    "answer": "AGRIPPINA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom did Nero marry — though not for long — after divorcing Octavia, taking her from her previous husband?",
    "answer": "POPPAEA SABINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Agrippina also objected to Nero’s affair with what freedwoman of Claudius?",
    "answer": "(CLAUDIA) ACTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author disparages his father Patricius while praising his mother’s piety in an autobiography of his path from neo-Platonism and Manichaeism to Christianity, the Confessions?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTINE // (AURELIUS) AUGUSTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name Augustine’s mother.",
    "answer": "MONICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What book by what author changed Augustine’s life and inspired him to pursue philosophy?",
    "answer": "CICERO’S HORTĒNSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb adimō, give the 3rd person plural, perfect passive subjunctive, keeping in mind that it is a compound of emō and forms its fourth principal part with the same vowel as emō.",
    "answer": "ADEMPTĪ SINT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the same form for attingō.",
    "answer": "ATTACTĪ SINT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Make both the form from the tossup and first bonus active. ADĒMERINT and ATTIGERINT",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because her son looked too much like his Thracian father, what Athenian princess murdered her son Itys before serving him to Tereus to get revenge for her sister Philomela?",
    "answer": "PROCNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the corresponding birds that Tereus, Philomela, and Procne were all turned into. HOOPOE, SWALLOW, NIGHTINGALE [“SWALLOW” and “NIGHTINGALE” CAN BE FLIPPED]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Pandion had married Tereus to Procne for helping him in a war against what city led by Labdacus?",
    "answer": "THEBES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dēscrībāmus nunc proprietātēs dictiōnum in hāc sententia: “dīs genite et genitūre deōs.” Quō cāsū sunt et “genite” et “genitūre”?",
    "answer": "VOCĀTĪVŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is exemplified by the word dīs?",
    "answer": "(ABLATIVE OF) {SOURCE / ORIGIN}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What modern English letter is orthographically descended from the Greek letter which gives its name to the rhetorical device in that quote?",
    "answer": "X"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who cites his father’s participation at Bedriacum for an anecdote, goes per speciēs in a gossipy and rumor-heavy style through the lives and personalities of twelve Roman rulers?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under what emperor was Suetonius employed in the imperial archives, giving him a wealth of material with which to compose his biographies?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What later work, purporting to be by six different authors, imitates Suetonius’s style but is so unreliable that many scholars have assumed it has to be a joke or parody?",
    "answer": "HISTORIA AUGUSTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared by a senator whose support of the lēx Sempronia Agrāria got him a spot on the Gracchi’s land commission, and the co-consul of Junius Pullus who failed to heed the chickens?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS PULCHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tiberius Gracchus came to prominence while on the staff of Gaius Hostilius Mancinus during the siege of what city, which was finally defeated in the year of his tribunate?",
    "answer": "NUMANTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claudius Pulcher also had family ties to the Gracchi. What was his relationship with Tiberius?",
    "answer": "FATHER-IN-LAW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following exclamation into English: “Quam pulcher est homō quī virtūtem habet!”",
    "answer": "HOW BEAUTIFUL IS A MAN WHO HAS VIRTUE!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: “Quotiēns mūlus aquam bibit, totiēns ego vīnum.”",
    "answer": "AS OFTEN AS A MULE DRINKS WATER I DO (DRINK) WINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally, translate this one: “Tantō mē pauperior eris quantō tē sapientior sum.”",
    "answer": "YOU WILL BE AS MUCH POORER THAN I AS I AM WISER THAN YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king, who lived with his 6 sons and 6 daughters that were married to one another, refused to help Odysseus when he returned 10 days later after his crew had opened the bag of winds?",
    "answer": "AEOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Aeneid, what goddess commands Aeolus to try sinking Aeneas’ ships with his winds?",
    "answer": "JUNO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to some sources, what son of Aeolus proposed to him the idea of having his sons marry his daughters, since he had already committed incest with his sister Canace?",
    "answer": "SEMIFINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Works in what form were famously discovered by Petrarch after being posthumously published by Tiro, revealing their author’s relations with Lucceius and other familiārēs as well as his best friend Atticus?",
    "answer": "EPISTLES / LETTERS / EPISTULAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author’s disappointingly mediocre letter-collection, which includes a reference to a historical work on the Parthian wars of Lucius Verus, was rediscovered in the 19th century?",
    "answer": "(M. CORNELIUS) FRONTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name any two Latin authors between the death of Fronto and 565 AD who published an extant prose letter collection.",
    "answer": "POSSIBLE ANSWERS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify and correct the mistake, if any, in the following Latin sentence: Līberōs meōs īrātus rogāvī quō pridiē īverint et quid fēcissent.",
    "answer": "ĪVERINT SHOULD BE ĪVISSENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify and correct the mistake, if any, in the following Latin sentence: Adeō magistrum timeō nē eum alloquī audeam.",
    "answer": "NĒ SHOULD BE UT NŌN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify and correct the mistake, if any, in the following Latin sentence, which is intended to have a purpose clause: Fugiō ut nēmō mē inveniat.",
    "answer": "UT NĒMŌ SHOULD BE NĒ QUIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The capture of Vetera was the high point of whose revolt, which was incited by Fonteius Capito’s false accusations and saw him pretend to support Vespasian before Cerealis defeated his Batavian forces?",
    "answer": "JULIUS CIVILIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two allies, also with the nōmen Julius, helped Civilis form his imperium Galliārum? (JULIUS) CLASSICUS and (JULIUS) TUTOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cerealis also fought in Britain and seems to have dealt with a revolt by Venutius, the former husband of what Brigantian queen who once turned Caratacus over to the Romans?",
    "answer": "CARTIMANDUA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island, which saw a sacrifice to Apollo, Artemis, and Leto after the murder of Thersites, was the birthplace of the pirate-fleeing, dolphin-riding Greek singer Arion, and the home of Orpheus’s lyre?",
    "answer": "LESBOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why did Achilles murder Thersites?",
    "answer": "FOR MOCKING HIM FOR LAMENTING AFTER MURDERING PENTHESILEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Arion had spent most of his life at the court of what tyrant of Corinth?",
    "answer": "PERIANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of object are all of the following: phasēlus, scapha, ratis, and — by metonymy — puppis?",
    "answer": "BOAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Navēs onerāriae taedā et pice et stuppā complētae sunt. Quid Anglicē significat “pix”?",
    "answer": "PITCH / ASPHALT / TAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Navis in syrtim incessit. Quid Anglicē significat “syrtis”?",
    "answer": "SANDBANK / SHOAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological man was depicted “on his knees,” or en gonasin, after he fought the Ligurians in a return journey that also saw the birth of Scythes, the defeat of Eryx, and the death of Cacus?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Engonasin is not the only constellation that commemorates Heracles. The constellation Ophiuchus portrays him killing what sort of animal at Omphale’s behest?",
    "answer": "SNAKE / SERPENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Heracles was wounded and fell to his knees while battling the Ligurians, what miraculous event did Zeus send to save him, which explains the terrain around the city of Marseilles?",
    "answer": "A RAIN OF STONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author’s “Tale of the Tub” was potentially inspired by Aristides and the fābulae Milēsiae, which he combines with knowledge about the cults of Osiris and Isis in an 11-book narrative about Lucius?",
    "answer": "(L.) APULEIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Republican historian, a so-called ēmendātor sermōnis ūsitātī, penned a Latin collection of fābulae Milēsiae?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) SISENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name either the wife of Milo whom Lucius saw transform into an owl, or her servant who accidentally gave Lucius the wrong potion and turned him into a donkey. PAMPHILA or PHOTIS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus failed to obtain the consulship of what year B.C., which saw Caesar’s first crossing of the English Channel and the fulfillment of deals discussed in the previous year at Luca?",
    "answer": "55 (B.C.)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What law of 55 B.C. was one such deal, as it procured governorships in Syria and Spain for Crassus and Pompey, respectively?",
    "answer": "LĒX TREBŌNIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ahenobarbus, a staunch opponent of Caesar, attempted in 49 B.C. to intercept Caesar’s forces at what city, which previously served as a rebel base until it was abandoned for Bovianum Vetus?",
    "answer": "CORFINIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: “I do not know what children he is the father of.”",
    "answer": "NESCIŌ QUŌRUM {FĪLIŌRUM / NĀTŌRUM / LĪBERŌRUM} PATER SIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this one using dēsum: “I never thought I would lack words.”",
    "answer": "{DĒFŪTURA (ESSE) // DĒFORE}"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence, using two different non-indicative forms of caveō: “Don’t beware big dogs more than small ones.”",
    "answer": "PARVŌS (CANĒS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words “roulette,” “round,” “adroit,” “enroll,” and “rotate,” which does NOT belong by derivation, since it is from regō rather than rota?",
    "answer": "ADROIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb is at the root of “routine” and “route”?",
    "answer": "RUMPŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun is at the root of the Spanish word “arroyo” meaning “ravine” and the French word “rue” meaning “street,” as well as an English word meaning “shaped into alternate ridges and grooves”?",
    "answer": "RUGA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "New alluvial deposits allowed what man to find respite from his madness after anger at the effects of Harmonia’s necklace and robe led him to kill his mother Eriphyle and avenge his father Amphiaraus?",
    "answer": "ALCM(A)EON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "These alluvial deposits were found at what river, whose god gave Alcmaeon his daughter Callirhoe in marriage?",
    "answer": "ACHELOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Alcmaeon’s tomb, surrounded by tall cypress trees, was found near what city, where he was murdered at the command of king Phegeus?",
    "answer": "PSOPHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what field of study might one use two similar three-letter abbreviations, one ending with F and one with D, that feature passive periphrastics with faciendum and dēmōnstrandum?",
    "answer": "MATH(EMATICS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. In what field of work within Classics might one find abbreviations like ed. pr. and MSS., as well as phrases like falsa lectiō?",
    "answer": "FROM MANUSCRIPTS [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The abbreviation ed. pr. refers to the first publication of a particular text. What does it stand for?",
    "answer": "ĒDITIŌ PRĪNCEPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In his criticism of epigrammatic sententiae and the Senecan style, who advocates for a focus on rērum pondera and the old ideal of the vir bonus dīcendī perītus in a 12-book work on an orator’s education?",
    "answer": "(M. FABIUS) QUINTILIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "About what Flavian epic poet, who adapted Apollonius of Rhodes, did Quintilian write “multum nūper amīsimus”?",
    "answer": "(C.) VALERIUS FLACCUS (BALBUS SETINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What megalomaniacal rhetorician was a notorious example of the fear of corrupt teachers passing on their morals to their students?",
    "answer": "REMMIUS PALAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The reports of an enslaved man named Vindicius forced what consul to preside over the execution of his own sons, before he simultaneously killed and was killed by his opponent at Silva Arsia in 509 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(L. JUNIUS) BRUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Shortly after this battle, Publicola earned the people’s favor by moving his house off of what hill?",
    "answer": "VELIA // VELIAN (HILL)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The battle of Silva Arsia was inconclusive at first, but what supernatural event proved that the Romans had defeated the Etruscans?",
    "answer": "ETRUSCANS HAD SUSTAINED ONE MORE LOSS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words ter, quater, pater, alter, and ūter, how many of them can you add an “e” at the end of to get a legitimate Latin verb form?",
    "answer": "FOUR (ALL EXCEPT ALTER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "How many of those four verb forms – that is, tere, quatere, patere, and ūtere – could be imperative?",
    "answer": "ALL FOUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify which of these verb forms, if any, would still be legitimate verb forms if the first “e” were lengthened, and parse the resulting forms.",
    "answer": "ŪTĒRE – 2ND SINGULAR FUTURE (OF ŪTOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Premiering in 191 B.C. but later revived with the actor Roscius, what Plautine play features the pimp Ballio outsmarted by an enslaved man whose name is derived from the Greek for “fake”?",
    "answer": "PSEUDOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Plautine play, where a man tries to convince his daughters to divorce their husbands, premiered at the Plebeian games of 200 B.C. and is known for its remarkable lack of dramatic events?",
    "answer": "STICHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In what play of Plautus does Saturio sell a pretend Arabian captive to a pimp so that he can buy a good meal?",
    "answer": "PERSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Helios nightly rode the currents of what river, which was believed to issue from the Underworld and to circle around the flat earth, marking the furthest boundaries of the world?",
    "answer": "OCEANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What peculiar vessel did Helios use to complete his daily journey on the river Ocean? A description is fine.",
    "answer": "(GOLDEN) CUP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Prometheus Bound, the river Oceanus appears as a character and rides on what animal, which fought the Arimaspians for gold at the northern limits of the world?",
    "answer": "GRIFFIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage about scenes of horror during the civil war, which I will read twice, then answer in English the question that follows. Paucī, cum prīmum cīvium sanguis effūsus est, vīsū ipsō perterritī diffūgēre. Alius autem, ut corpus frātris impūne spoliāre posset, abscīsum caput longē mīsit; alius, ōra parentis lacerāns, nimiā probābat spectantibus īrā eum quem iugulāret nōn esse patrem. The question: What caused a few soldiers to flee the battlefield?",
    "answer": "THE SIGHT OF CITIZENS’ BLOOD BEING SHED [ACCEPT CLOSE EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did one soldier manage to take spoils from his own brother’s body without the body being recognized?",
    "answer": "HE {CUT OFF // HURLED / KICKED AWAY} HIS BROTHER’S HEAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did the soldier who killed his father attempt to prove to the spectators, and how?",
    "answer": "DISPLAYED TOWARD THE BODY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Efforts against what phenomenon provoked a revolt on the Caelian Hill by Felicissimus, saw the creation of the Antoniniānus, and led to an ineffectual 301 A.D. Edict by Diocletian?",
    "answer": "PRACTICAL EFFECT OF THAT ACTION?”; DO NOT ACCEPT “PRICE GOUGING”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When the emperor Constans failed to quell inflation, what man usurped rule of the West in 350 A.D. until Constantius II in turn defeated him?",
    "answer": "MAGNENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What term refers to the new gold coin that replaced the aureus during the reign of Diocletian and was stabilized at 72 to the Roman pound by Constantine?",
    "answer": "SOLIDUS / NOMISMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word appears in the ancient names of Chaves in modern-day Portugal, Baden-Baden in modern-day Germany, Aix-en-’ in modern-day France, and Bath in modern-day Britain?",
    "answer": "AQUA(E)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the modern name of Germany’s city of Aquae Granni, which was Charlemagne’s capital?",
    "answer": "AACHEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what modern-day country is the city of Aquae Regiae located, like Hadrumentum and Thysdrus?",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Iliad, elm trees were planted around the burial mound of what king, who ruled a city at the foot of Mt. Placus, and, after being killed alongside his 7 sons, was buried in full armor by Achilles?",
    "answer": "EETION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the apt name of Eetion’s city that he ruled?",
    "answer": "HYPOPLACIAN THEBES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During another of Achilles’ excursions, he captures what son of Priam, while he worked in an orchard, and sold him and his brothers Isus and Antiphus for ransom?",
    "answer": "LYCAON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, would an Ancient Roman likely NOT have recognized as a profession? caupō, tortor, abūtor, lignārius.",
    "answer": "ABŪTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, would an Ancient Roman likely NOT have eaten? trīticum, pāvō, caepa, olea.",
    "answer": "NONE OF THE ABOVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, would an Ancient Roman likely NOT have recognized as a color? līvidus, cānus, prasinus, hirsūtus.",
    "answer": "HIRSŪTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Titles meaning “Night Watch” and “Battle on the Ships” — Nyctēgresia and Epinausimachē — were coined by what eminent figure in the collegium poētārum, a native of Pisaurum and prolific tragedian?",
    "answer": "ACCIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For what nobleman and fellow tragedian did Accius notably refuse to rise in a meeting of the collegium poētārum?",
    "answer": "(C. JULIUS) CAESAR STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Accius wasn’t the only tragedian with difficult Greek titles. Name either the tragedy of Ennius whose name contains a Greek noun meaning “ransom,” or his tragedy whose name contains a Greek noun meaning “prisoner of war.” HECTORIS LUTRA or ANDROMACHA AECHMALŌTIS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What conflict, at whose sites archaeologists found sling bullets labeled “Piso,” saw Rupilius defeat a supposed fire-breather and prophet in 132 B.C. during a large Sicilian revolt co-led by Cleon? 2023 Harvard Certamen Adv. Finals Visual",
    "answer": "FIRST SERVILE WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Inscriptions on sling bullets, sometimes with insulting messages or obscene drawings, were common in Roman combat. For instance, these 11 sling bullets were all found around what Italian city?",
    "answer": "PERUSIA / PERUGIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the nōmen of the man referred to in sling bullet 8, whose praenōmen was Quintus?",
    "answer": "SALVIDIENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What exact Latin form completes these blanks: “sed vetant [blank] Iovis”; “corruptissimā rē pūblicā plūrimae [blank]”; “quid [blank] sine mōribus vānae prōficiunt?”; “silent [blank] enim inter arma.”",
    "answer": "LĒGĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Fill in the following sentence with Latin of your own making that idiomatically explains the relevant phrase: “Prōverbium ‘ab asinō lānam’ dictum est dē eīs hominibus quī [blank].”",
    "answer": "SAMPLE ANSWER: ALIQUID FACERE CONANTUR QUOD FIERI NON POTEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now do the same for this sentence: “Prōverbium ‘Acheruntis pābulum’ dictum est dē eīs hominibus quī [blank].”",
    "answer": "SAMPLE ANSWER: MORTE DIGNI SUNT OB NEQUITIAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who ensured the survival of Latin literature when he began the tradition of scriptōria in his monastery at Vivarium, to which he retired in 554 after writing a history of the Goths and befriending Boethius?",
    "answer": "CASSIODORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Both Boethius and Cassiodorus served in what position at the culmination of their political careers?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER OFFICIŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author from Seville made an essential contribution to the preservation of classical knowledge in medieval times with his Orīginēs sīve Etymologiae, a monumental encyclopedic work?",
    "answer": "ISIDORE (OF SEVILLE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When recognized by the spotter, perform the following commands: tendēns manum ad vultum sociī, interpōne pollicem duōbus digitīs et clāmā Anglicē tē nāsum eius cēpisse.",
    "answer": "BETWEEN THEIR INDEX AND MIDDLE FINGERS, AND SHOUT “GOT YOUR NOSE!”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform these commands: Simulā tē invēnisse nummulum aureum post aurem sodālis, et dīc Anglicē tibi in animō esse illum nummum moderātōribus prō quīnque punctīs trādere.",
    "answer": "THAT THEY PLAN TO GIVE IT TO THE MODERATORS IN EXCHANGE FOR FIVE POINTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform these commands: ūtrāque manū facite circulum pollice et indice; deinde, manibus inversīs, tenēte circulōs iūxtā oculōs quasi persōnam gerās.",
    "answer": "THEIR HANDS UPSIDE DOWN AND HOLD THE CIRCLES AGAINST THEIR EYES LIKE A MASK"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What event, where judges wore dark-coloured clothing in mourning, rewarded victors with parsley, and was founded by Adrastus to honor an infant nicknamed Archemorus?",
    "answer": "NEMEAN GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Right after these games, the Seven Against Thebes reached Thebes where Tydeus met what man, who was sent alongside Polyphontes and 50 other men to challenge him?",
    "answer": "MAEON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the father of the 4 leading defenders of Thebes, most notably Melanippus, whose brains were eaten?",
    "answer": "ASTACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation, if necessary, between “decoy” and “coy,” the first of which is cognate with “cage” and the second of which is cognate with “acquit.” CAVUS / CAVEA and QUIĒS / QUIESCŌ / QUIĒTUS, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation, if necessary, between “chinch” and “cinch.” CIMEX and CINGŌ, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation, if necessary, between “colony” and “colonel.” COLŌ / COLŌNUS and COLUMNA, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, the site of Hadrian’s death, was connected to Puteoli with a pontoon bridge by Caligula, as he sought to disprove an astrologer’s prediction by riding across the Bay of Naples on horseback?",
    "answer": "BAIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Republican commander died of a massive hemorrhage in Puteoli after retiring from power?",
    "answer": "SULLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the name of the astrologer of Tiberius who had cast doubt on Caligula’s imperial prospects?",
    "answer": "THRASYLLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players, there is an extra clue after the question. Which of the following is the highest honor a Roman could earn: corōna obsidiōnālis, corōna aurea, corōna querca, corōna mūrālis? This honor was awarded to the individual who raised a siege.",
    "answer": "CORŌNA OBSIDIŌNĀLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What honor was a gold crown awarded to the first person to enter a besieged town?",
    "answer": "CORŌNA MŪRĀLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What was the second highest honor, awarded for saving the life of a citizen?",
    "answer": "CORŌNA CĪVICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage adapted from Augustine, which I will read twice, then answer in English the question that follows. Cum parārem recitāre imperātōrī laudēs, in quibus mentientī favērētur ā scientibus, aspexī pauperem iocantem. Ingemuī, quod omnibus cōnātibus nihil vellem aliud nisi laetitiam nancīscī, quō mē mendīcus ille praecessisset numquam illūc fortasse ventūrum. The question: Augustine fears he may never reach what goal despite all his efforts, even though the beggar had achieved it easily?",
    "answer": "(ACHIEVING) HAPPINESS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How does Augustine describe what happens as someone is reciting an imperial panegyric?",
    "answer": "THE SPEAKER LIES, BUT THE AUDIENCE FAVORS HIM EVEN THOUGH THEY KNOW HE’S LYING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The passage continues. Sī quis autem rogāret utrum tālis esse māllem quālis ille, an quālis ego tunc essem, ēligerem mē ipsum cūrīs cōnfectum — perversitāte, nōn vēritāte. The question: What question is Augustine unable to provide a logical answer to?",
    "answer": "WHETHER HE WOULD RATHER BE LIKE THE BEGGAR OR IN HIS CURRENT STATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Crassicius Pasicles wrote a commentary on what author, a native of Brescia who wrote a propempticon to Asinius Pollio and labored for 9 years to write the story of Myrrha and Cinyras in his Zmyrna?",
    "answer": "CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What fellow neoteric wrote an epicēdion for his wife Quintilia?",
    "answer": "LICINIUS CALVUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Cinna may have brought what Greek author to Rome, a friend of Cornelius Gallus whose Erōtica Pathēmata was supposedly written as a source of obscure myths for elegists?",
    "answer": "PARTHENIUS (OF NICAEA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Objects of what type were recovered from Maenalus by the Mantineans, found near a forge in Tegea by the Spartans, and brought to Troy after Helenus demanded that they be taken from the body of Pelops?",
    "answer": "BONES / SKELETONS (OF DEAD HEROES)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Around 475 B.C., on what island did the Athenian general Cimon claim to find the bones of Theseus, accurately reflecting their likely mythological location?",
    "answer": "SCYROS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological figure’s bones were recovered from Maenalus by the Mantineans?",
    "answer": "ARCAS(’S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What foreign ruler landed at Demetrias and was beaten by Acilius Glabrio despite Aetolian support, forcing him to retreat home and eventually agree to the Treaty of Apamea after losing at Magnesia?",
    "answer": "ANTIOCHUS {III // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During the Roman-Seleucid War, a Roman fleet off the coast of what town defeated a Seleucid fleet under the command of the Rhodian admiral Polyxenidas?",
    "answer": "MYONESSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Rhodian admiral fought on the Roman side at Myonessus after defeating a Phoenician navy under Hannibal at Side a month earlier?",
    "answer": "EUDAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English this sentence, with an extra clue after two readings: “Meā interest ea quibus opus nōn sit abesse.” [pause] Note that ea is the accusative subject of the infinitive.",
    "answer": "THERE IS NO NEED {BE ABSENT // NOT BE HERE}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence: “Manifestum est paucissimōs esse quī ratiōne quōquō modō ūtī possint.”",
    "answer": "IT IS {CLEAR / PLAIN} THAT THERE ARE VERY FEW (MEN) WHO CAN USE REASON IN ANY WAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence adapted from the Dē Bellō Cīvilī: “Ita loquitur Afrānius: nōn esse mīlitibus suīs ab eīs suscēnsendum, quod fidem ergā Pompēium cōnservāverint.”",
    "answer": "SOLDIERS FOR PRESERVING THEIR FAITH TOWARDS POMPEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After he dreamt that a woman asked him to give her a home at Anaphe, who threw the Triton-given gift of a clod of earth into the sea, then returned home with the Argonauts he had once saved with a dove?",
    "answer": "EUPHEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Euphemus was originally from what town at the tip of the Peloponnesus, which was celebrated as an entrance to the Underworld?",
    "answer": "TAENARUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Spartan leader led Euphemus’ descendants to the island Calliste, which he later renamed after himself?",
    "answer": "THERAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What ruler was slain by an Amal chieftain at the orders of the Eastern emperor who had made him patricius — Zeno — when his reign over Italy became troublesome in the 480s A.D.?",
    "answer": "ODO(V)ACER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeno had previously tried to take advantage of Theoderic the Amal by sending him against another Theoderic with what surname?",
    "answer": "STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name any of the Ostrogothic rulers who came after Theoderic and sought to prevent Justinian’s generals from recapturing Italy.",
    "answer": "THEODAHAD / VITIGIS / ILDEBAD / ERARIC / TOTILA / TEIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What fate was inflicted on Grunnius Corocotta in the Testāmentum Porcellī and on a gigantic gift given to Domitian, though he had to call a council to figure out just how to do so in Juvenal’s Fourth Satire?",
    "answer": "(BEING) {COOKED / EATEN}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What contemporary of Tiberius describes an ideal where “at the table no one will recognize what he is eating”?",
    "answer": "(M. GAVIUS) APICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Ausonius includes a description of the narrator giving instructions to a cook?",
    "answer": "EPHĒMERIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Used once after the verb form pudet by Tacitus, rarely with opus est, and often with the adjective dignus, what specific type of verb form is often found after adjectives like foedus and mīrābilis?",
    "answer": "ABLATIVE SUPINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a form of pudet, say in Latin “A shameful crime has been committed.”",
    "answer": "PUDENDUM {SCELUS / FACINUS} {COMMISSUM / FACTUM / PATRĀTUM} EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the most common construction with dignus, say in Latin: “She is worthy of being spared, but not forgiven.”",
    "answer": "DIGNA EST CUI PARCĀTUR, SED NŌN (CUI) IGNOSCĀTUR"
  },
    {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid est nōmen tibi? That is, what is your name?",
    "answer": "PLAYER SHOULD SAY THEIR NAME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid est nōmen moderātōrī?",
    "answer": "PLAYER SHOULD SAY THE MODERATOR’S NAME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid est nōmen magistrō tuō? Moderator should say: “Subsequent questions will count for points. Good luck and have fun!”",
    "answer": "CORRECT-SOUNDING]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scattered nuts and coins, a spelt cake called the farreum lībum, and a basket carried by a boy called the camillus are all objects found at what type of Roman marriage ceremony?",
    "answer": "CONFARREĀTIŌ [PROMPT ON “WEDDING” BEFORE “WHAT TYPE”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Roman confarreātiō, two children walked on each side of the bride and one in front, all of whom were required to be patrīmī et mātrīmī. What does this condition mean?",
    "answer": "THEIR FATHER AND MOTHER NEEDED TO BE LIVING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "During the dēductiō of the bride, what early form of Italian poetry was sung to the Sabine god Talassio?",
    "answer": "FESCENNINE VERSES // VERSŪS FESCENNĪNĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Excluding prefixes, the English word “kerchief” derives from what two Latin words, one of which means “to cover” and the other of which is at the root of “chief,” “precipitate” and “capitulate”? OPERIŌ and CAPUT",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what two Latin nouns do we derive “jeopardy”? IOCUS and PARS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what two Latin words do we derive “hidalgo”? (ALI)QUIS and FILIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who had to retrieve water from the Styx, fetch the beauty of Proserpina, and sort a room full of grain into piles, desperate to prove her love for her husband Cupid?",
    "answer": "PSYCHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Psyche was unable to organize the cereals by herself and instead relied on the help of what animals? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "ANT(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What object instructed Psyche on how to fetch Proserpina’s beauty from the Underworld?",
    "answer": "(A TALKING) TOWER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Works in what genre include a 135-section work by Jerome and the extant corpus of both Cornelius Nepos and Suetonius, all of whom wrote a Dē Virīs Illūstribus?",
    "answer": "BIOGRAPHY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to one of the biographies included in Suetonius’s collection, what author was born at Volaterrae and studied under Cornutus before publishing six works?",
    "answer": "PERSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to one of Jerome’s biographies, what early Latin Christian author “wrote a dialogue representing a discussion between a Christian and a Gentile,” the Octāvius?",
    "answer": "MINUCIUS FELIX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Deterred from adding new centuries of knights when a whetstone was cut with a razor, what king saw another miracle in his own house happen to a son of Ocrisia, an omen interpreted by Tanaquil?",
    "answer": "TARQUINIUS PRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The original three centuries of knights had been created by Romulus. Two of them were the Titiēs and Lūcērēs; what was the third?",
    "answer": "RAMNĒS / RAMNĒNSĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Tarquinius Priscus claimed the throne, he won the people’s favor with a speech defending his right to rule; in this speech, he mentioned the example of what man, who was killed at Lavinium?",
    "answer": "TITUS TATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What object indirectly caused a son of Portheus’s death, was built by Epeius, and was deceptively described as an offering to Minerva by Sinon, persuading Priam to welcome it?",
    "answer": "TROJAN HORSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between this son of Portheus and the most famous of the Spartoi, who fathered Pentheus by Agave?",
    "answer": "ECHION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During Sinon’s story, he claims that he was persecuted by Ulysses in alliance with what son of Thestor, who would later die of envy at a rival’s superior skill?",
    "answer": "CALCHAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Biological experiments are described as conducted either in vīvō or with what other Latin phrase, which denotes that they take place under artificial conditions and literally means “in glass”?",
    "answer": "IN VITRŌ [ACCEPT ENGLISH PRONUNCIATION]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin and English for the medical abbreviation q.s.",
    "answer": "{QUANTUM SATIS // QUANTUM SUFFICIT} – AS MUCH AS IS ENOUGH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While reading Caesar, you encounter the word hīberna and wonder how it means “winter-quarters.” You check the dictionary and find that part of the entry for hībernus reads “hīberna, ōrum, n. (sc. castra), winter-quarters.” What is the Latin for the abbreviation sc., and what does it mean in context? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "SCĪLICET, UNDERSTAND THAT THE FOLLOWING WORD IS IMPLIED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who occupied Cappadocia and Bithynia, executed Aquilius with molten gold, and ordered a massacre of 80,000 Romans in Asia in 88 B.C., leading to three wars against him and his kingdom of Pontus?",
    "answer": "MITHRIDATES {VI // THE GREAT // EUPATOR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general did Mithridates appoint to capture Greece on his behalf?",
    "answer": "ARCHELAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city did Archelaus capture with the help of a revolutionary named Aristion?",
    "answer": "ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Possibly from Pedum or Gabii, what “terse and elegant” author describes his love for Marathus and Nemesis in his elegies, which are often contrasted with those of Propertius?",
    "answer": "(ALBIUS) TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tibullus’s most famous lover is Delia, though. What was her real name?",
    "answer": "PLANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tibullus’s corpus also contains six poems addressed to Neaera by what man?",
    "answer": "LYGDAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following quote by Augustine into English: “Melius est reprehendant nōs grammaticī, quam nōn intellegant populī.” [pause] In Classical Latin this would have ut after melius est.",
    "answer": "// IT IS BETTER FOR THE GRAMMARIANS TO … THAN FOR THE PEOPLE TO …"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Rewrite that sentence to use infinitives rather than subjunctive verbs.",
    "answer": "MELIUS EST REPREHENDERE NŌS GRAMMATICŌS QUAM NŌN INTELLEGERE POPULŌS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this punning sentence by Augustine, expressing a similar sentiment: “In nostrā disertitūdine vōs dēsertī eritis.” Keep in mind that disertus and facundus are synonyms.",
    "answer": "IN OUR ELOQUENCE YOU (ALL) {WILL BE // WILL HAVE BEEN} {DESERTED / ABANDONED}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who covered the years 78 to 67 B.C. in a work that showed the fullest development of the inconcinnitās and Thucydidean style of his monographs, Bellum Iugurthīnum and Bellum Catilīnae?",
    "answer": "(C.) SALLUST(IUS CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What work of Tacitus takes remarkably direct inspiration from a battle depicted in the Bellum Iugurthīnum while describing the Battle of Mons Graupius?",
    "answer": "AGRICOLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Tacitus is noteworthy for having far less inconcinnitās and a much more smooth and flowing style than any of his other works?",
    "answer": "DIALOGUS DĒ ŌRĀTŌRIBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, a protege of Claudius Pompeianus and former schoolteacher, was asked to take the throne by Aemilius Laetus and Eclectus after his predecessor, Commodus, was murdered?",
    "answer": "PERTINAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Commodus was killed on the evening of December 31 in what year? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "192 A.D."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claudius Pompeianus had previously chosen to stay out of a plot against Commodus by Ummidius Quadratus, Appius Claudius Quintianus, and what woman?",
    "answer": "LUCILLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin using a gerund: “Nobody seemed to surpass Atalanta in running.”",
    "answer": "SUPERĀRE / VINCERE // ATALANTAE PRAESTĀRE / EXCELLERE}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin using a gerund: “Nothing is more useful for learning than leisure.”",
    "answer": "NIHIL DISCENDŌ ŪTILIUS EST {ŌTIŌ // QUAM ŌTIUM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two compounds of eō — one as a gerund, the other as a gerundive — say in Latin: “With hope of returning having been removed, we will be prepared to undergo dangers.”",
    "answer": "PARĀBIMUR} AD PERICULA SUBEUNDA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two Latin adjectives are technically neither singular nor plural, but dual, as evidenced by endings like -ōbus and their meanings of “both” and “two,” respectively? AMBŌ and DUO [ACCEPT IN EITHER ORDER]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "If I say that I have ter dēnī of something, how many do I have?",
    "answer": "30 / THIRTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using the same formula for multiplication, say “four times two.”",
    "answer": "QUATER BĪNĪ [ALSO ACCEPT BIS QUATERNĪ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Courted by both Poseidon and Apollo, what deity rejected their advances and swore an oath of chastity that earned her the right to be worshiped in every home and temple’s hearth?",
    "answer": "HESTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why is Hestia known as both the first- and last-born of Cronus and Rhea?",
    "answer": "SHE WAS THE FIRST TO BE BORN BUT LAST TO BE DISGORGED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Similarly, what daughter of Daedalion was pursued by both Apollo and Hermes?",
    "answer": "CHIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the following verbs, which describes an action most likely performed by a stella: pugnō, luctor, micō, hiemō?",
    "answer": "MICŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of these represents an action most likely undertaken by an ancilla: equitō, mīlitō, dīmicō, dēspoliō, ministrō?",
    "answer": "MINISTRŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the following verbs, which two represent an action most likely undertaken by a medīcus: sānō, medeor, lacessō, sepeliō, flagellō? SĀNŌ and MEDEOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What victor at Idistaviso, after being sent to Asia and quarreling with the governor of Syria, suddenly died in 19 A.D., leaving his wife Agrippina the Elder to bring his ashes to his uncle Tiberius? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "GERMANICUS (JULIUS CAESAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this governor of Syria?",
    "answer": "(CN. CALPURNIUS) PISO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Shortly before his death, Germanicus had provoked controversy by going on a tour of what place, which Augustus had forbidden senators from entering?",
    "answer": "EGYPT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author was an informer for Nero and the last man he appointed consul, but later began worshiping busts of Vergil and slavishly imitating him in a 17-book epic, Pūnica?",
    "answer": "(TIB. CATIUS ASCONIUS) SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Flavian poet composed an epic poem on frāternae aciēs with the aim of following its model, the Aeneid, “at a distance”?",
    "answer": "(P. PAPINIUS) STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet hailing from Setia was a decemvir who adapted the work of a Hellenistic epic poet?",
    "answer": "(C.) VALERIUS FLACCUS (BALBUS SETINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What god fell hopelessly in love with Orchamus’s daughter Leucothoe and spurned Clytie, who transformed into a heliotrope pining after him?",
    "answer": "SOL / APOLLO / HELIOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Leucothoe was buried alive by her father for her love, but Sol transformed her into what type of tree after sprinkling her grave with nectar?",
    "answer": "FRANKINCENSE (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The story of Sol and Leucothoe was told by what king’s daughters, who scorned the orgiastic rites of Bacchus in favor of their weaving?",
    "answer": "MINYAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When recognized by the spotter, perform the following command: Surge et ambulā in angulum pariētum.",
    "answer": "PLAYER GETS UP AND WALKS INTO A CORNER OF THE ROOM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform the following command, in celebration of the return of in-person spotter questions: Dīc esse bibendum et tunc pede līberō pulsā tellūrem.",
    "answer": "BEATS THE GROUND WITH THEIR FOOT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform the following command: Fūnēs māchinae signatōriae leviter quatite. Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "ROUND TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sort of animal prevented Ancaeus from tasting his wine, forced Nestor to spear-vault into a tree, gave a scar that Eurycleia recognized on Odysseus, and terrorized Mt. Erymanthus?",
    "answer": "BOAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Odysseus had gotten his scar while hunting with what maternal grandfather of his?",
    "answer": "AUTOLYCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Heracles manage to capture the Erymanthian boar?",
    "answer": "CHASED IT INTO SNOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author depicted the complaint of a walnut tree in Nux, invoked a coprophilic bird in the Ībis, and wrote Epistulae ex Pontō — Letters from the Black Sea — and Trīstia to lament his exile at Tomi?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) OVID(IUS NASO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What work of “civil poetry” by Ovid is a poetical calendar meant to illustrate the myths and customs of Latium?",
    "answer": "FĀSTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Fāstī may have drawn on the research of what grammarian from Praeneste?",
    "answer": "(M.) VERRIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun, a cognate of the first part of Iuppiter, is regularly feminine when used of a specific or fixed time, but is otherwise one of the only fifth-declension nouns to be masculine?",
    "answer": "DIĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grammatical term refers to nouns that vary in gender, such as diēs and epulum?",
    "answer": "HETEROGENEOUS / HETEROGENE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What masculine noun regularly becomes neuter in the plural except when it means “topics of argument” or “passages from books”?",
    "answer": "LOCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin term for the system, made official in 180 B.C. by the Lēx Villia, which was circumvented by ambitious generals like Pompey who ignored the established prerequisites for holding offices.",
    "answer": "CURSUS HONŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who had started his career well before the minimum age requirements, was found mysteriously dead in 129 B.C., perhaps due to foul play from his wife Sempronia?",
    "answer": "(P. CORNELIUS) SCIPIO AEMILIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pompey was able to flout age and rank requirements due to the personal loyalty of his army, many of whom came from what specific region in Northeast Italy?",
    "answer": "PICENUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following Latin sentence into English: “Nisi Iūnōnem laesisset, Aenēās tot labōrēs nōn subīsset.” Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "UNDERGONE SO MANY {LABORS / TOILS / HARDSHIPS}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of conditional would be used to say “If he were to hurt Juno, Aeneas would go through many labors”?",
    "answer": "HURTING… WOULD BE GOING…”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the following sentence: “Sī quaerās cur vēnerim, nihil aliud dīcam quam mē vēnisse ut certāmen lūderem.”",
    "answer": "OTHER THAN THAT I CAME TO PLAY CERTAMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet popularized a philosopher from Messina, criticized the faunī vātēsque who had written in Saturnians, and used his Hedyphaegetica and Annālēs to introduce dactylic hexameter?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ennius versified the Aetolian campaign of Fulvius Nobilior with what fābula praetexta, his only known one aside from Sabinae?",
    "answer": "AMBRACIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What controversial claim did that philosopher from Messina, Euhemerus, make about the gods?",
    "answer": "FROM STORIES OF MORTALS [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Iliad, what Trojan ally tells a story involving the Solymi and the treachery of Anteia, then exchanges his 100-oxen-worth golden armor with the bronze armor of Diomedes?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Diomedes opens their conversation by telling the story of how Lycurgus persecuted what god and his “nurses,” beating them with an ox-goad?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, surnamed Alcyone, features in a story about her husband and the Curetes told by Phoenix in Book 9 of the Iliad?",
    "answer": "CLEOPATRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb do we derive “jocund,” “aid,” and “adjutant,” the latter two of which are also clearly related to it in meaning?",
    "answer": "IUVŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Iuvō is at the root of the second half of “Gatorade,” whose spelling was changed to avoid marketing it as a medicinal beverage. What Latin noun gives us the first half of “Gatorade” and the word “lizard”?",
    "answer": "LACERTUS / LACERTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“Gatorade” is a near rhyme with “Renegade,” the name of a popular TikTok song. “Renegade” obviously derives from negō, which is cognate with what defective Latin verb?",
    "answer": "AIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb oblīviscor, give the 3rd person singular, imperfect subjunctive.",
    "answer": "OBLĪVISCERĒTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb ulciscor, give the 2nd person plural, pluperfect subjunctive. Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "ULTĪ ESSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb ōrdior, give the same form.",
    "answer": "ŌRSĪ ESSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Disgruntled at his treatment in Antioch, what late emperor unwisely hastened across the Tigris River to face Shapur II, only to be killed near Ctesiphon, possibly by a Christian in his own ranks?",
    "answer": "JULIAN (THE APOSTATE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what philosophical school, promoted by Plotinus and Porphyry and common among pagans in the late Empire, did Julian adhere?",
    "answer": "NEO-PLATONISM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Julian’s predecessor, Constantius II, had won a major battle at Mursa against what usurper, who had overthrown his brother Constans?",
    "answer": "MAGNENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two Latin forms, which can be found before adjectives like necessārius to form their two-word comparatives and superlatives, are the comparative and superlative adverbs of magnus? MAGIS and MAXIMĒ",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Make the comparative adjective prior superlative.",
    "answer": "PRĪMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What are the two superlatives for the comparative adjective īnferior? ĪNFIMUS and ĪMUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, whose work was parodied by Eumolpus in the Satyricon, condemns the protagonists of his epic while praising Cato the Younger as a Stoic hero in the war between Caesar and Pompey?",
    "answer": "(M. ANNAEUS) LUCAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What protagonist, traveling alongside Giton, hears Eumolpus’s poetry in the Satyricon?",
    "answer": "ENCOLPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "One of Lucan’s sources may be the lost Histories of what grandfather of his?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who executed his predecessor’s architect Apollodorus of Damascus and generals Palma and Quietus, set up a cult for a drowned Bithynian youth, and connected the Solway Firth to the Tyne with a wall?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hadrian was said to have become emperor thanks to the intervention of what woman, Trajan’s wife?",
    "answer": "(POMPEIA) PLOTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Apollodorus of Damascus angered Hadrian by criticizing what large temple, whose construction the emperor supervised between the Colosseum and the Temple of Peace?",
    "answer": "(TEMPLE OF) VENUS AND ROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: This question has an extra clue. Which of these provinces was located furthest west: Pannonia Superior, Galatia, Crēta et Cȳrēnaica, and Armenia Maior? It bordered Dalmatia.",
    "answer": "PANNONIA SUPERIOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What modern-day country did the Romans call Cȳrēnaica? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "LIBYA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name either of the Roman provinces that lay to the south of Galatia, bordering on the Mediterranean Sea, when the empire was at its furthest extent around 117 A.D.. LYCIA & PAMPHYLIA or CILICIA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity, mocked for the obscurity of her father Coeus by a sister of Pelops, was most offended by the idea that seven sons and seven daughters were better than her twins, Apollo and Artemis?",
    "answer": "LETO [ACCEPT “LATONA” BEFORE “ARTEMIS,” SINCE THE STORY IS FROM OVID]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Ovid’s account, Niobe interrupted a sacrifice to Latona that was set up by what daughter of Tiresias, said to rival her father in the gift of prophecy?",
    "answer": "MANTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Coeus also fathered what other deity, who was pursued by Zeus and turned into a quail?",
    "answer": "ASTERIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who defeated Egyptians at Panium, alarming Pergamum, and allied with the Aetolians against Rome, though defeats at Myonessus and Magnesia severely harmed his Seleucid Empire?",
    "answer": "ANTIOCHUS {III // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What consul, under whom Cato served as military tribune, defeated Antiochus at Thermopylae?",
    "answer": "(M.’) ACILIUS GLABRIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What naval commander from an island off the coast of Anatolia was put in command of Antiochus’ main fleet during the subsequent war?",
    "answer": "POLYXENIDAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The words “tolle, lege” encouraged what author to abandon Manichaeism, which he had pursued after reading Cicero’s Hortēnsius, and write his Christian autobiography, the Confessions?",
    "answer": "(ST.) AUGUSTINE // (AURELIUS) AUGUSTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what work does Augustine respond to accusations after Alaric’s sack of Rome that Christianity was causing the Roman Empire’s disintegration?",
    "answer": "DĒ CĪVITĀTE DEĪ / CITY OF GOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name both of Augustine’s parents, one a pagan local official at Thagaste, the other a devout Christian whose death is told very movingly in Book 9 of the Confessions. PATRICIUS and MONICA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological pair, who met at Marathon when one tried to steal the other’s cattle, together carried off the queen Antiope and were trapped in the underworld by the Chairs of Forgetfulness? THESEUS and P(E)IRITHOUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the wife of Pirithous that was abducted by the centaur Eurytion at their wedding?",
    "answer": "HIPPODAMIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Theseus and Pirithous kidnapped Helen, to what city in Attica did they take her?",
    "answer": "APHIDNAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Phrases meaning “from that point,” and “at that time,” “what news?,” and “two thousand soldiers” — inde locī, id temporis, quid novī, and duo mīlia mīlitum — all exhibit what use of the genitive? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is often seen in words like capitis, maiestātis, and repetundārum?",
    "answer": "CHARGE / PENALTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive can be replaced by a prepositional phrase with ergā?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Vergil describes Dido’s flight from Tyre in book 1 of the Aeneid, he emphasizes her remarkable ability to organize the plan with what three-word phrase meaning “a woman was the leader of the deed”?",
    "answer": "DUX FĒMINA FACTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In book 6, the Sibyl warns Aeneas that entering the underworld is much easier than escaping with what three-word phrase? Nowadays, it idiomatically means “once you do this, there’s no turning back.”",
    "answer": "FACILIS DĒSCENSUS {AVERNŌ / AVERNĪ}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What far-north island fills in the blank of the Vergilian phrase ultima [blank], which is used today to describe any place that feels like an exciting or novel frontier? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "ROUND THREE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work, in which Photis bungles a potion, features the inset tale of Cupid and Psyche as heard by its protagonist, Lucius, while in the form of a donkey?",
    "answer": "(APULEIUS’S) METAMORPHŌSĒS / ASINUS AUREUS / THE GOLDEN ASS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Metamorphōsēs has a surprise ending where Lucius is initiated into the cult of what deity?",
    "answer": "ISIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Apuleius was persuaded to marry Pudentilla by what friend of his, who was her son?",
    "answer": "PONTIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: “Sīs fortior patre meō, cuius digitus in bellō caesus est.”",
    "answer": "(MAY YOU) BE BRAVER THAN MY FATHER, WHOSE FINGER WAS CUT (OFF) IN WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this one: “Cum crūs amīsisset, tamen decem mīlia passuum Rōmam cucurrit.”",
    "answer": "ALTHOUGH HE HAD LOST HIS LEG, NEVERTHELESS HE RAN TEN MILES TO ROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence adapted from Pliny the Elder: “Multum ad tuam glōriam rēfert, in quālēs tua virtūs casūs inciderit.”",
    "answer": "INTO WHAT SORT OF CIRCUMSTANCES YOUR VIRTUE HAS FALLEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wondered why his head-sheep was lagging behind the rest of the flock, not realizing that the sheep was hiding his antagonist Outis, or “No-one,” who had blinded him?",
    "answer": "POLYPHEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To weaken Polyphemus, Odysseus used the wine he got from what priest of Apollo at Ismarus?",
    "answer": "MARON"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What son of Eurymus had warned Polyphemus that someone named Odysseus would wound him?",
    "answer": "TELEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, where a massacre was perpetrated in 215 A.D. by Caracalla, saw so-called “Donations” to Alexander Helios and the other children of Marc Antony by its queen, Cleopatra?",
    "answer": "ALEXANDRIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name both Alexander Helios’s twin sister and their brother who was born a few years later. CLEOPATRA SELENE and PTOLEMY PHILADELPHUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general of Antony won a victory at Mt. Gindarus against the Parthians in 38 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(P.) VENTIDIUS (BASSUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the words dēlūbrum, fānum, aedēs in the singular, and templum?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun, mostly synonymous with nemus, is used to refer to a grove or consecrated wood?",
    "answer": "LŪCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Etymologically, what is a nūmen, which metaphorically refers to divine power? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "A NOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Reproached for a style of “sand without lime” by Caligula, who nearly condemned him to death, what author described the daily practice of Stoicism to his friend Lucilius in 124 Epistulae Mōrālēs?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Seneca wrote nine surviving works of what type of fābula, which are the only extant representatives of the genre, since Pacuvius and Accius are lost?",
    "answer": "FĀBULA(E) {COTHURNĀTA(E) / CRĒPIDĀTA(E)}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Seneca’s tragedies, which shares its title with Ennius’s final work, is the only one without an extant Greek model?",
    "answer": "THYESTĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the verbs suādeō, dēficiō, ignoscō, īrascor, and faveō, which does NOT take the dative, even though its meaning of “fail” might suggest that?",
    "answer": "DĒFICIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good Latin using parcō: “They are not spared.” You will need an impersonal passive.",
    "answer": "EĪS NŌN PARCITUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good Latin using mīnor: “I threaten them with death.”",
    "answer": "EĪS MORTEM MĪNOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though he did nothing for his wife and daughter Prisca and Valeria, who was forced into a conference at Carnuntum in 308 when Galerius requested that he come out of retirement at Split?",
    "answer": "DIOCLETIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What modern day country was the home of Diocletian during his retirement?",
    "answer": "CROATIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Diocletian’s death, Valeria and Prisca soon ended up at the court of what Caesar, who was defeated by Licinius and died in 313 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MAXIMINUS {DAIA / DAZA}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the classical equivalent of the form dūcier, which could be used in the sentences “He believed that he was being led to his death” or “He did not want to be led to his death.”",
    "answer": "DŪCĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the primary Latin form equivalent to the alternate form abūtēre, which appears in a famous Latin sentence.",
    "answer": "ABŪTĒRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the primary Latin form equivalent to the alternate form levassō.",
    "answer": "LEVĀVERŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group, which applied a name meaning “Beginner of Death” to an infant, included a man who tried to cannibalize Melanippus and a seer whose wife Eriphyle forced him to join Adrastus?",
    "answer": "SEVEN AGAINST THEBES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this infant, who died at Nemea when he was left in a bed of parsley?",
    "answer": "OPHELTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What old king of Argos, the father of Evadne, advised Polynices to bribe Eriphyle with the necklace of Harmonia? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "IPHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun, in two very similar quotes by Vergil and Terence, follows either audentīs or fortīs and is said to “favor” them?",
    "answer": "FORTŪNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Give the idiomatic meaning of the Juvenalian quote frontis nulla fidēs. Note that frontis is an objective genitive.",
    "answer": "YOU SHOULDN’T TRUST APPEARANCES [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the idiomatic meaning of this quote from Horace about the nature of travel: caelum nōn animum mūtant quī trans mare currunt.",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek work inspired the plot of Niptra by Pacuvius and was translated after 272 B.C. by a Tarentine grammāticus named Livius Andronicus?",
    "answer": "ODYSSEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What schoolteacher in the late Republic was known for forcing his students to learn Livius Andronicus and beating them when they failed?",
    "answer": "(L.) ORBILIUS (PUPILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which other play of Pacuvius also featured Ulysses as a key character?",
    "answer": "ARMŌRUM IŪDICIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Marcius Rex built the first high-level variety of what piece of infrastructure in 140 B.C., whose other examples include the Appia and the Tepula, known for its lukewarm waters?",
    "answer": "AQUEDUCT(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Augustus built the Aqua Alsietīna to host mock naval battles known by what Latin term?",
    "answer": "NAUMACHIA(E)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between two aqueducts, one made during the reign of Claudius, which are surnamed Vetus and Nōvus?",
    "answer": "(AQUA) ANIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who escaped to Camicus but was revealed when he passed a thread through a seashell, showing the same ingenuity as when he designed a hollow bull for Pasiphae and built the Labyrinth?",
    "answer": "DAEDALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the king of Camicus who sheltered Daedalus? His daughters soon killed Minos by scalding him in his bath.",
    "answer": "COCALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another account says that, after Icarus’s death, Daedalus arrived in what city, where he decorated a temple with the story of his life, though “his fatherly hands twice fell” when he tried to paint Icarus?",
    "answer": "CUMAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between a consul who died at Cape Telamon and the co-consul of Manlius Vulso who invaded Africa but was soon locked in a spiky box and killed by the Carthaginians? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "(ATILIUS) REGULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cape Telamon came a year after the Romans signed a treaty with the Carthaginians setting their Spanish borders at what geographical feature?",
    "answer": "{EBRO / HIBERUS} RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After what naval battle in 255 B.C., the year of Regulus’s capture, was the victorious Roman fleet annihilated by a storm?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) CAPE HERMAEUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man was accused of trying to murder an Alexandrian envoy and poison his lover Clodia, leading to a slew of invective being delivered against her when Cicero defended him in a 56 B.C. speech?",
    "answer": "(M.) CAELIUS (RUFUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Cicero’s skill with invective was also displayed in his attacks on what freedman of Sulla in one of his early speeches?",
    "answer": "CHRYSOGONUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what speech, delivered in the interim between two of the Catilinarians, does Cicero humorously parody Cato the Younger’s Stoic beliefs while defending a client accused of electoral corruption?",
    "answer": "PRŌ MŪRĒNĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What river, a dry imitation of which was seen at Buthrotum, earned the wrath of Hephaestus and was scorched because it tried to drown Achilles on the Trojan plain?",
    "answer": "SCAMANDER / XANTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why had Scamander tried to drown Achilles?",
    "answer": "ACHILLES WAS FILLING HIS WATERS WITH CORPSES [ACCEPT OBV. EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scamander was actually the progenitor of the Trojan race through what son, said in other accounts to have immigrated from Crete?",
    "answer": "TEUCER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin word for “to fold” refers to a person who assists or partners with another in committing a crime?",
    "answer": "ACCOMPLICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of plicō is a synonym of the English word “braid”?",
    "answer": "PLEAT/PLAIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words “comply,” “supply,” “reply,” and “apply,” which two derive from plicō? REPLY and APPLY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: there will be an extra clue. Say in the best classical Latin: “I ran to the Forum of Augustus to see bigger temples.” Know that purpose clauses with a comparative are introduced by quō.",
    "answer": "TEMPLA VĪSUM // AD MAIŌRA TEMPLA VIDENDA}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A purpose clause introduced by quō is really a relative clause of purpose, where quō exemplifies what use of the ablative? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "DEGREE OF DIFFERENCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in the best classical Latin: “I do not doubt that there are more temples in the Forum than in the Campus Martius.”",
    "answer": "TEMPLŌRUM SIT} IN FORŌ QUAM (IN) CAMPŌ MARTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By wearing a cast to conceal a dagger and falsely promising to give the emperor a list of conspirators before stabbing him in the groin, what former butler was able to assassinate Domitian?",
    "answer": "STEPHANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This conspiracy also may have involved Domitian’s wife Domitia. She was the daughter of what man, a star general in the East under Nero?",
    "answer": "(CN. DOMITIUS) CORBULO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The conspiracy also involved what Praetorian Prefect, whom Nerva reluctantly executed? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "SEMIFINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What case and number is lacking in words like faex and cor, has two possible forms in words like aetās or cīvitās, and in one of the declensions features the same vowel repeated twice in a row?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE PLURAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Greek genitive plural ending, which is sometimes used with titles of works like the Georgics or the Metamorphoses?",
    "answer": "-ŌN / -ΩΝ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Greek genitive singular ending of Styx?",
    "answer": "STYGOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A man with what cognōmen wrote a Saturnian line beginning “dabunt malum” before securing the exile to Utica of the author who had claimed that his family became consuls by fate?",
    "answer": "METELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Naevius’s line “fātō Metellī Rōmae fīunt cōnsulēs” is preserved in a commentary on Cicero’s Verrines falsely ascribed to what scholar, who wrote five extant commentaries on Cicero speeches?",
    "answer": "(Q.) ASCONIUS (PEDIANUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Plautine play alludes to an imprisoned poet, perhaps referencing Naevius?",
    "answer": "MĪLES GLŌRIŌSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who asked Zeus to make her son’s body never decay, even though his desire to marry a princess from Pessinus caused her to drive her son Attis mad and make him castrate himself?",
    "answer": "CYBELE / AGDISTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "From what sort of tree, which also grew on the grave of a Thracian princess loved by Demophon, was Attis’s mom Nana impregnated?",
    "answer": "ALMOND (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Tantalus carved an image of Cybele on a rock near Mt. Sipylus?",
    "answer": "BROTEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, the mother of Iullus and Antyllus, navigated a trifecta of political marriages to populāris partisans before allying with her brother-in-law Lucius Antonius during the Perusine War?",
    "answer": "FULVIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the first and second husbands of Fulvia, in order. (P.) CLODIUS PULCHER and (C.) SCRIBONIUS CURIO",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scribonius Curio had died when he was sent to Africa to fight Juba I and what Roman governor?",
    "answer": "(P.) ATTIUS VARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what general category of meaning do the words conger, fiber, ēricius, pāpiliō, and ānser belong?",
    "answer": "ANIMALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by pērniciēs and strāgēs? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "DESTRUCTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by adȳtum and penētrāle?",
    "answer": "SANCTUARY // INNER CHAMBER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work, of which Pseudaeneas, Crās Crēdō Hodiē Nihil, and Sexagēsis are parts, was inspired by a philosopher from Gadara and written in 150 books of mixed prose and verse by Varro Reatinus?",
    "answer": "(VARRO REATINUS’S) SATURAE MENIPPEAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group was attacked in the Trikaranos, one of the Menippean Satires?",
    "answer": "FIRST TRIUMVIRATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, a personification of an abstract concept, appears in a Menippean Satire composed shortly after the fall of the Western Empire, wearing a garment that many people have torn pieces from?",
    "answer": "PHILOSOPHY / PHILOSOPHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of soldiers proved ineffective at Panormus in 250 B.C. and later at Naragarra, where lanes were opened to allow these “Lucanian oxen” to harmlessly charge, unlike at Heraclea under Pyrrhus?",
    "answer": "ELEPHANT(S) // MEN CONTROLLING ELEPHANTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "As the Carthaginians marched towards Lake Trasimene in 217 B.C., how many elephants did Hannibal have left in his force?",
    "answer": "ONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Livy, what Roman consul in 169 B.C. had to devise a complicated contraption to get elephants down Mount Olympus during a perilous 11-day march in the Third Macedonian War?",
    "answer": "(Q.) MARCIUS (PHILIPPUS) // (Q. MARCIUS) PHILIPPUS [LIVY AUC 44.5]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word is the first word in the official Roman name of Gloucester, as well as that of Colchester and that of Cologne, referring to their status as Roman settlements in captured territory?",
    "answer": "COLŌNIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the shortened, one-word name of Gloucester.",
    "answer": "GLEVUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What county town in today’s East Midlands was known to the Romans as Colōnia Lindum?",
    "answer": "LINCOLN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device is seen in the phrase “quod ā cultū atque hūmānitāte prōvinciae longissimē absunt,” where the nouns cultū atque hūmānitāte are like the noun-adjective pair hūmānō cultū? [cf. Amm. 15.11.4, which paraphrases the sentence and says “ab hūmāniōre cultū”]",
    "answer": "HENDIADYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Besides the fact that cornus is metonymy for “javelin,” what literary device is seen in the line “pariter effūdit lacrimās cornumque sonantem”?",
    "answer": "ZEUGMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device is seen in the lines “nātumque in valle reductā [...] tālibus adfāta est dictīs sēque obtulit ultrō”?",
    "answer": "HYSTERON PROTERON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What land, through which the Phasis river flows, has a capital at Aea where a Thessalian foreigner fought men who sprung out of the ground and yoked two bulls who breathed fire? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "COLCHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The night before Jason, the Thessalian foreigner, completed the tasks, he performed a sacrifice to Hecate, calling her by what name?",
    "answer": "BRIMO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Medea had completely dismembered Absyrtus, Aeetes picked up the various body parts and buried them in what city, whose name derives from the “cuttings” of his body? TOMI [FROM τέμνω, CUT]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What man, granted commission over a revolt in Faesulae to stop him from undoing Sulla’s reforms in his 78 B.C. consulship, started a revolt soon suppressed by Lutatius Catulus at Milvian Bridge?",
    "answer": "MARCUS AEMILIUS LEPIDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, the loser at Lauro River, absorbed the remnants of the Lepidus rebellion?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) SERTORIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where was Lepidus’s ally, Junius Brutus, defeated by Pompey in 77 B.C.?",
    "answer": "MUTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author of a historical work spending 41 books on Augustus’s reign and a treatise proposing three new letters for the alphabet studied under a native of Patavium — Livy — before becoming emperor?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Claudius also defended Cicero against the son of what author, a notoriously critical native of Teate?",
    "answer": "(C.) ASINIUS POLLIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who was the protagonist of Nero’s Troica, a retelling of the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "PARIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into Latin: “Are you afraid to trust the words of the witness?”",
    "answer": "TIMĒS(NE) VERBĪS TESTIS CRĒDERE?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in the best Latin: “I said these things so that you would never think that you had been betrayed.”",
    "answer": "HAEC DĪXĪ NĒ UMQUAM PUTĀRĒS TĒ PRODITUM ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in the best classical Latin: “It will be allowed for me to be lazy provided that I work today.”",
    "answer": "MODO // TANTUM / ITA UT} HODIĒ LABŌREM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who gave the Balyra river its name after he threw an instrument into it, since after he lost a contest at Dorium in an attempt to lie with the Muses, he was stripped of his musical talent and sight??",
    "answer": "PHILAMMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “amenity” and “amenable,” the second of which is cognate with “demeanor” and “promenade.” AMOENUS (PLEASANT) and {MĪNOR (THREATEN) / MĪNAE (THREATS)}, RESPECTIVELY Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “toil” meaning “hard work” and the rare word “toil” meaning “net,” the second of which is cognate with “toilet.” TUNDŌ (BEAT) and {TEXŌ (WEAVE) / TĒLA (WEB)}, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “scourge” and “scour,” the second of which is cognate with “proxy.” CŌRIUM (SKIN) and CŪRA (CARE), RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following sentences adapted from Cicero, which I shall read twice, then answer in Latin the question that follows. There will be another clue after the question. Putō Crassum nōn moritūrum fuisse, sī huic ōminī pāruisset: cum ad Syriam proficīscerētur, quīdam mercātor, fīcōs vēndēns urbe Caunō dēlātās, clāmitābat “Cauneās! Cauneās!” Monitus est hōc ōmine Crassus, cavēret nē īret. The question: Quid ēvēnisset Crassō, sī ōminī pāruisset? [pause] Your answer should contain a verb in the pluperfect subjunctive.",
    "answer": "[ALSO ACCEPT “NN MORITŪRUS FUIT // VĪCTŪRUS FUIT” ETC. BEFORE THE HINT]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The word shouted by the merchant, Cauneae, is a proper adjective used as a substantive. What did the merchant intend for it to mean?",
    "answer": "FIGS FROM (THE CITY OF) CAUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The last sentence of the passage suggests that the exclamation of “Cauneās!” was taken as an omen because it sounded like what three-word phrase addressed to Crassus? You have forty seconds.",
    "answer": "CAVĒ NĒ EĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a 170-chapter work, who gives charms to cure a dislocation and advises selling both scrap metal and old slaves, showing rustic wisdom mixed with the ultra-conservative values he displayed as censor?",
    "answer": "(M. PORCIUS) CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What imperial author extensively draws upon the Catonian ideal of a vir bonus dīcendī perītus in the 12th and final book of his magnum opus?",
    "answer": "(M. FABIUS) QUINTILIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Cato refused to name major commanders in his Orīginēs, he did name what valiant soldier, whose brave deeds he compared to Leonidas in one of the extant fragments of the work?",
    "answer": "(Q.) CAEDICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Macareus exclaimed “Why does a Trojan vessel now carry a Greek?” on seeing what son of Adamastus, who joined Aeneas’s crew after Ulysses left him at Polyphemus’s island?",
    "answer": "ACHAEMENIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Near the land of the Cyclopes, the crew notices smoking Mt. Etna, which was said to have buried what giant struck down by Athena after fleeing Sicily during the Gigantomachy?",
    "answer": "ENCELADUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After sailing away from the Cyclopes, the crew immediately arrives at what island at the entrance to the bay of Syracuse, to which the river Alpheius had once found a way from Elis to pursue Arethusa? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "ORTYGIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What military office created by Gallienus, which Probus and Aurelian held before becoming emperor, shares its name with a position held by Aebutius Elva in 496 B.C. and by Minucius Rufus in 217 B.C.?",
    "answer": "COMMANDER” BEFORE “SHARES ITS NAME”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the late empire, Stilicho rose to what supreme military office, which commanded both the cavalry and the infantry?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER UTRĪUSQUE MĪLITIAE // MASTER OF EACH ARMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Alaric first threatened Rome, he was similarly made magister utrīusque mīlitiae, while what brother-in-law of his became Count of the Domestics? Moderator should say: “All challenges on toss-ups 1 through 19 must be resolved before toss-up 20 is read. If any players or coaches would like to lodge a challenge, please speak up now.”",
    "answer": "ATHAULF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following Latin phrases is most similar to clāvam extorquēre Herculī in its idiomatic meaning: oleum addere camīnō, ab asinō lānam, in flagrante dēlictō, cum tacent clāmant?",
    "answer": "AB ASINŌ LANAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin phrase plays off of dating systems to express that something is not possible and emphatically means “never”?",
    "answer": "AD KALENDĀS GRAECĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other Latin phrase, which literally means “you are weaving a little rope out of sand,” is also used to indicate the pursuit of something impossible? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“Who was Hecuba’s mother?” was a trivia question proposed to guests by what emperor, whose reign saw the revolt of Florus and Sacrovir and the victories of Dolabella and Blaesus over Tacfarinas?",
    "answer": "TIBERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What 3-word Latin phrase, similar but not identical to a famous quote from tragedy, did Tiberius supposedly use as his motto?",
    "answer": "ODERINT DUM PROBENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Like Julius Florus and Julius Sacrovir, what two chiefs of the Treveri, both of whom have Julius in their name, later worked with Julius Civilis to rebel against Vespasian? JULIUS CLASSICUS and JULIUS TUTOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words “parody,” “disparage,” “apparel,” and “pair,” which does not belong, because it does not even derive from Latin?",
    "answer": "PARODY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words “satire,” “imposthume,” “affidavit,” “ague,” and “ditty,” which does not derive from Latin?",
    "answer": "IMPOSTHUME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the military ranks “admiral,” “colonel,” “sergeant,” “commodore,” and “lieutenant,” which does not derive from Latin, since it comes from an Arabic word for a military leader?",
    "answer": "ADMIRAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Iliad, who vowed to sacrifice a hundred lambs before striking a dove to win the archery contest at Patroclus’ funeral games, after which he returned to his homeland Crete alongside Idomeneus?",
    "answer": "MERIONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What item from Eleon did Meriones give to Odysseus, which was originally stolen by Odysseus’ grandfather Autolycus?",
    "answer": "AMYNTOR’S HELMET [PROMPT ON “HELMET”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Meriones was responsible for some of the most cruel wounds in the Iliad. Who was the builder of Paris’ ship who was struck in the right buttock?",
    "answer": "PHERECLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Writing perhaps to celebrate Claudius’ invasion of Britain, what author provides fabulous descriptions of distant or scarcely known regions in his Dē Sitū Orbis or Chōrographia?",
    "answer": "POMPONIUS MELA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Upon what first-century Greek geographer from Amasea did Pomponius base much of his work?",
    "answer": "STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What historical figure, who is better known for his military and political exploits, drew up a gigantic map of the entire world accompanied by commentāriī? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "(MARCUS VIPSANIUS) AGRIPPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words spūma, glaeba, manicae, plānitiēs, and alvus, which is being described in the following sentence: Cum salum aestuet, hanc māteriem albam in marī videās.",
    "answer": "SPŪMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words frūx, favīlla, formīdō, frūstum, and fūcus, which is being described in the following sentence: Est māteriēs ātra et saepe incandēscēns quae post incendium superest.",
    "answer": "FAVĪLLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words ammentum, acerra, anhēlitus, annōna, and antemna, which is being described in the following sentence: Hoc saepe, ut Ovidiānīs verbīs ūtar, “ē lassō venit ōre” Harvard 2022 Adv Fin Customs Visual",
    "answer": "ANHĒLITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "I will now hand out materials for a visual question. At my signal, you will have 15 seconds to open and examine them, after which I will read the question. Pictured are examples of four types of Roman wall construction techniques, which are all named a different type of opus. Please identify the type of opus exemplified by panel A, named for its resemblance to a net.",
    "answer": "(OPUS) RĒTICULĀTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the type of opus exemplified by panel B, named for the haphazard placement of the uncut stones that make it up.",
    "answer": "(OPUS) INCERTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the type of opus exemplified by panel D, named for a Roman province featuring many examples of it on monumental works.",
    "answer": "(OPUS) AFRICĀNUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What genre did Cicero hope would be an opus ōrātōrium maximē, criticizing writers such as Gaius Fannius and Licinius Macer while giving higher praise to Coelius Antipater’s 7-book monograph?",
    "answer": "HISTORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Fannius was the son-in-law of what man, a member of the Scipionic Circle who, like Scipio himself, was accused of writing Terence’s comedies for him?",
    "answer": "(C.) LAELIUS (SAPIENS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In the same passage of Cicero, he remarks that what Roman historian “endeavors at something childish, such that he seems to have read only Clitarchus and no other Greek”?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) SISENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What office, aided by the curātor dē Minuciā, was abused to cause Cleander’s death and held by Gaius Turranius, whose time as prefect of Egypt taught him the supply chain that helped Rome’s poor?",
    "answer": "PRAEFECTUS ANNŌNAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what prefecture, which originated in the monarchy and was held by Lucretius Tricipitinus, did Augustus appoint Messalla, only to have him retire after six days?",
    "answer": "PRAEFECTUS URBĪ // URBAN PREFECT(URE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who may have been praefectus urbī but is listed by Livy as a praefectus annōnae, exposed Spurius Maelius for treason while making his own distribution of grain in a public capacity? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "(L.) MINUCIUS (ESQUILINUS AUGURINUS) [NO RELATION TO CURĀTOR DĒ MINUCIĀ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: there will be an extra clue after two readings. Say in Latin: “That sea is too wide to be crossed.” You can translate this sentence using a “quam ut” construction.",
    "answer": "ILLUD MARE LĀTIUS EST QUAM {UT / QUOD} {TRANSEĀTUR / TRANSICIĀTUR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the word ante, say in good classical Latin: “She will not return home until she finds her brother.”",
    "answer": "NŌN ANTE DOMUM {REDĪBIT / REVERTĒTUR} QUAM FRĀTREM {INVENIET / INVĒNERIT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into Latin, using the equivalent within indirect discourse of a future perfect indicative: “He said that whoever caught a dove would receive a reward.”",
    "answer": "{ACCEPTŪRUM / RĒCEPTŪRUM} (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island — home to Hyllus’s mother, Melite — served as the refuge of a Euboean woman who had nursed Dionysus and the adopted homeland of natives of Hypereia who were led by Nausithous?",
    "answer": "SCHERIA / DREPANE / PHAEACIA / CORFU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Nausithous led the Phaeacians from Hypereia since they were being harassed by what neighbors?",
    "answer": "CYCLOPES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Nausithous died to Apollo on the day of his wedding?",
    "answer": "RHEXENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What region was the destination of a 417 A.D. voyage described in the poem Dē Reditū Suō, featured a river described in an epyllion by Ausonius, and was the site of Ausonius’s birth?",
    "answer": "GAUL / GALLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Namatianus’s Dē Reditū Suō claims that what man burned the Sibylline Books, even though his contemporary Claudian calls him a general as great as Scipio Africanus in the Dē Bellō Gothicō?",
    "answer": "STILICHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other late Christian author spent most of his life in Gaul, studying at Bordeaux and living for a time in Tours, where he met St. Martin and wrote his Life?",
    "answer": "SULPICIUS SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Paid 10,000 talents to restore Ptolemy Auletes to the throne, what client of Pompey became consul in 58 B.C. as a reward for actions as tribune in 67, when he passed a law to deal with the scourge of piracy?",
    "answer": "(A.) GABINIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What explanation had the Senate earlier given for forbidding Pompey from restoring Auletes to the throne with Roman military power?",
    "answer": "THEY SAID THE SIBYLLINE BOOKS FORBADE IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Also in 67 B.C., another tribune, Gaius Cornelius, passed a law mandating that holders of what position follow the edicts they were required to lay down when they took office?",
    "answer": "PRAETOR(SHIP)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What three-letter Latin word ending, derived from a one-word Latin fraction, is used in other one-word fractions that have a denominator of twelve in their simplest form, like the words for 5/12 and 7/12? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "-UNX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Just as deunx is derived from dē and uncia – subtracting 1/12 from 1 – the fraction dōdrāns is ultimately derived from dē and what other one-word fraction?",
    "answer": "QUADRĀNS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Count from 1/12 to 11/12 in one-word Latin fractions. Your answer will include the fractions uncia, quadrāns, dodrāns, and deunx. You have 60 seconds.",
    "answer": "SEPTŪNX, BĒS / BESSIS, DŌDRĀNS, DEXTĀNS, DEUNX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who won his kingdom after defeating the invading Idas, was suckled by a doe and named for the animal, and seized the infant Orestes to force the Greeks to heal a wound from Achilles’ spear?",
    "answer": "TELEPHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Telephus originally had come to Teuthrania in search of what woman, his mother?",
    "answer": "AUGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king’s shepherds found the infant Telephus on Mount Parthenius and gave him his name?",
    "answer": "CORYTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following sentences adapted from Tacitus’s Agricola, which I shall read twice, then answer in English the questions that follow. Domitiānus hunc rērum cursum, quamquam nūllā verbōrum iactantiā in epistulīs Agricolae auctum, fronte laetus, pectore ānxius excēpit. Sciēbat dērīsuī fuisse nūper falsum ē Germāniā triumphum, ēmptīs hominibus quōrum habitūs in captīvōrum speciem fōrmārentur: at nunc vēram victōriam ingentī fāmā celebrārī. The question: What was Domitian’s mood when he heard of Agricola’s victories?",
    "answer": "HAPPY ON THE OUTSIDE, NERVOUS ON THE INSIDE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What had been the reaction to Domitian’s triumph over the Germans?",
    "answer": "IT HAD BEEN RIDICULED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Domitian fake his triumph?",
    "answer": "BY BUYING PEOPLE AND DRESSING THEM LIKE CAPTIVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work rejects the “words that persecuted Lycambes” of the Parian poet that inspired it, but wishes a shipwreck on a bad poet, depicts the witch Canidia, and playfully mocks Maecenas, its author’s patron?",
    "answer": "(HORACE’S) EPODES / IAMBĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who is this poetaster who receives an inverted propempticon in the Epodes?",
    "answer": "MAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "About what man does Horace write that his whole life “stands before one’s eyes, as if it were painted on a votive tablet”?",
    "answer": "(C.) LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun is the O in Frederick III’s motto A.E.I.O.U. — Austriae est imperāre [blank] universō — and appears in papal blessings addressed “urbī et [blank],” “to the city and to the world”?",
    "answer": "ORBĪ / ORBIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catholic depictions of the crucifixion of Jesus often bear a titulus on the cross reading simply INRI. What is the full Latin for this abbreviation? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "IĒSUS NAZARĒNUS RĒX IUDAEŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin abbreviation used in place of the English abbreviation B.C. for expressing the year relative to Jesus’s birth.",
    "answer": "A.C.N."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity was supposed to be the heir to Zeus until he was distracted with toys and carried away, after which Athena could only rescue his heart from the Titans who had torn him into pieces?",
    "answer": "ZAGREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was abandoned by his mother because she feared her father Crotopus, and was eventually shredded to pieces by dogs?",
    "answer": "LINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In order to overtake Arcadia, Pelops pretended friendship with what king, whom he had dismembered and scattered his limbs across the land?",
    "answer": "STYMPHALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: there will be an extra clue after two readings. Translate the following line of poetry: “Exoritur clāmorque virum clangorque tubārum.” Note that virum is genitive plural.",
    "answer": "(BOTH) THE SHOUTING OF MEN AND THE CLANG OF TRUMPETS (A)RISE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Translate the following lines of poetry, which I will hand out on paper. Keep in mind that a classicum is a war trumpet. You have sixty seconds. “Sēcūrōs cēpisse pudet cum coniuge somnōs, / ēque tuō, quatiunt miserum cum classica mundum, / surrēxisse sinū.”",
    "answer": "RISEN FROM YOUR BOSOM, WHEN WAR TRUMPETS SHAKE THE MISERABLE WORLD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The sentence “Coeperat trepidus īnvīsā terrā dēcēdere” can be rearranged into a well-formed hexameter line that has no elisions and begins with coeperat. Do so. You have eighty seconds. Moderator should say: “All challenges on toss-ups 1 through 19 must be resolved before toss-up 20 is read. If any players or coaches would like to lodge a challenge, please speak up now.”",
    "answer": "COEPERAT INVĪSĀ TREPIDUS DĒCĒDERE TERRĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After defeating Victor to recover Gaul, what Frankish general found the hanging corpse of the young emperor Valentinian II and decided to raise the rhetorician Eugenius to the purple?",
    "answer": "ARBOGAST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Victor was the son of what other usurper, who was surrendered by his own troops in 388 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MAGNUS MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Early in Valentinian II’s life, his regents were his mother and another Frankish general. Name either. ",
    "answer": "JUSTINA or MEROBAUDES Advanced — Finals"
  },
    {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s kidnapping of Pelops’s son Chrysippus cursed him to die at the Cleft Way at the hands of his own son, Oedipus?",
    "answer": "LAIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Oedipus encountered Laius, he was ironically fleeing from what city in order to avoid murdering the people he thought were his parents?",
    "answer": "CORINTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before kidnapping Chrysippus, Laius had spent his time teaching the boy what skill, which Amphitryon is also said to have taught to Heracles?",
    "answer": "CHARIOT-DRIVING [ACCEPT OBV. EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: “Let it snow today.”",
    "answer": "HODIĒ NINGAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin, with only two words: “The dew will fall tomorrow.”",
    "answer": "CRĀS RŌRĀBIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good Latin, using four words: “It has been thundering for three days now.”",
    "answer": "TRĒS IAM DIĒS TONAT [MUST BE PRESENT TENSE]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work provides 29 reasons not to fear death, describes how dreams come from simulācra, and expounds on the atomic theory of Epicurus in six books of didactic poetry by Lucretius?",
    "answer": "DĒ RRUM NTR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other Latin noun describes the random “swerve” in atoms that accounts for free will?",
    "answer": "CLĪNĀMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what man is the Dē Rērum Nātūrā dedicated?",
    "answer": "(C.) MEMMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between ter and vēr. THRICE // THREE TIMES and SPRING (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between ōrō and ovō. PRAY / BEG / PLEAD and EXULT / REJOICE / TRIUMPH (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between pix and vix. PITCH / TAR and HARDLY / SCARCELY / BARELY (RESPECTIVELY) Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Saoterus, Perennis, and Cleander all effectively controlled the empire during the reign of what man, who preferred to kill ostriches and other animals in the arena while impersonating Hercules?",
    "answer": "COMMODUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name any two of the people who participated in Commodus’s assassination: his mistress, his chamberlain, his wrestling partner, or his praetorian prefect.",
    "answer": "ANY TWO OF: MARCIA; ECLECTUS; NARCISSUS; (Q. AEMILIUS) LAETUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How many consulships was Cleander said to have sold in one day?",
    "answer": "TWENTY-FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose banishment to Corsica by Claudius — where he wrote two consolations — probably inspired his mocking description of the emperor’s deification in the Apocolocyntosis?",
    "answer": "(L. ANNAEUS) SENECA THE YOUNGER [PROMPT ON “SENECA”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Despite his bad relationship with Claudius, Seneca the Younger became the tutor of Nero and wrote what work advising Nero to act with philanthropic benevolence towards his subjects?",
    "answer": "DĒ CLĒMENTIĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some, however, believe that Seneca the Younger loosely alludes to Nero’s ungratefulness in what seven-book work dedicated to Aebutius Liberalis?",
    "answer": "DĒ BENEFICIĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After refusing to make peace at Nicaea, what king was defeated at a site known as “Dog’s Heads,” showing the inferiority of the phalanx to the maniple and ending the Second Macedonian War?",
    "answer": "PHILIP V (OF MACEDON)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "After his victory at Cynoscephalae, Flamininus declared freedom for all Greeks at what festival?",
    "answer": "ISTHMIAN GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What consul of 200 B.C. had started the Second Macedonian War, but suffered a defeat at Lyncestis the very next year?",
    "answer": "(P. SULPICIUS) GALBA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun with what meaning is at the root of “pilgrim,” “peregrination,” and “agrarian”?",
    "answer": "AGER – FIELD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun with what meaning is at the ultimate root of “age” and “eternal”?",
    "answer": "AEVUM – AGE / LIFETIME / GENERATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “aim”?",
    "answer": "AESTIMŌ – ESTIMATE / RECKON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What couple’s marriage was arranged at the cave of Macris by Arete after her husband, Alcinoüs, vowed to protect them from the pursuing Colchians on the condition that they got married? JASON and MEDEA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What aunt of Medea purified the couple for the murder of Medea’s brother, Absyrtus?",
    "answer": "CIRCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While some accounts credit Medea with killing the bronze giant Talos, others give this honor to what Malian archer, the father of Philoctetes? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "POEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Rēctor, cūstōs, and monitor are all alternative names of what enslaved person, who would keep their assigned boy out of harm and accompany him to and from school?",
    "answer": "PAEDAGŌGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The enslaved people usually enlisted as a paedagōgus would be expected to know what language, to prevent the children from forgetting what their nurse had taught them?",
    "answer": "GREEK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What word would a boy use to address his paedagōgus? This may be related to the fact that a paedagōgus had the right to compel obedience by mild punishments.",
    "answer": "DOMINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of clause is used as an alternative to the future passive infinitive — where it is introduced by fore ut — but more often comes after fīō, ēveniō, or accidō?",
    "answer": "SUBSTANTIVE CLAUSE OF RESULT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the phrase “sciō fore ut vincar,” “fore” stands in for what two-word form?",
    "answer": "FUTŪRUM ESSE [MUST BE NEUTER]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What word can regularly introduce a substantive clause meaning “the fact that,” which explains why it often introduces indirect speech in post-classical Latin?",
    "answer": "QUOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Because Sisyphus saw the abduction of Aegina, Zeus sent what god to carry him off to the Underworld, only for Sisyphus to tie him up and prevent all mortals from dying?",
    "answer": "THANATOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sisyphus later avoided death again by having what wife of his not perform the proper burial rites for him? She is sometimes said to be the dimmest star of the Pleiades.",
    "answer": "MEROPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another story of Thanatos takes place in what Thessalian city, where he took a woman to the Underworld in place of her husband?",
    "answer": "PHERAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During what conflict was Marius’s advice ignored by both Rutilius Lupus and Lucius Cato, causing them to succumb to the Marsi, one of many Italian tribes struggling for equal citizenship?",
    "answer": "SOCIAL / MARSIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Marsic leader led the aforementioned attacks against Lupus and Cato?",
    "answer": "(Q.) {POPPAEDIUS / POMPAEDIUS} SILO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Marius’s unwillingness to simply be put out to pasture was demonstrated clearly in 87 B.C. when he convinced what tribune to transfer Sulla’s Mithridatic command to him?",
    "answer": "(P.) SULPICIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a Latin adverb meaning “little by little.”",
    "answer": "[SEE BELOW] [DO NOT READ ANSWERS UNTIL AFTER B1]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give another. Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "PAULĀTIM / GRADĀTIM / PEDETEMPTIM / PEDETENTIM / SĒNSIM / MODERĀTIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin noun and verb, along with their meanings, at the root of the adverb pedetentim, one of the words meaning “little by little.” PĒS – FOOT and TENDŌ – STRETCH / REACH",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What scholar, to whom Trajan granted the iūs trium līberōrum, spoke of various poets in his Dē Vīrīs Illūstribus and delved into the lives of 12 emperors in his Dē Vītā Caesarum?",
    "answer": "(C.) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "To what praetorian prefect and patron did Suetonius dedicate his Dē Vītā Caesarum?",
    "answer": "(C.) SEPTICIUS CLARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Suetonius’s Life of Vergil seems to have been a major source for what 4th-century commentator, a teacher of Jerome and Servius?",
    "answer": "(AELIUS) DONATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What empire defeated Roman forces at Rhandeia in 62 A.D. and placed Tiridates I on the throne of Armenia, a region that often served as a buffer between them and Rome to the west?",
    "answer": "PARTHIANS // PARTHIAN EMPIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What star general of Nero in the East, and future father-in-law of Domitian, avenged the defeat at Rhandeia and made peace with the Parthian king Vologeses I?",
    "answer": "(CN. DOMITIUS) CORBULO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During the reign of which Roman emperor did the Parthian Empire give way to the Sassanids?",
    "answer": "SEVERUS ALEXANDER // ALEXANDER SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following mottoes, if any, is NOT associated with U.S. currency: “Novus ōrdō saeclōrum,” “Annuit coeptīs,” “Ē plūribus ūnum,” or “Fideī dēfēnsor”?",
    "answer": "FIDEĪ DĒFĒNSOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin motto of the Royal Stuart dynasty of Scotland, appearing on coins minted in 1578 and 1580?",
    "answer": "NĒMŌ MĒ IMPŪNE LACESSIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two-word phrase, an expression of stability, integrity and tranquil equanimity, was the motto of Elizabeth I?",
    "answer": "SEMPER EADEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Chloreus’s golden armor and Arruns’ prayer to Apollo sealed the fate of what ally of Turnus, a warrior queen who led the Volsci?",
    "answer": "CAMILLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Camilla had been under the protection of Diana ever since what father of hers prayed to Diana before throwing her across the Amasenus river?",
    "answer": "METABUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What nymph did Diana have immediately avenge Camilla’s death by killing Arruns?",
    "answer": "OPIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, the subject of a funeral epigram by Domitius Marsus, discussed conquering a puer dēlicātus named Marathus and came to prefer Nemesis to his original lover Delia? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Horace, Tibullus had an unhappy love for what woman, though we never hear of her in Tibullus's own corpus?",
    "answer": "GLYCERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the so-called Corpus Tibulliānum are 5 poems of Sulpicia which are addressed to what man?",
    "answer": "CERINTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Audendō virtūs crēscit, morandō timor.”",
    "answer": "{VIRTUE / BRAVERY / MANLINESS} GROWS BY DARING, FEAR (GROWS) BY DELAYING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Sapientiā nōbīs opus est ad regendōs animī mōtūs.”",
    "answer": "CORRECT} THE {MOVEMENTS / IMPULSES / PASSIONS} OF THE MIND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English, keeping in mind that posse is a subjective infinitive: “Multīs hominibus timendī causās attulit timērī posse.” Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "ROUND TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following ancient cities was located farthest west: Massilia, Hadrumetum, Aquae Sulis, Aquincum, Olympia?",
    "answer": "AQUAE SULIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of those same cities was located farthest south?",
    "answer": "HADRUMETUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following ancient cities, if any, was NOT located in Gaul: Cenabum, Genava, Bibracte, Arelate, Gesoriacum?",
    "answer": "ALL IN GAUL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What native of Arezzo gave a farm in Sabine country to Horace and requested that Vergil compose the Georgics while acting as an influential patron of the arts during the reign of Augustus?",
    "answer": "(C. CILNIUS) MAECENAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who first loved Lycinna, then turned to Hostia, was also patronized by Maecenas?",
    "answer": "(SEX.) PROPERTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What minor author of Thyestes and Dē Morte, best known as the publisher of Vergil’s Aeneid, was also patronized by Maecenas?",
    "answer": "(L.) VARIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is contained in the mottoes of the University of California, Amherst College, the state of Vermont, and the University of Chicago — crēscat scientia, vīta excōlātur?",
    "answer": "JUSSIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in the motto of North Dakota?",
    "answer": "PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in the motto of the University of Georgia?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Every year, after wetting their wings in the Aesepus river, flocks of birds sprinkled water on the grave of what Ethiopian king, whom Achilles killed during the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "MEMNON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What goddess of the dawn created dew when she shed tears over the death of her son, Memnon?",
    "answer": "EOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What son of Nestor did Memnon kill during the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "ANTILOCHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What series of conflicts are described here? The timely arrival of Archidamus kept the enemy busy during the first iteration. The second one began when Publilius Philo besieged Naples, and saw two major Roman defeats. The third one culminated in a dēvōtiō at Sentinum.",
    "answer": "SAMNITE WARS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Archidamus was the first of four kings summoned to Italy by what city, a colony of Sparta? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "TARENTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While besieging Naples, Publilius Philo held what office for the first time ever?",
    "answer": "PROCONSUL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Named for the springs of Oceanus, who carried the thunderbolts of Zeus after he threw off his rider on the way to Olympus because of the sting of a gadfly?",
    "answer": "PEGASUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What brother of Pegasus, whose name means “Golden Sword,” was born alongside him from Medusa’s severed head?",
    "answer": "CHRYSAOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what mountain, home to the Muses, did Pegasus create a spring named Hippocrene with the stamp of his hoof?",
    "answer": "HELICON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What English word, when derived from sūs, means “tarnish” or “make dirty,” but when derived from solum, means “the upper layer of earth in which plants grow”?",
    "answer": "SOIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word, when derived from a Latin word meaning “to fall,” refers to an example of a thing occurring, but when derived from a Latin word meaning “box,” refers to a container?",
    "answer": "CASE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word, when derived from the Latin word for “juniper tree,” refers to a beverage, but when derived from the word for “to beget,” refers to a machine?",
    "answer": "GIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Cranes, hydraulic devices, sundials, and machines of war all have a place in the magnum opus of what Augustan-age engineer and author of Dē Architectūrā?",
    "answer": "(M.) VITRUVIUS (POLLIO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into how many books was this work divided?",
    "answer": "TEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What structure outside the city limits of Rome is Vitruvius accredited with having constructed?",
    "answer": "BASILICA OF FANO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Executed at Archelais in Cappadocia, what equestrian lost the throne when the 3rd legion, stationed in Syria, defected and won a victory at Antioch in 218 A.D., allowing Elagabalus to take power?",
    "answer": "MACRINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grandmother of Elagabalus was instrumental in initiating this revolt?",
    "answer": "JULIA MAESA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What lover of Julia Soaemias led the Severan forces at the battle of Antioch and was later executed by Elagabalus for attempting to temper the emperor’s vices?",
    "answer": "GANNYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding sound effects, what literary device can be found in the Ovidian lines “lātrātor Anūbis, sānctaque Būbastis, variusque colōribus Āpis, [...] sīstraque erant, numquamque satis quaesītus Osīris,” due to their repetition of the conjunction -que? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "POLYSYNDETON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "[Note to mod: emphasize the pause] Besides a rhetorical question, what literary device can be found in the Ovidian phrase “quōs equidem āctūtum—sed quid praedīcere poenam attinet”?",
    "answer": "APOSIOPESIS / ANACOLUTHON / PRETERITION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding sound effects, what literary device can be found in the Ovidian phrase “manet imperfossus inque cruentātus”?",
    "answer": "TMESIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sotades of Maronea, Archestratus of Gela, and Euhemerus of Messina were all inspirations for what early author, a native of Rudiae best known for his 18-book historical epic, Annālēs?",
    "answer": "(Q.) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the title of Ennius’s gastronomical epic inspired by Archestratus of Gela?",
    "answer": "HEDYPHAEGETICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Along with the Euhemerus, Ennius also wrote a work based on what Sicilian comic poet turned philosopher, who interpreted the gods as allegories for natural substances?",
    "answer": "EPICHARMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Nēmō tē nēquior invenīrī potest.” [Brief pause] Note that nēquior is the comparative of nēquam, meaning “wicked”.",
    "answer": "NO ONE MORE {WICKED / WORTHLESS} THAN YOU CAN BE FOUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Horace: “Vīlius argentum est aurō, virtūtibus aurum.”",
    "answer": "(AND / BUT) GOLD (IS CHEAPER) THAN VIRTUES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence, adapted from one of Cicero’s letters: “Velim sciās nēminem cuiquam cāriōrem umquam fuisse quam tē mihi.”",
    "answer": "BEEN MORE DEAR TO ANYONE THAN YOU (ARE) TO ME [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Livy, a man with what nōmen, standing near the Porta Capēna, shouted “So perish any Roman woman who mourns for an enemy!” after his sister mourned for one of the Curiatii?",
    "answer": "HORATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. What technique had this man used to defeat the three Curiatii after his two brothers had died in the conflict?",
    "answer": "DIFFERENT PACES), THEN KILLED THEM ONE BY ONE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Alba Longa was ultimately destroyed, what was the only type of building to be spared?",
    "answer": "TEMPLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "[Note to mod: make the “o” sound clear, so players don’t hear pascō] For the verb poscō, give the 2nd person plural, pluperfect active subjunctive. Like pendō, this verb is reduplicative.",
    "answer": "POPOSCISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the same form for pascō.",
    "answer": "PĀVISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the same form for pergō. Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "PERRĒXISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king’s children-in-law include Andraemon by his daughter Gorge, Heracles by his daughter Deianeira, and Cleopatra by his son Meleager?",
    "answer": "OENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Which of Oeneus’s children in the tossup has no divine parentage in any version of their myth?",
    "answer": "GORGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Tydeus is sometimes considered the product of an incestuous union between Oeneus and Gorge, his mother is more usually said to be what daughter of Hipponous?",
    "answer": "PERIBOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What location in south-central Pontus saw Lucullus’s legate Triarius suffer a heavy defeat in 67 B.C., but is more known for the Caesarian victory in 47 B.C. that produced the quote “Vēnī, Vīdī, Vīcī”?",
    "answer": "ZELA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Pontic king did Caesar defeat at the second battle of Zela?",
    "answer": "PHARNACES II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After brushing aside Pharnaces, Caesar passed the Pontic throne to what improbable “son of Mithridates,” who had aided Caesar’s war efforts in Egypt?",
    "answer": "MITHRIDATES OF PERGAMUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of animal is described in the following sentences? This type of animal prevented Telephus from sleeping with his mom. After Admetus forgot to pay proper respects to Artemis during his marriage rites, he found his bedroom filled with this type of animal. Ares transformed Cadmus and Harmonia into this type of animal at their deaths.",
    "answer": "SNAKE(S) / SERPENT(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was Telephus’s mother, a daughter of Aleus?",
    "answer": "AUGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During a disastrous plague, the Romans brought what deity from Epidaurus to Rome in the form of a huge snake?",
    "answer": "AESCULAPIUS / ASCLEPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good classical Latin: “I fear that the Romans will not win today.”",
    "answer": "{TIMEŌ / VEREOR / METUŌ} {UT // NĒ NŌN} RŌMĀNĪ HODIĒ {VINCANT / VICTŪRĪ SINT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in good classical Latin, using fruor for “enjoy”: “If anyone defeats the Romans, he will enjoy eternal glory.”",
    "answer": "SĪ QUIS RŌMĀNŌS {VINCET / VĪCERIT}, {AETERNĀ / SEMPITERNĀ} GLŌRIĀ FRUĒTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in good classical Latin, using supersum for “survive”: “Nevertheless, I do not doubt that the empire will survive.”",
    "answer": "NŌN TAMEN DUBITŌ QUĪN IMPERIUM {SUPERSIT / SUPERFUTŪRUM SIT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete the following analogy: tūtus : salvus :: scelus : .",
    "answer": "FACINUS / VITIUM / CRĪMEN / FRAUS / PECCĀTUM / NĒQUITIA / NEFĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now complete this analogy: sublīmis : celsus :: vacuus : .",
    "answer": "VĀNUS / INĀNIS / IGNĀVUS / LĪBER / VASTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally, complete this analogy: lassus : impiger :: prīscus : . Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "NOVUS / REMISSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "After spending some time in Forum Corneli, what author took advantage of Pliny the Younger’s generosity to return to Bilbilis, despite winning the favor of Domitian at Rome through his epigrams?",
    "answer": "(M. VALERIUS) MARTIAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work did Martial publish to celebrate the opening of the Colosseum?",
    "answer": "LIBER SPECTĀCULŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "One of Martial’s most touching epigrams commemorates the death of what six-year-old enslaved girl, asking the spirits to let her “play in some Elysian glade”? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "ROUND THREE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What structure was replaced with a hastily constructed pontoon bridge, which gave way after an army was driven from the Sāxa Rubra by Constantine in the 312 A.D. battle to which it gives its name?",
    "answer": "MILVIAN BRIDGE // PŌNS MILVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What proconsul had defeated the rebel Lepidus at the Milvian Bridge several centuries before?",
    "answer": "(Q.) LUTATIUS CATULUS (CAPITOLINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Milvian Bridge had been rebuilt in stone by what censor of 109 B.C., a long-time Prīnceps Senātūs who presided over the Mamilian Commission during the Jugurthine War?",
    "answer": "(M.) AEMILIUS SCAURUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What people — who had a propensity to convey all men to safety — did Poseidon threaten to ring with a mountain chain after they brought Odysseus back to Ithaca?",
    "answer": "PHAEACIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What father of Alcinous had led the Phaeacians to the island of Scheria after they were driven out of Hypereia?",
    "answer": "NAUSITHOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When the Phaeacians brought Odysseus to Ithaca, they dropped him off at the cove of what being, the father of the Gorgons and the Graeae?",
    "answer": "PHORCYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The English noun biscuit, or, if you prefer, biscotti, is derived from what two Latin words — one a numeral adverb, the other a verb that is also at the root of “concoct” and “cuisine”? BIS (TWICE) and COQUŌ (COOK)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give an English adjective derived from the Latin prefix prae and the verb coquō.",
    "answer": "PRECOCIOUS / PRECOOKED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now, give a noun referring to a type of food that is derived from those same two words, though its form may also be influenced by a Latin word for “sunny.”",
    "answer": "APRICOT [INFLUENCED BY “APRĪCUS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, whose death we use to date the eruption of Mount Vesuvius, was a famous naturalist and philosopher who wrote the encyclopedic Nātūrālis Historia?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER // C. PLINIUS SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what man was the Nātūrālis Historia dedicated?",
    "answer": "TITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which work of Pliny the Elder was a history of the German wars in 20 volumes?",
    "answer": "BELLA GERMĀNIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The phrases “multō sanguine ea victōria stetit” and “exsilium patriā sēde mūtāvit” demonstrate what use of the ablative, more commonly found with numerical quantities like “pānis tribus sēstertiīs cōnstat”? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "(ABLATIVE OF) PRICE // (DEFINITE) VALUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the idiomatic meaning of “tantī,” a genitive of indefinite value, in phrases like “sunt iūrgia tantī”?",
    "answer": "WORTH IT // WORTHWHILE // WORTH THE PRICE [ACCEPT IDIOMATIC EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a genitive of indefinite value and the verb rēfert, say in good classical Latin: “It is greatly in my interest to win.”",
    "answer": "MAGNĪ MEĀ RĒFERT VINCERE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The adjective mactus is almost exclusively used in what case, which is unattested in the singular for deus in classical Latin, and is exemplified by the forms Orpheu, Aenēā, and mī?",
    "answer": "VOCATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What form is used as the vocative singular of deus in post-classical Latin, including the Vulgate?",
    "answer": "DEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the vocative of the name Capys?",
    "answer": "CAPY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who spent his time studying the Ācta of Tiberius after he dressed as a priest of Isis to escape from the Vitellian siege of the Capitoline, setting up the paranoid and autocratic atmosphere of his reign?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What uncle of Domitian and brother of Vespasian was killed during the Vitellian siege of the Capitoline?",
    "answer": "FLAVIUS SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. Domitian’s father Vespasian was initially kicked from Nero’s inner circle after he displeased the emperor by what means?",
    "answer": "HE FELL ASLEEP DURING ONE OF NERO’S PERFORMANCES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider the following lines from Book 6 of Lucretius’s Dē Rērum Nātūra: “Dēnique quod longō venit impete, sūmere dēbet / mōbilitātem etiam atque etiam, quae crēscit eundō…” What state draws its motto from this excerpt?",
    "answer": "NEW MEXICO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider these lines from Horace’s Odes: “Sī nōn suppliciō culpa recīditur, / quid lēgēs sine mōribus / vānae prōficiunt…” What university draws its motto from these lines?",
    "answer": "UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider this excerpt from Cicero’s Ad Atticum: “Sōl [...] excidisse mihi ē mundō vidētur. Ut aegrōtō, dum anima est, spēs esse dīcitur, sīc ego, quoad Pompēius in Ītaliā fuit, spērāre nōn dēstitī.” What state draws its motto from this passage?",
    "answer": "SOUTH CAROLINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author composed Aeterne rērum conditor and several other hymns, earning him the title “Father of Church Song,” though he is more known for his Dē Officiīs Ministrōrum and his historical activity as bishop of Milan? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "(ST.) AMBROSE // (AURELIUS) AMBROSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Ambrose’s sermons at Milan played an important role in the conversion of what other author, who had obtained the chair of rhetoric there?",
    "answer": "(ST.) AUGUSTINE // (AURELIUS) AUGUSTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Ambrose is an exegetical work on the six days of creation in nine books?",
    "answer": "HEXAMERON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group of animals was either stolen by a half-snake half-woman north of the Black Sea or a fire-breathing son of Vulcan named Cacus while Heracles herded them back to Eurystheus?",
    "answer": "CATTLE OF GERYON [PROMPT ON “CATTLE” WITH “WHOSE CATTLE?”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During this labor, Heracles killed what herdsman and what guard-dog of Geryon? EURYTION and ORTH(R)US",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What herdsman of Hades caught sight of Heracles driving away Geryon’s cattle and alerted Geryon?",
    "answer": "MENOETES / MENOETIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What genre, pioneered by a native of Suessa Aurunca who established hexameter as its standard meter, was given a Stoic flavor by Persius, but most famously took up a tone of savage indignātiō in the hands of Juvenal?",
    "answer": "SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this native of Suessa Aurunca?",
    "answer": "(C.) LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though Romans claimed satire as “tōta nostra,” what Greek author from Gadara wrote satires in a mixture of prose and verse which were imitated by Varro?",
    "answer": "MENIPPUS (OF GADARA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin term for the young boy who carried the utensils down the aisle for the cōnfarreātiō’s wedding procession?",
    "answer": "CAMILLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin term for the box which the camillus would carry?",
    "answer": "CUMERA / CUMERUM [NOT “CUMERUS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin term for the matron who would bring the husband and wife together during the cōnfarreātiō ceremony?",
    "answer": "PRŌNUBA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of object contained an inscription foolishly read aloud by Cydippe, was gathered at Tamasus by Aphrodite in order to help Melanion, and was most famously thrown into the wedding of Peleus and Thetis by Eris?",
    "answer": "APPLE(S) / FRUIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of object, first used during Acrisius and Proetus’s duel at Epidaurus, was made by the craftsman Tychius for Ajax the Greater?",
    "answer": "SHIELD(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hera bribed Eileithyia to delay the birth of Heracles with a golden, thirteen-foot long version of what type of object? Alcmeon met his death after his wife, Callirhoe, asked him to give her one of these objects that had been crafted by Hephaestus. Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "NECKLACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following subordinate clause from Tacitus’s Annālēs: “quō facilius novum rēgnum tuērētur.” [Brief pause] Keep in mind that tueor is synonymous with servō or cūstōdiō.",
    "answer": "HE MIGHT MORE EASILY {GUARD // WATCH (OVER)} THE NEW KINGDOM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence, adapted from Tacitus’s Annālēs: “Morte prohibitus est nē bellum ultrā prōferret.”",
    "answer": "FORTH // EXTENDING} WAR {FURTHER / BEYOND}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence adapted from the Annālēs, keeping in mind that perōdī is basically synonymous with ōdī: “Plērīque superbiam Parthōrum perōsī datum ā Rōmānīs rēgem mālēbant.”",
    "answer": "A KING GIVEN BY THE ROMANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who managed to destroy a siege device known as a sambūca, lift ships right out of the water with giant cranes, and possibly reflect the sun with giant bronze mirrors when he was called on to craft defenses for Syracuse around 213 B.C.?",
    "answer": "ARCHIMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Marcellus, the city’s captor, was eventually ambushed and killed in what year, which also saw a victory for Scipio at Baecula?",
    "answer": "208 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of king Hiero had provoked this siege when he allied himself with Carthage?",
    "answer": "HIERONYMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Cretan king Carmanor purified what deity for murder after the four-day old god killed the monstrous serpent Python at Delphi?",
    "answer": "APOLLO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Ovid’s Metamorphoses, Apollo’s arrogance after slaying the Python leads him to mock and provoke the anger of what other god?",
    "answer": "CUPID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What spring did Apollo hide under great rocks because its nymph had tricked him into choosing Delphi, rather than the spring, as the site of his oracle? The seer Teiresias died after he drank from the waters of this same spring.",
    "answer": "TELPHUSA // TILPHU(S)SA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Described as “rērum Rōmānārum florentissimus auctor” by Tacitus, what man was twice expelled from the Senate for moral turpitude, only to write moralizing monographs on the Jugurthine War and the Catilinarian Conspiracy?",
    "answer": "(C.) SALLUST(IUS CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Two epistles attributed to Sallust address what man, who supported him throughout his political career and gave him the governorship of Africa Nova?",
    "answer": "(C.) JULIUS CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sallust was a native of what city in Sabine territory? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "AMITERNUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a two word phrase used frequently in classical Latin for the superlative of senex, which literally means “greatest in birth.”",
    "answer": "MAXIMUS NĀTŪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What conqueror of Fregellae seized upon the murder of one of his servants by pro-Gracchan partisans as a pretext for receiving the first ever Senātūs Cōnsultum Ultimum, which declared Gaius Gracchus an enemy of the state?",
    "answer": "(L.) OPIMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What supporter of Gaius Gracchus, who was declared an enemy in the same Senātūs Cōnsultum Ultimum, had proposed a law regarding Italian enfranchisement while consul in 125 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(M.) FULVIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What law proposed, with Gaius Gracchus’s support, the founding of a colony on the site of old Carthage?",
    "answer": "LĒX RUBRIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What base Latin verb, when compounded with ab-, means “to hide,” when compounded with per-, means “to destroy,” and, when compounded with vēnum, means “to sell”?",
    "answer": "DŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The passives of perdō and vendō are usually supplied by compounds of what other Latin verb with the same prefixes? One of these compounds is commonly listed as a neutral passive verb. EŌ [PEREŌ and VĒNEŌ]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other compound, consisting of dō and two prefixes, also means “to hide”? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "PRELIMS TIEBREAKER (FOR 2ND/3RD SEED)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Wedding processions were arranged and the sportula was doled out in which part of the house, a courtyard with pavement running from the street entrance to the ātrium?",
    "answer": "VESTIBULUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before receiving the sportula, clients would perform what activity, which involved greeting their patron in his ātrium in the early morning? Give the Latin term.",
    "answer": "SALŪTĀTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which type of ātrium had a roof with two pairs of beams crossing each other at right angles?",
    "answer": "(ĀTRIUM) TUSCĀNICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who told the herald Venulus that forces from his city of Argyripa would not be able to help Turnus, since he was still plagued by troubles from Venus, whom he had wounded at Troy?",
    "answer": "DIOMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into what type of animal were Diomedes’s companions transformed by the angry goddess?",
    "answer": "BIRDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Apulian king, who shares his name with Turnus’s father, had welcomed Diomedes to Italy?",
    "answer": "DAUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After he was defeated in the plains between Callinicum and Carrhae by the Sassanid king Narses, what commander was publicly humiliated by Diocletian, even though this Eastern Caesar and his Augustus saw eye to eye on issues such as the Great Persecution?",
    "answer": "GALERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nominal Western Augustus was sent forth by Galerius in 307 A.D. to dislodge the usurper Maxentius, though he was ultimately captured and killed by Maximian?",
    "answer": "(FLAVIUS VALERIUS) SEVERUS (II)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Severus was captured while being besieged in what Northern Italian city, which would become the capital of the Western Empire during the reign of Honorius?",
    "answer": "RAVENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “īlicet” vel “prōtinus”?",
    "answer": "STRAIGHTAWAY / IMMEDIATELY / FORTHWITH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “īlex”?",
    "answer": "(HOLM)OAK (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “illecebra”?",
    "answer": "ENTICEMENT / CHARM / BAIT / LURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though his style was sometimes branded as bombastic, contorted, and reckless with neologisms, what author of Dulorestes and Armōrum Iūdicium was praised by Cicero as the greatest of all Latin tragic poets?",
    "answer": "(M.) PACUVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which cothurnāta of Pacuvius features the disguised Ulysses returning to Ithaca where he is mortally wounded by his son Telegonus?",
    "answer": "NIPTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which cothurnāta of Pacuvius includes a contest between Orestes and Pylades to determine which of the two would show greater nobility in the face of death? Advanced — Tiebreakers",
    "answer": "SEMIFINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "26 hymns — 12 on daily events, and 14 on martyrs — as well as the didactic poems Apotheosis, Hamartigenia, and Psychomachia, were written by what author, the greatest Christian lyric poet?",
    "answer": "(AURELIUS) PRUDENTIUS (CLEMENS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though Prudentius calls him the greatest living orator, what pagan author of 10 books of letters and several Relātiōnēs did he attack in a two-book polemical work?",
    "answer": "(Q. AURELIUS) SYMMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What earlier Christian poet gives us the fullest record of Christian chiliastic fantasies within his Carmen Apologēticum, or Carmen dē Duōbus Populīs?",
    "answer": "COMMODIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who threw a footstool at the disguised Odysseus and took Melantho as a lover, then became the second suitor to be killed, dying immediately after Antinous?",
    "answer": "EURYMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What suitor from Same tried to throw an ox hoof at Odysseus but missed?",
    "answer": "CTESIPPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What seer and son of Oenops sought mercy from Odysseus only to be decapitated?",
    "answer": "LEODES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin adjective, which often modifies words like ventus or rēs in the meaning of “favorable” or “propitious,” is derived from the gerundive of a deponent verb and normally serves as an ordinal number?",
    "answer": "SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other adjective, derived from a perfect passive participle, means “unfavorable” and can be used as a preposition?",
    "answer": "ADVERSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Due to differences in Greek and Roman augury, what Latin adjective, a synonym of scaevus in its base meaning, can take on the meaning of either “favorable” or “unfavorable,” though it is the latter meaning that is preserved in its most direct English derivative?",
    "answer": "SINISTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "First distinguished from perduelliō in a 103 B.C. law by Saturninus, what charge came to rely on the evidence of dēlātōrēs to condemn enemies of the emperor on vague accusations of treason?",
    "answer": "MĀIESTĀS (LAESA / IMMINŪTA / DĒMINŪTA / MINŪTA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Saturninus used māiestās to try and exile what two men for their recent military defeat? (Q.) SERVILIUS CAEPIO and (CN.) MALLIUS MAXIMUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What cousin of Domitian was executed along with his wife Domitilla on charges of māiestās? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "FLAVIUS CLEMENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author gives us all the following quotations? “Nescit vōx missa revertī.” “Caelum nōn animum mūtant quī trāns mare currunt.” “Quandōque bonus dormītat Homērus.”",
    "answer": "HORACE // (Q.) HORATIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase from Vergil means “the utmost limit” or “an unknown region,” and includes the name of the location considered the farthest north in classical thought?",
    "answer": "ULTIMA THŪLĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin phrase found in Persius means “live mindful of death”?",
    "answer": "VĪVE MEMOR LĒTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sister of Sterope and Sthenele may have committed suicide when a bronze statue of her husband was burned by her father Acastus, though the more common account is that she was unable to bear her grief at being separated from his shade after a three-hour reunion?",
    "answer": "LAODAM(E)IA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Laodamia’s husband, Protesilaus, was honored at a shrine in what Thracian city near Sestus, which in historical times was plundered by Artaÿctes?",
    "answer": "ELAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. What omen demonstrated that Protesilaus still had the power to avenge insults, scaring Artaÿctes into agreeing to give back the riches he had stolen from the temple?",
    "answer": "A FISH LEAPT IN A PAN WHILE BEING COOKED [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin into English: “Aliunde aliō trānsfugiunt.”",
    "answer": "THEY FLEE (ACROSS) FROM ONE PLACE TO ANOTHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into idiomatic English: “Aliud aliī nātūra iter ostendit.”",
    "answer": "NATURE SHOWS DIFFERENT PATHS TO DIFFERENT PEOPLE."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Vergil’s Georgics, understanding that aliās is a temporal adverb, into English: “Nōn aliās caelō cecidērunt plūra serēnō fulgura.”",
    "answer": "AT NO OTHER TIME HAVE MORE LIGHTNING BOLTS FALLEN {DURING / FROM} A CALM SKY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jurisprudence, military art, agriculture, and oratory are among the six artēs covered in what early imperial author’s encyclopedic handbook, of which only the eight books on medicine survive?",
    "answer": "(A. CORNELIUS) CELSUS’"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What contemporary of Tiberius reported the dietetic and medicinal qualities of the various ingredients contained in his ten-book corpus of cooking recipes?",
    "answer": "(M. GAVIUS) APICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Augustan Age figure, likely motivated by patriotic purposes, drew a massive map of the known world along with commentariī which may have provided a basis for future geographers?",
    "answer": "(M. VIPSANIUS) AGRIPPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following forms, if any, can function as more than one part of speech, excluding any substantivation: gregis, relictī, maeror, seram, dōs?",
    "answer": "SERAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the full dictionary entry, including its meaning, of any two of the words of which seram can be a form, ignoring vowel lengths. Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "[SEE BELOW]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the full dictionary entry of two more words, of which seram can be a form.",
    "answer": "SERŌ, SERERE, SERUĪ, SERTUM – JOIN / FASTEN / BRAID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Over half a million of what group of people — across 50 fortresses and 985 villages — were massacred when a governor of Britain, Gaius Julius Severus, was sent by Hadrian to suppress their revolt and banish them from the new colony of Aelia Capitolina?",
    "answer": "JEWS / JUDAEANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This genocidal act was the culmination of a long series of offenses against the Jews. What emperor had instructed Publius Petronius to set up a statue of him at the Temple in Jerusalem and tolerated attacks on the Alexandrian Jewish population from Greek mobs?",
    "answer": "CALIGULA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Jewish scholar and philosopher led a delegation to seek redress from Caligula after the prefect Avilius Flaccus encouraged these attacks?",
    "answer": "PHILO (OF ALEXANDRIA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the best use of the dative case that can be found in the following sentence: “Tetrarchīān Caesar Dēiotārō dēmit.”",
    "answer": "SEPARATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now identify the case and use of ullī in this line from Ovid: “Barbarus hīc ego sum quī nōn intellegor ullī.”",
    "answer": "DATIVE OF AGENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the case and use of reditūs in this sentence from Vergil: “Sanguine quaerendī reditūs animāque litandum Argolicā.”",
    "answer": "NOMINATIVE SUBJECT [“RETURNS MUST BE SOUGHT…”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where in Rome might one find the umbilīcus urbis, the milliārium aureum, the Porticus of Gaius and Lucius and the Temple of Castor?",
    "answer": "ROMAN FORUM // FORUM RŌMĀNUM [PROMPT ON “FORUM”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Also in the Forum is a shrine to Venus under what epithet, which connects her to purification and to Rome’s sewer system?",
    "answer": "(VENUS) CLOACINA / CLUACINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin name for the valley which connects the Forum to the Forum Boārium and contains the Arch of Janus?",
    "answer": "VĒLĀBRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What island provided a naval force under the command of Eudamus that defeated Hannibal during the Seleucid War, was protected from the Senate’s calls for war by Cato the Elder in 168 B.C., and served as Tiberius’s first location of voluntary exile from 6 B.C. to 2 A.D.?",
    "answer": "RHODES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Rhodian naval commander was defeated by the allied forces of Eumenes II and a Roman admiral at the battle of Cape Corycus? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "POLYXENIDAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who was this Roman admiral, who had led 80 battleships into the Aegean Sea in 191 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(C.) LIVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The statue of Venus Prōspiciēns on Cyprus serves as a reminder of what woman, who mocked a young man’s love until he hanged himself, causing her to be turned to stone?",
    "answer": "ANAXARETE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Athenian woman in the early books of the Metamorphoses was transformed into a black stone shortly after Minerva summoned Invidia, or Envy, to infect her?",
    "answer": "AGLAURUS / AGRAULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What women from Amathus were also turned into stone because they lost all shame after becoming the first prostitutes?",
    "answer": "PROPOETIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What 645-verse work of Latin literature, which imitates Manilius while describing air currents in subterranean channels as the cause for volcanic eruptions, was falsely attributed to Vergil and included in the Appendix Vergiliāna?",
    "answer": "AETNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the title of Manilius’s work on signs of the zodiac and other astrological phenomena?",
    "answer": "ASTRONOMICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which other work from the Appendix Vergiliāna shares its title with an idyll by Sueius about varieties of nuts?",
    "answer": "MORĒTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What usurper was killed when he refused to let his troops sack Moguntiacum — which had supported the revolt of Laelianus — almost 9 years after he killed Saloninus and founded the Gallic Empire?",
    "answer": "POSTUMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general of Gallienus unsuccessfully attacked Postumus in 265 A.D. before he himself revolted in 268?",
    "answer": "AUREOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What strategic city along the Rhine River served as the capital of Postumus’s Gallic empire?",
    "answer": "TRIER // AUGUSTA TREVERORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into the best classical Latin: “He who kills the king will be made king.” [Brief pause] Note that in this sentence, the tenses should be equivalent to a future more vivid conditional.",
    "answer": "(IS) QUĪ RĒGEM {INTERFICIET / INTERFĒCERIT} RĒX {FĪET / CREĀBITUR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Without using a conjunction, say in Latin: “Our enemies will not escape if they are defeated first.”",
    "answer": "PRIUS VĪCTĪ NŌN {EFFUGIENT / ĒVĀDENT} {INIMĪCĪ / HOSTĒS} NOSTRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Without using a conjunction, say in Latin: “He does not seem like he will accuse the emperor.”",
    "answer": "NŌN VIDĒTUR IMPERĀTŌREM {ACCŪSĀTŪRUS / ARGŪTŪRUS}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who wrote in opposition to Philinus, likely provided a primary source for Books 22-23 of Livy when he described his own trip to the Delphic Oracle in his Greek annalistic narrative, the first prose history of Rome? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "(Q.) FABIUS PICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which annalist, known for his use of the librī linteī, is best remembered as the father of a neoteric poet who wrote the epyllion Io?",
    "answer": "(C.) LICINIUS MACER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which annalist served at Numantia and eschewed simple annalistic chronicle in favor of giving eyewitness accounts and demonstrating “quō cōnsiliō quāque ratiōne” events occurred?",
    "answer": "(C.) SEMPRONIUS ASELLIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological group is described here? The daughters of Hyacinth were sacrificed on the grave of Geraestus, a member of this group. This group was credited with building the walls of Tiryns and Mycenae. The constellation Sagitta represents the arrow Apollo used to kill this group in order to avenge the death of Asclepius.",
    "answer": "CYCLOP(E)S"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Argonaut Polyphemus was a member of what group, which also included Coronus and Exadius?",
    "answer": "LAPITHS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What fabulous group of one-eyed people constantly warred with the griffins and stole their gold at every opportunity? Moderator should say: “All challenges on toss-ups 1 through 19 must be resolved before toss-up 20 is read. If any players or coaches would like to lodge a challenge, please speak up now.”",
    "answer": "ARIMASPI(ANS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in ultimate derivation between “cover” and “recover,” keeping in mind that the latter word is cognate with “recuperate.” OPERIŌ and CAPIŌ (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in ultimate derivation between “examination” and “exanimation.” AGŌ and ANIMUS (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in ultimate derivation between “callow” and “callous.” CALVUS and CALLUM (RESPECTIVELY) Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After her grandfather Numitorius and fiancé Icilius unsuccessfully defended her from Marcus Claudius — who claimed she had been his slave — what woman was led away by her father and stabbed in the heart, kicking off the Second Secession of the Plebs?",
    "answer": "VERGINIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Among the laws passed by Valerius Potitus and Horatius Barbatus after this secession was the re-establishment of what right, which was originally secured by Publicola in 509 B.C. against a magistrate’s coercitiō and further strengthened by Valerius Maximus in 300?",
    "answer": "PRŌVOCĀTIŌ [PROMPT FOR THE LATIN IF THEY ANSWER IN ENGLISH]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What later law, which Livy calls “a new beginning” for “the liberty of the Roman plebs,” was so effective at preventing debt servitude that the practice of nexum soon fell into total disuse?",
    "answer": "LĒX POETELIA (PAPIRIA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the Latin words spissus, confertus, and crēber?",
    "answer": "THICK / DENSE / CROWDED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the Latin words hāmātus and uncus?",
    "answer": "HOOKED / CROOKED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the Latin words subdolus and vafer?",
    "answer": "SLY / CUNNING / CRAFTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author provided precedent for Augustine’s Confessions in his Ad Dōnātum, promoted forgiving people who renounced their faith during persecutions in his Dē Lāpsīs, and took a firm stand against heresies in his Dē Catholicae Ecclēsiae Ūnitāte?",
    "answer": "(THASCIUS CAECILIUS) CYPRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name both the emperor whose persecutions Cyprian survived and the one whose persecutions saw his death. DECIUS and VALERIAN (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which priest of Rome opposed Cyprian’s stance on the lāpsī, and had his followers elect him as their own pope?",
    "answer": "NOVATIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group, who according to Homer received the daughters of Pandareus as servants from the Harpies, was impersonated by the maids of Polyxo when they hanged Helen and was known to the Romans as the Dirae?",
    "answer": "FURIES / EUMENIDES / ERINYES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Furies were identified at Athens with the Eumenides and what other chthonian deities in a cave on the Areopagus?",
    "answer": "SEMNAI THEAI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Thebes and son of Tisamenus, hounded by the Furies of Laius and Oedipus, left Thebes on the advice of an oracle and left the throne to Damasichthon? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "AUTESION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an idiomatic translation of this sentence from Book 1 of Livy’s Ab Urbe Conditā: “Ēvēnit facile quod dīs cordī esset.”",
    "answer": "THAT WHICH WAS {PLEASING TO // DESIRED BY} THE GODS TURNED OUT EASILY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate from Livy’s Ab Urbe Conditā: “Utinam prō decore tantum hoc vōbīs et nōn prō salūte esset certāmen.”",
    "answer": "AND NOT FOR YOUR {SURVIVAL / SAFETY}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate from Livy’s Ab Urbe Conditā: “Incolumis ad suōs trānāvit, rem ausus plūs fāmae habitūram quam fideī.”",
    "answer": "THAT WOULD HAVE MORE REPUTE THAN CREDIBILITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what region of Greece — home to the rivers Cocytus and Acheron — did Heracles sire a child by Phylas’s daughter Astyoche in Ephyra and Odysseus lead an army against the Brygi with queen Callidice?",
    "answer": "THESPROTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of tree did Heracles take a fancy to in Thesprotia and subsequently introduce to the Peloponnesus?",
    "answer": "(WHITE) POPLAR (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Atreus visited Thesprotia, he mistook what woman for the daughter of king Thesprotus?",
    "answer": "PELOPIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Terence, in which the protagonist unwittingly rapes his own fiancée, gives a sober and sympathetic portrayal of Bacchis the courtesan and Sostrata the titular mother-in-law, which may explain its poor reception and repeated failure?",
    "answer": "HECYRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Terence, partly derived from Diphilus’s Synapothneskontes, compares the different upbringings of Aeschinus and Ctesipho?",
    "answer": "ADELPHOE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What braggart soldier plays an important role in Terence’s Eunuchus, his most comedic play?",
    "answer": "THRASO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A residue called hallec would come from the several-month process of making what substance, which was the result of fermenting salt and fish intestines in the sun?",
    "answer": "GARUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What dish was made by removing the stones of an olive, chopping up the pulp, and seasoning it with various spices before mixing it in a jar with oil and would eventually be eaten with cheese?",
    "answer": "EPITȲRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the production of wine, the grape juice would be left to ferment in what large, thick-walled jars that were specifically designed for storage? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "DŌLIUM / DŌLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the scansion, that is, the order of dactyls and spondees, in the first four feet of this line from Vergil: “Insonuēre cavae gemitumque dedēre cavernae.”",
    "answer": "DDDD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the scansion of the first four feet of this line from Vergil: “Incedunt pueri, pariterque ante ora parentum.”",
    "answer": "SDDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the scansion of the first four feet of this line from Vergil: “Sit pecori, apibus quanta experientia parcis.”",
    "answer": "DDSD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What tribe joined forces with elements of the Suevi and Alans to break into Roman Gaul on December 31, 406 A.D., though they would be pushed into Spain by Constantine III before finally settling in Africa under the command of King Genseric?",
    "answer": "VANDALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While they were still in Spain, the Vandals were forced to endure attacks from what Visigothic king, who had signed a deal with Constantius III to reclaim the Iberian peninsula for Rome?",
    "answer": "WALLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Genseric succeeded him as leader of the Vandal Kingdom in 477 A.D. and would father the future king Hilderic through his marriage to Valentinian III’s daughter Eudocia?",
    "answer": "HUNERIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is grammatically incorrect about the following sentence? “Cōnsilium inībō senātōrum iuxtā aede Castoris interficiendōrum.”",
    "answer": "IUXTĀ TAKES ACCUSATIVE, NOT ABLATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is grammatically infelicitous about the following sentence? “Opportūnissimē haec imperātōrī nocendī occāsiō ā mē nacta est.”",
    "answer": "NANCISCOR IS DEPONENT, SO IT CANNOT BE PASSIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is grammatically infelicitous about the following sentence? “Minus difficile est rēx fierī quam semper secundum philosophiae praecepta rēgnāre.”",
    "answer": "INFINITIVES ARE ACCUSATIVE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Moliones were killed on their way to what event, which was rededicated to Poseidon by Theseus, and initially founded in honor of a dead child carried to the shore by a dolphin?",
    "answer": "ISTHMIAN GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Thessalian immigrant to Elis, along with the Moliones, aided Augeas in his war against Heracles and had famous funeral games in his honor where Nestor won almost every contest?",
    "answer": "AMARYNCEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The tomb of the Moliones can be seen at what city, where Heracles had previously stayed with Molorchus prior to fighting the Nemean Lion? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "CLEONAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s controversial testimony against a governor of Macedonia who attacked the Odrysae, as well as a narrow escape from a conspiracy involving Varro Murena, led him to resign the consulship and obtain imperium prōcōnsulāre māius from the Senate?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who was the governor of Macedonia who waged this unauthorized war?",
    "answer": "(M.) PRIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What specific right was added to Augustus’s proconsular power when it was made māius?",
    "answer": "EXERCISE COMMAND OVER ALL THE LEGIONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "While reading a new edition of your favorite Latin poem, you notice that a word is different from what you remember, so you look at the apparātus criticus and read, “The MSS disagree on the fourth foot.” What is the Latin and English for the abbreviation in this sentence?",
    "answer": "{MANŪSCRĪPTA // MANŪ SCRĪPTA} – MANUSCRIPTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "You come across the form prōripuit in the same work and have the same thought, so you look down to read “v.l. prōrūpit”. What is the Latin and English for that abbreviation?",
    "answer": "VARIA LĒCTIŌ – VARIOUS / VARIANT / DIFFERENT READING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "At the top of Lewis and Short entries for verbs, you can often find a list of the various forms attested, which are used to inform principal parts and catalogue irregularities. If you encounter the abbreviation “plqpf.” in such a section, what would the corresponding Latin and English be?",
    "answer": "{PLŪSQUAMPERFECTUM // PLŪS QUAM PERFECTUM} – PLUPERFECT"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Drawing on Junius Cordus, Marius Maximus, and many fictitious sources, what problematic work of history, attributed to Trebellius Pollio, Flavius Vopiscus, and four others, gives unreliable biographies of 2nd- and 3rd-century emperors?",
    "answer": "HADRIĀNŌ USQUE AD NUMERIĀNUM DĪVERSĪS COMPOSITAE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name any two of the six authors not mentioned in the toss-up.",
    "answer": "VULCACIUS GALLICANUS, AELIUS LAMPRIDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Because of the unreliability of these biographies, modern historians are forced to rely extensively on 4th-century epitomes such as what man’s Liber dē Caesaribus?",
    "answer": "AURELIUS VICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What late-Republican figure, the subject of a praetexta by Curiatius Maternus and a biography by Thrasea Paetus, appears as a Stoic hero in the later books of the Pharsālia, since his stubborn incorruptability and dramatic suicide made him a model for writers nostalgic for the Republic?",
    "answer": "(M. PORCIUS) CATO THE YOUNGER / UTICENSIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cato’s march through the desert in book 9 of the Pharsālia is interrupted by a long and gruesome digression on what type of animal?",
    "answer": "SNAKE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What speech of Cicero humorously attacks Cato while defending a client accused of electoral corruption? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "PRŌ MŪRĒNĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What name is shared by a consul who saw one of his armies defect to Sulla in 83 B.C., and a consul who ceded command to Domitius Ahenobarbus prior to the battle of Magnesia due to an illness that was afflicting both him and his brother Scipio Africanus?",
    "answer": "L. (CORNELIUS) SCIPIO (ASIATICUS / ASIAGENES / ASIAGENUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What other consul of 83 B.C. did not fare any better against Sulla?",
    "answer": "(C.) NORBANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Antiochus III’s defeat at Magnesia, what consul of 189 B.C. was sent to Asia to remove the Scipio brothers from command and impose far harsher terms on the Seleucid monarchy?",
    "answer": "(CN.) MANLIUS VULSO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify, in order, the three alliterative Latin words that are at the ultimate roots of three words in the following sentence: “This unreasonable insurrection shows the erosion of society’s morals.”",
    "answer": "REOR, REGŌ, RODŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify, in order, the four alliterative Latin words that are the ultimate roots of four different words in the following sentence: “The king decreed an excise tax for the excision of excess fat.”",
    "answer": "CERNŌ, CENSEŌ, CAEDŌ, CĒDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Let’s have some fun with these words! Please come up with an original English sentence that — without repeating any of the words in the first bonus — contains a derivative of cernō, censeō, caedō, cēdō, and cadō.",
    "answer": "OPPORTUNITY TO SOLVE THE CASE BY COMMITTING SUICIDE”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between a Scythian king who condemned his daughter Idaea to death for her crimes against her stepsons, and a man who married Bateia after immigrating to the Troad from Samothrace, the home of his mother Electra?",
    "answer": "DARDANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The second Dardanus received from Zeus an image of what god, which eventually found its way to Aroe after being given in a chest to a son of Euaemon and Opis?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Idaea is most known for what she did to Phineus’s sons by Cleopatra, she also bore him two sons of her own: Thynus and what man, the eponym of a tribe encountered by the Argonauts whose kings included Dascylus and Lycus?",
    "answer": "MARIANDYNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into completely alliterative Latin: “Let the wealth be given up to the gods of the two temples.”",
    "answer": "DĪVITIAE {DĒDANTUR / DENTUR} DEĪS DUŌRUM DĒLŪBRŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into completely alliterative Latin: “The Thracian touched the burnt incenses with the ankle of a bull.”",
    "answer": "THRĀX TĀLŌ TAURĪ TŪRA TOSTA TETIGIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into completely alliterative Latin, also using three Greek inflections: “A story of the Metamorphoses recalls Memnon being changed at death.” Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "MȲTHOS METAMORPHŌSEŌN MEMNONA MEMORAT MORTE {MŪTĀRĪ / MŪTĀTUM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb careō, give the perfect active infinitive.",
    "answer": "CARUISSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the same form for cernō.",
    "answer": "CRĒVISSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change crēvisse to the future tense.",
    "answer": "CRĒTURUS/-A/-UM ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Known in Latin as Vallum Aelium, what structure, begun in 122 A.D., served as the northern boundary of the Roman Empire until the construction of a fortification north of it 20 years later?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN’S WALL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What governor of Britannia supervised the construction of Hadrian’s Wall?",
    "answer": "(A.) PLATORIUS NEPOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Immediately north of the wall was the territory of which Scottish tribe?",
    "answer": "PICTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Augustus’s Res Gestae, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: Annōs undēvīginti nātus exercitum prīvātō consiliō et prīvātā impensā comparāvī, per quem rem pūblicam ā dominātiōne factiōnis oppressam in libertatem vindicāvī … Populus autem eōdem annō mē consulem, cum consulēs uterque bellō cecidisset, et triumvirum reī pūblicae constituendae creāvit. The question: Augustus claims that he freed the republic from the oppression of what? (from: rem pūblicam ā dominātiōne factiōnis oppressam)",
    "answer": "(THE DOMINATION OF) A FACTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Describe how Augustus mustered an army. (from: exercitum prīvātō consiliō et prīvātā impensā comparāvī)",
    "answer": "WITH PRIVATE PLANS & PRIVATE EXPENSE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What tragedy led the Roman people to install Augustus as triumvir and consul? (from: cum consulēs uterque bellō cecidisset)",
    "answer": "THE DEATH OF THE TWO CONSULS (IN WAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Described by Donatus as tall, dark, and rustic, which Roman author studied under the Epicurean Siro, was nicknamed Parthenias for his social aloofness, and wrote works such as Bucolics and Georgics?",
    "answer": "VIRGIL / (P.) VERGILIUS MARO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Georgics, Virgil removes mention of what prefect of Egypt, who had fallen out of favor with Augustus?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In place of a panegyric to Cornelius Gallus, there is an epyllion concerning what mythological beekeeper?",
    "answer": "ARISTAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What princess, the daughter of Alcinous and Arete, resembled Artemis, according to Odysseus, the man she aided in Book VI of the Odyssey?",
    "answer": "NAUSICAÄ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Thesprotian queen entertained Odysseus and even bore the hero a son during his inland journey after killing the suitors?",
    "answer": "CALLIDICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other woman in Odysseus’s life was the granddaughter of the god Hermes? ANTICLEIA (prompt on “his mother”)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Paraffin” and “infinitesimal” are derived from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "FINIS – END / BOUNDARY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of finis means “to skillfully handle a situation”?",
    "answer": "FINESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of a synonym of finis means “to get rid of completely usually by killing off”?",
    "answer": "ELIMINATE (FROM LĪMEN – END / THRESHOLD)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Livy writes falsus utinam vātēs sim what use of the subjunctive is he employing?",
    "answer": "OPTATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is expressed by the Ciceronian phrase nihil video quod timeam?",
    "answer": "RELATIVE CLAUSE OF CHARACTERISTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is seen in the Plautine quote etiamne eam salūtem?",
    "answer": "DELIBERATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Certain caves near the famed silver mines of Thrace were said to be the home of the oracular spirit of what Thracian king whose assassination was caused by a spy named Dolon?",
    "answer": "RHESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name two Muses given as Rhesus’ mother by the river Strymon.",
    "answer": "EUTERPE / CALLIOPE / CLIO / TERPSICHORE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is interesting about Rhesus’ conception?",
    "answer": "HIS MOTHER WAS IMPREGNATED BY THE RIVER AS SHE WADED IN IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which rhetorical device, excluding all forms of alliteration can be found in the following lines adapted from Vergil’s Aeneid: versat … lōrīcam ex aere rigentem, sanguineam, ingentem, quālis cum caerula nubes solis inardescit radiīs longēque refulgent. (not a metaphor because quālis means “like” and so this is an explicit comparison)",
    "answer": "SIMILE / ASYNDETON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now do the same for the following lines from Book 1, concerning Neptune quelling the winds: Quōs egō—sed mōtōs praestat componere fluctūs.",
    "answer": "APOSIOPESIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now do the same for the following lines from Book 2 concerning the sack of Troy: est urbe egressīs tumulus templumque vetustum desertae Cereris. CHIASMUS: templumque vetustum desertae Cereris / (The temple, not Ceres herself, is deserted by the Trojans)",
    "answer": "HYPALLAGE / TRANSFERRED EPITHET:"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Publius Servilius Vatia Isauricus, Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, Marcus Antonius, and Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus were the co-consuls of what Roman dictator who was assassinated in the Theatre of Pompey on the Ides of March, 44 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(C.) IULIUS CAESAR / JULIUS CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of those men served as co-consul with Caesar from 48-47 B.C.?",
    "answer": "ISAURICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what year did Caesar serve with Bibulus?",
    "answer": "58 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Cīvēs veritī sunt nē barbarī tōtam urbem arderent.",
    "answer": "WOULD BURN / BURNED THE ENTIRE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Sunt quī pacem desiderent, sed bellum eīs praeparendum est. (accept literal translation: … BUT WAR MUST BE PREPARED FOR THEM)",
    "answer": "THERE ARE THOSE WHO DESIRE PEACE, BUT THEY MUST PREPARE FOR WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate: Caesare transiente Rubicōnem, nōn dūbium est quin bellum civile accidat. (accept literal translation: WITH CAESAR CROSSING THE RUBICON)",
    "answer": "THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT CIVIL WAR WILL / MAY HAPPEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When he was unable to fulfill the king’s demand that all inhabitants of Seriphos gift him with horses, who was ordered by king Polydectes to bring the head of the Gorgon Medusa?",
    "answer": "PERSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two deities provided Perseus with all of the tools that he would need to kill Medusa?",
    "answer": "ATHENA & HERMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On his way back from killing Medusa, Perseus saved Andromeda from death by a sea monster. Who was the mother of Andromeda, who had boasted that her daughter was prettier than the Nereids?",
    "answer": "CASSIOPEIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What early Roman author wrote a work that declared cabbage to be a very versatile crop?",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER / (M. PORCIUS) CATO MAIOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other Silver Age author wrote letters to his friends, which included the emperor Trajan?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Silver Age author wrote a work that included a werewolf interrupting a dinner party?",
    "answer": "PETRONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: Cicero makes his speeches too long. (do NOT accept habet, this is not a correct use of the idiom, do accept nimium longās or valdē longās, if given)",
    "answer": "CICERŌ (SUĀS) ŌRĀTIŌNĒS LONGIŌRĒS FACIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin without using an ablative: I have harmed men greater than you.",
    "answer": "NOCUĪ VIRĪS MAIŌRIBUS QUAM TIBI / VŌBĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: I have used and always will use the biggest words of all.",
    "answer": "ŪSUS SUM ET SEMPER ŪTAR MAXIMĪS VERBĪS / DICTĪS OMNIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Edict of Milan and the Nicene Creed are hallmarks of the reign of what Roman emperor, who was the first to convert to Christianity?",
    "answer": "CONSTANTINE I / THE GREAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name Constantine’s father, whose death led to the demise of the Tetrarchy.",
    "answer": "CONSTANTIUS (I) CHLORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where in 337 A.D. did Constantine’s relatives meet to discuss partitioning of the empire?",
    "answer": "SIRMIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the motto of Brookyln College, nil sine magnō labōre?",
    "answer": "NOTHING WITHOUT GREAT LABOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the motto of Dartmouth College, vox clamantis in desertō?",
    "answer": "THE VOICE OF ONE CRYING IN THE WILDERNESS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the motto of Wellesley College, nōn ministrārī sed ministrāre?",
    "answer": "NOT TO BE SERVED, BUT TO SERVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book IV of the Metamorphoses, Alcithoë considers the stories of Daphnis, Celmis, and the Curetes before finally telling the story of what 15-year-old boy, who quite literally became one with the nymph Salmacis?",
    "answer": "HERMAPHRODITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Salmacis and Hermaphroditus merged, Salmacis’s pool had what enervating effect on men who bathed in it?",
    "answer": "MADE THEM SOFT AND EFFEMINATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Soon after this story, Alcithoë and her two sisters are transformed into what animals?",
    "answer": "BATS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Arch of Septimius Severus, the Temple of Divine Caesar, and the Regia are all located in which part of the city of Rome?",
    "answer": "ROMAN FORUM / FORUM ROMANUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Horologium Augusti and the Ara Pacis are located in which part of the city of Rome?",
    "answer": "CAMPUS MARTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What temple in the Roman Forum was closed in times of peace and open in times of war?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE OF JANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs fingō and cingō",
    "answer": "FINGŌ – TO SHAPE / FORM / PRODUCE; CINGŌ – TO BIND / SURROUND / ENCIRCLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the nouns rāmus and rēmus",
    "answer": "RĀMUS - BRANCH; RĒMUS - OAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs pandō and pangō.",
    "answer": "PANDŌ - SPREAD OUT; PANGŌ – FASTEN / FIX / COMPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, the son of a tribunus angusticlavi, worked as an imperial secretary under Hadrian where he had wide access to court documents for writing his De Vita Caesarum?",
    "answer": "(C.) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into how many books is Suetonius’s De Vita Caesarum divided?",
    "answer": "12"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Suetonius, of which only the De Grammaticis et Rhetoribus survives, is a collection of biographies subdivided by genres? Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin motto of Boston.",
    "answer": "AS HE WAS WITH OUR FATHERS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now give the Latin motto of our northern neighbors, Canada.",
    "answer": "Ā MARĪ USQUE AD MARE (FROM SEA TO SEA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Not only does Canada have a Latin motto, but some of its provinces do. Newfoundland and Labrador has as its motto Quaerite prīmē regnum Deī. Translate that.",
    "answer": "SEEK FIRST THE KINGDOM OF GOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following verbs, if any, is not syntactically like the others: pudet, ponit, paenitet, piget?",
    "answer": "PONIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What do the other three verbs have in common?",
    "answer": "(THEY ARE) IMPERSONAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What case would the cause of revulsion take in a sentence with pudet? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "GENITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Seiuges, bigae, and quadrigae were all types of what vehicle found in the circus?",
    "answer": "CHARIOTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The honor ducenarius was given to a horse who won how many races?",
    "answer": "TWO HUNDRED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What term referred to the starting gates for a Roman horse race? Mythology:",
    "answer": "CARCERES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the Gigantomachy, missiles of red-hot metal were the deadly weapons of which deity as he defeated his gigantic enemy Mimas?",
    "answer": "HEPHAESTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What enemy of Poseidon was defeated and covered by the island Nisyrus?",
    "answer": "POLYBOTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two giants were destroyed by the bronze clubs of the Fates?",
    "answer": "AGRIUS & THOAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What character in mythology was poorly regarded in 5th century Athens as a “tricksy sophist” and in Roman times as a prime example of the untrustworthiness of Greeks, far cries from his earlier reputation as a courageous, resourceful, and crafty leader whose actions were crucial for the Greeks’ victory in the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "ODYSSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "One example of Odysseus’ depiction as a trickster is in Euripides’ Iphigenia in Aulis, in which Odysseus lies to Iphigenia’s mother Clytemnestra by saying that rather than being sacrificed, she will be wed to what man?",
    "answer": "7"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "This conception of Odysseus as an untrustworthy Greek is seen throughout Virgil’s Aeneid, such as in whose rhetorical question “sic notus Ulixes?” as he urges the Trojans to not bring the horse within the city walls? Literature:",
    "answer": "LAOCOÖN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Pacuvius celebrates the victor at Pydna in 168 B.C.?",
    "answer": "PAULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of work is Paullus?",
    "answer": "FABULA PRAETEXTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Along with which author from Pisaurum is Pacuvius held as a top tragedian?",
    "answer": "ROUND 2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, born in Arpinum in 106 B.C., rose to fame after defeating his rival Hortensius in trial and soon became the most successful orator of his time?",
    "answer": "(M. TULLIUS) CICERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In what series of 14 speeches, modeled after those of the Greek orator Demosthenes, does Cicero vehemently attack Mark Antony?",
    "answer": "THE PHILIPPICS / PHILIPPICAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What last work of Cicero includes a discussion of moral duties in three books?",
    "answer": "DE OFFICIIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Noting that aveo, avēre can mean “to desire,” and “hail” in the imperative, translate into completely alliterative Latin: Hail, grandfather, do you desire birds?",
    "answer": "AVĒ, AVE, AVĒSNE AVĒS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into completely alliterative Latin: Why did the fifth oak tree seek peace?",
    "answer": "QUĀRĒ QUĪNTA QUERCUS QUIĒTEM QUAESĪVIT?"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Translate into completely alliterative Latin: “The battle lines and the goose will hear the weapons of the citadel.”",
    "answer": "ACIĒS ATQUE ĀNSER(QUE) ARMA ARCIS AUDIENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the incessant demanding of the tribune Terentilius Harsa, what legislation, forming the foundation of Roman law, was formally passed in 449 B.C.? ",
    "answer": "(L.) VALERIUS (POTITUS) & (M.) HORATIUS (BARBATUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grammatical property is in common among the nouns ravis, vīs, sitis, and febris?",
    "answer": "(THEY ARE) PURE I-STEM(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give a pure i-stem noun which means “rain.”",
    "answer": "IMBER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two pure i-stem nouns which can mean “ship.”",
    "answer": "PUPPIS & LINTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, the son of Hagnias, and the helmsman of the Argo, died while the Argonauts stayed among the Mariandyni?",
    "answer": "TIPHYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name one of the two Argonauts who was murdered by the Libyan shepherd Caphaurus when they tried to steal his sheep?",
    "answer": "CANTHUS / ERIBOTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Teleon, almost swam to his death but was saved by Aphrodite and taken to Lilybaeum in Sicily?",
    "answer": "9"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Roman author’s works include a discussion of language and style, a poem about a trip to Spain, and a verse epigram about Terence, although he is perhaps better known for his Commentarii on the Civil and Gallic Wars?",
    "answer": "(C. IULIUS / JULIUS) CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom did Caesar dedicate his three-book discussion of language and style, entitled De Analogia?",
    "answer": "(M. TULLIUS) CICERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name any two works in the so-called Corpus Caesarianum.",
    "answer": "BELLUM AFRICUM, BELLUM HISPANIENSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Cute,” “vinegar,” “aglet,” and “acuity” are all derived from what Latin adjective, with what meaning?",
    "answer": "ĀCER - SHARP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Puny,” “naïve,” and “renaissance” are all derived from Latin verb, with what meaning?",
    "answer": "NASCOR – TO BE BORN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Proctor,” “sure,” and “curio” are derived from ultimately derived from what Latin noun, with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CŪRA – CARE / CONCERN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Named Cottus, Briareus, and Gyes, what siblings of the Titans later guarded them in Tartarus and are distinguished by their hundreds of limbs?",
    "answer": "HECATONCHIRES / CENTIMANES / HUNDRED-HANDED ONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other three siblings of the Titans and Hecatonchires were known as Thunder, Lightning, and Bright?",
    "answer": "CYCLOPES / BRONTES, STEROPES, ARGES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Hesiod, what primordial sea deity did Gaia bear on her own alongside Uranus and the hills?",
    "answer": "PONTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which king of Rome who may have reigned from 616-579 B.C., is credited with doubling the membership of the Roman Senate, draining the Roman Forum, and constructing the Cloaca Maxima and Circus Maximus?",
    "answer": "TARQUINIUS PRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Tarquinius Priscus’s Etruscan name?",
    "answer": "LUCOMO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to some traditions, Tanaquil, Tarquinius Priscus’s wife, also changed her name when she came to Rome. What was her new name, which is believed to have been invoked at Roman weddings?",
    "answer": "GAIA (CAECILIA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Caelum nōn animum mūtant quī trans mare currunt and Eheu fugācēs labuntur annī are both quotations from what Venusian author who advises his readers to carpe diem?",
    "answer": "HORACE / (Q.) HORATIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What four worded quotation from Horace denotes the immortality that his book of Odes would bring him?",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the colloquial meaning of the following Horatian quotation: parturient montēs, nascētur rīdiculus mūs.",
    "answer": "ALL THAT WORK AND NOTHING TO SHOW FOR IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between moror and morior.",
    "answer": "MOROR – TO DELAY; MORIOR – TO DIE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between manus and mānēs.",
    "answer": "MANUS – HAND / TEAM / BAND ; MĀNĒS – SHADES / SPIRITS (OF THE DEAD)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between mōs and mūs.",
    "answer": "MŌS – CUSTOM / HABIT; MŪS – MOUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What child of Cronus and Rhea is said to have been saved after Rhea gave Cronus a literal horse instead, while sending the child to the care of the Telchines on Rhodes?",
    "answer": "POSEIDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeus, not Poseidon, is the child who was traditionally saved from his father’s ferocity. What tribe was said to bang their shields in order to mask the sounds of the infant Zeus’s cries?",
    "answer": "CURETES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some traditions say that what other child of Cronus and Rhea was saved by being given to Ophion and Eurynome?",
    "answer": "HERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, in a poem in Sapphic strophe, compares his love to a flower that is plowed down after his mistress Lesbia’s betrayal?",
    "answer": "(C. VALERIUS) CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The theme of betrayal is especially poignant in Catullus 64, which includes an ecphrasis of the abandonment of what mythological character?",
    "answer": "ARIADNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catullus 2 and 3 focus on what pet owned by Lesbia?",
    "answer": "PASSER / SPARROW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On formal documents and inscriptions, what did the letter l denote about a person’s status?",
    "answer": "(HE / SHE WAS A) FREEDMAN / FREEDWOMAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What part of a freedman’s name usually came from his slave name?",
    "answer": "COGNOMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under what circumstances would a master give a manumitted slave his praenomen? (e.g. Marcus Tullius Tiro, slave of Marcus Tullius Cicero)",
    "answer": "WHEN THE SLAVE WAS THE MASTER’S FAVORITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Athenās navigābō ut meum patrem inveniam.",
    "answer": "I WILL SAIL TO ATHENS TO FIND MY FATHER."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Pompeius mīsit legātōs quī pācem cum Caesare peterent.",
    "answer": "POMPEY SENT ENVOYS TO SEEK PEACE WITH CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Dē victōriā Caesaris gaudeamus et desperent!",
    "answer": "LET US REJOICE AND LET THEM DESPAIR OF CAESAR’S VICTORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By ignoring a lame man asking for a rope, a floating corpse asking to be taken aboard, and three women asking for help weaving a piece of cloth, who was able to safely enter the Underworld on her mission to fill a box with Proserpina’s beauty ointment?",
    "answer": "PSYCHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Psyche was able to complete this task with the help of what talking object, who had earlier convinced her not to commit suicide?",
    "answer": "(TALKING) TOWER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What child did Psyche bear by Cupid?",
    "answer": "VOLUPTA(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author participated in the military campaigns in Germany under Domitius Corbulo and dedicated to the emperor Titus his encyclopedic work entitled Historia Naturalis?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER / GAIUS PLINIUS SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into how many books is the Historia Naturalis divided?",
    "answer": "37"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pliny the Elder’s historical work on Germany was used as a source material by what later historian and friend of Pliny the Younger?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS CORNELIUS) TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle on the city borders of Rome saw the forces of Sulla defeat the alliance of Marian and Samnite forces in 82 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) COLLINE GATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What future member of the First Triumvirate commanded the right flank of Sulla’s army at Colline Gate?",
    "answer": "(M. LICINIUS) CRASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "From what temple did Sulla give a speech accompanied by the screams of tortured Samnite prisoners in 82 B.C.?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE OF BELLONA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Propertius’s Elegies, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: Quālis et unde genus, quī sint mihi, Tulle, Penātēs, quaeris prō nostra semper amīcitia. sī Perusina tibi patriae sunt nota sepulcra, Italiae dūrīs fūnera tempōribus, cum Romāna suōs ēgit discordia cīvēs. The question: Ad quem Propertius dīcit?",
    "answer": "TULLUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quālia tempōra in Italiā sunt?",
    "answer": "DŪRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quōs Romāna discordia ēgit?",
    "answer": "SUŌS CĪVĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb aufero, auferre, give the 2nd person plural, pluperfect, passive, subjunctive.",
    "answer": "ABLATĪ/-AE/-A ESSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change that form to the active voice.",
    "answer": "ABSTULISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now for the same verb, give the future, passive, infinitive. Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Instar, gratiā, and tenus all govern what case? ",
    "answer": "CAUSĀ & ERGŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "With what type of verbs are supines ending in -um used?",
    "answer": "VERBS OF MOTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is exemplified by supines ending in -ū?",
    "answer": "ABLATIVE OF RESPECT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two examples of adjectives that used supines ending in - ū to express respect. MIRĀBILIS, FACILIS, DIFFICILIS, DIGNUS, (there are others) History/Culture:",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The family line of Decius Mus was famous for committing what type of act, a sacrifice by charging straight into enemy formation?",
    "answer": "DEVOTIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Name a battle where a Decius Mus committed devotio.",
    "answer": "MT. VESUVIUS (339 B.C.) / SENTINUM (295 B.C.) / ASCULUM (279 B.C.)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In which of these battles did devotio did not lead to an outright victory? Mythology:",
    "answer": "ASCULUM (279 B.C.)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Phrygian Dares was sent by Apollo to advise Hector not to fight what man, the dear friend of Achilles?",
    "answer": "PATROCLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the prophecy that Apollo informed Dares of?",
    "answer": "HE HIMSELF WOULD BE SLAIN BY ACHILLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Who killed Dares when he fled to the Greek camp? Literature:",
    "answer": "ODYSSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What late Roman author claims that God himself spoke the words Ciceronianus es, non Christanus to him in a dream, sparking his newfound devotion to Christianity and the eventual completion of his magnum opus, a complete Latin translation of the Bible?",
    "answer": "(ST.) JEROME / SOPHRONIUS EUSEBIUS HIERONYMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At whose behest did Jerome set out to write this translation, the Vulgata?",
    "answer": "POPE DAMASUS(‘S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Jerome consists of 135 biographies from St. Peter to Jerome himself?",
    "answer": "ROUND 3"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Containing a section thanking the Carthaginians for a statue dedicated to him and another section humorously praising a parrot as Second Sophists would, the Florida of what author shows his flexible and brilliant prose?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) APULEIUS (MADAURENSIS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the second section of which of Apuleius’ philosophical works does he discuss the position of demons and their function between the world of the gods and the world of men?",
    "answer": "DE DEO SOCRATIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For chapters 13 and 14 of his De Mundo, Apuleius is said to have drawn on the works of what man who wrote the Attic Nights?",
    "answer": "AULUS GELLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two infinitives, say in Latin: Moderator, don’t say that my answer is wrong.",
    "answer": "MODERĀTOR, NŌLĪ DĪCERE MEUM RESPONSUM FALSUM ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using cavē, say in Latin: Friends, don’t stop believing me.",
    "answer": "AMĪCĪ, CAVĒ DESINĀS / SISTĀS CREDERE MIHI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using nē, say in Latin: Marcus, don’t listen to that liar.",
    "answer": "MARCE, NĒ AUDĪVERIS ILLUM MENDĀCEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who recognized the corpse of her son Polydorus in Thrace on her journey back to Greece with Odysseus?",
    "answer": "HECUBA / HECABE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What local king had murdered Polydorus after he had been sent there to stay out of the war?",
    "answer": "POLYM(N)ESTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two actions did Hecuba’s servants take against Polymestor?",
    "answer": "HIS CHILDREN WERE MURDERED & HE WAS BLINDED WITH THEIR BROOCHES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Varsity,” “suzerain,” “prosaic,” “controversial,” and “versatility” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "VERTŌ – TO TURN (AROUND / ABOUT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Souvenir,” “convent,” “avenue,” “adventitious,” and “supervene” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "VENIŌ – TO COME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Valid,” “avail,” “prevalent,” and “convalescent” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "VALEŌ – TO BE STRONG / HAVE STRENGTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Constructed in 138 A.D., what temple in the Forum Romanum was said to have been the largest in all of Rome, dedicated to Venus and the Roma Aeterna?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE OF VENUS AND ROME / TEMPLUM VENERIS ET ROMAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Cassius Dio, the architecture of the Temple of Venus and Rome drew criticism from what prolific royal architect, a favorite of Trajan, leading to his execution?",
    "answer": "APOLLODORUS (OF DAMASCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name three of his architectural designs created during Trajan’s reign.",
    "answer": "LIBRARY OF TRAJAN, BASILICA ULPIA, ODEON OF DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Thamyris, the Harpies, and the daughters of king Pierus were all defeated in contests by what group of nine sisters?",
    "answer": "MUSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose daughters were threatened by Agamemnon because of their ability to produce endless supplies of food, and were thus transformed into white doves to protect them?",
    "answer": "ANIUS(‘S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose sisters were so devastated by his death that they were transformed into guinea fowl?",
    "answer": "MELEAGER(‘S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from one of Cicero’s Catilinarians, which I will read twice, and answer the question that follows in English: Iacet ille nunc prostrātus, Quirītes, et sē perculsum atque abiectum esse sentit et retorquet oculōs profectō saepe ad hanc urbem, quam ē suis faucibus ereptam esse lūget; quae quidem mihi laetārī vidētur, quod tantam pestem evomuerit forāsque proiēcerit. The question: According to Cicero, what does Catiline mourn about? (from: ē suis faucibus ereptam esse lūget)",
    "answer": "THAT THIS CITY WAS SNATCHED FROM HIS JAWS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What has Cicero done to Catiline for which he expects reproach? (from: quae quidem mihi laetārī vidētur, quod tantam pestem evomuerit forāsque proiēcerit",
    "answer": "THAT HE HAS THROWN HIM OUT AND FLUNG HIM OUT OF THE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Cicero, what does Catiline sense? (from: et sē perculsum atque abiectum esse sentit)",
    "answer": "THAT HE IS STRUCK DOWN AND CAST AWAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid sit futūrum crās, fuge quaerere is a famous quote from Horace’s Ode 1.9, exemplifying what grammatical construction, in which a future active participle is used with a form of sum?",
    "answer": "ACTIVE / FIRST PERIPHRASTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive does Horace use in that quote?",
    "answer": "INDIRECT QUESTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Horace follows that quote with et quem fors diērum cumque dabit, which would appear in prose as et quemcumque fors diērum dabit. What use of the genitive is exemplified there?",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE / OF THE WHOLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Inspired by Propertius’s verse epistle from Arethusa to Lycotas, which of Ovid’s works featured a collection of elegiac love letters written by mostly mythological women?",
    "answer": "HEROIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Most of Ovid’s Heriodes involve women writing to their male lovers. Name two of the three pairs of lovers who wrote in Ovid’s Heroides.",
    "answer": "PARIS & HELEN / HERO & LEANDER / ACONTIUS & CYDIPPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which work of Ovid does he proclaim pride in the originality of the Heroides?",
    "answer": "15"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which battle saw the deaths of the consuls Aulus Hirtius and Vibius Pansa against the forces of Mark Antony in 43 B.C.?",
    "answer": "MUTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what earlier skirmish of 43 B.C. was Vibius Pansa gravely wounded?",
    "answer": "FORUM GALLORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Two years later, the Perusine War was waged against Octavian by Lucius Antonius and what wife of Mark Antony?",
    "answer": "FULVIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eos, Phlegon, and Pyrois were all horses of which god, the father of Phaëthon?",
    "answer": "HELIOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the foster father of Phaëthon who took him and Clymene in?",
    "answer": "MEROPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is unusual about Phaëthon’s body in the Eridanus river?",
    "answer": "IT STILL BURNS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of Vermont, North Dakota, Missouri, Massachusetts, and Alabama, identify the state whose motto contains a semi-deponent verb.",
    "answer": "ALABAMA (AUDĒMUS IŪRA NOSTRA DEFENDERE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of those same states, identify the state whose Latin motto contains a future imperative.",
    "answer": "MISSOURI (SALUS POPULĪ SUPRĒMA LEX ESTŌ)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of those same states, identify one of the two states whose motto contains a subjunctive as well as the usage of it.",
    "answer": "VERMONT – JUSSIVE / NORTH DAKOTA – PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After the disaster at Cannae, what battle of 215 B.C. proved to be a saving grace for the Romans when the forces of Hasdrubal were driven back after attempting to mimic his brother’s tactical maneuvers at Cannae?",
    "answer": "DERTOSA / IBERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two Roman generals managed to defeat Hasdrubal, but instead of pursuing, continued to consolidate power in Spain?",
    "answer": "LUCIUS & GNAEUS (CORNELIUS) SCIPIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The Carthaginians won their only land battle without being led by Hannibal in the Second Punic War at what site in Spain circa 211 B.C., at which Publius Cornelius Scipio the Elder and Gnaeus Scipio were killed?",
    "answer": "UPPER BAETIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this quote from Book IX of Vergil’s Aeneid, whose English translation greets visitors to the Memorial Hall of the 9/11 Museum in New York City: Nulla diēs umquam memorī vōs eximet aevō.",
    "answer": "FROM A REMEMBERING / MINDFUL AGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this quote from the Romanian philosopher Emil Coiran: Est nulla nātiō in quā habitāmus, sed lingua; cavē errēs, ut prīma lingua vēra nostra patria est.",
    "answer": "MAKE NO MISTAKE, AS OUR FIRST LANGUAGE IS OUR TRUE FATHERLAND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this quote of the Marquis de Lafayette, translated into Latin, back into English: Rēs novae sacerrimae iūrum et maximē necessāriae officiōrum sunt.",
    "answer": "AND THE MOST INDISPENSABLE / NECESSARY OF DUTIES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeus’s seduction of Alcmene, a shipwreck, hidden treasure, a haunted house, and a brave but arrogant soldier are all plot points in the works of which late 3rd-century B.C. Umbrian playwright?",
    "answer": "(TITUS MACCIUS) PLAUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Plautus premiered at the Plebeian Games in 200 B.C. and is notable for having very little plot or structure?",
    "answer": "STICHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Plautus often combined the plots of multiple extant Greek plays into one play, a process known as what?",
    "answer": "CONTAMINATIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Argive seer and son of Coeranus predicted that his own son would either die of illness at home or die at Troy on the battlefield?",
    "answer": "POLYEIDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name this son of Polyeidus, who was killed by Paris.",
    "answer": "EUCHENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Cretan child had Polyeidus earlier brought back to life at the instigation of King Minos?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Avidius Nigrinus, Cornelius Palma Frontonianus, Publilius Celsus, and Lusius Quietus were all members of the conspiracy of the Four Consulars that occurred under which emperor in 118 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(P. AELIUS) HADRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, Praetorian Prefect at the time of Trajan’s death, was responsible for the smooth succession of Hadrian when he ordered the execution of the Four Consulars?",
    "answer": "(P. ACILIUS) ATTIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which friend did Hadrian call upon to suppress an uprising in Mauretania caused by the dismissal of Lusius Quietus, for which he would later be rewarded by becoming Praetorian Prefect in 125 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(Q. MARCIUS) TURBO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Make the phrase caecum fūnus dative singular.",
    "answer": "CAECŌ FŪNERĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change caecō fūnerī to the accusative plural.",
    "answer": "CAECA FŪNERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now change caeca fūnera to the genitive.",
    "answer": "CAECŌRUM FŪNERUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wrote a collection of 30 epigrams, entitled Liber Spectaculorum, to commemorate the opening of the Colosseum under the emperor Titus?",
    "answer": "(M. VALERIUS) MARTIAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which work of Martial is a book of short inscriptions for accompanying varying presents given on occasions such as Saturnalia?",
    "answer": "XENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which work of Martial is a book of short inscriptions for accompanying varying presents given to guests at banquets?",
    "answer": "APOPHORETA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a synonym of the Latin noun gladius. (do not accept pugiō, culter, sīca, or other words for “dagger” or “knife”)",
    "answer": "FERRUM / ENSIS / MŪCRŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a synonym of the Latin noun praemium.",
    "answer": "DŌNUM / MŪNUS / MANŪBIAE / NĪCĒTĒRIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a synonym of the Latin adjective mollis. Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is often seen following the adjectives sātus, ortus, ēditus, and genitus?",
    "answer": "ORIGIN / SOURCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of ablative naturally follows verbs such as triumphō, exsultō, gaudeō, and ardeō?",
    "answer": "CAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The adjectives immūnis, vacuus, and nūdus regularly take what use of ablative?",
    "answer": "SEPARATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What property is shared by the verb forms that appear in the mottoes of Columbia University, Johns Hopkins University, Idaho, and Missouri?",
    "answer": "ALL IN THE FUTURE TENSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What property is shared by the verb forms that appear in the mottoes of Amherst College, Vermont, Wyoming, and Kentucky?",
    "answer": "ALL IN THE SUBJUNCTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Again with regards to their verbs, what property is shared by the mottoes of Brooklyn College, Dartmouth College, and the District of Columbia? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "THEY DON’T HAVE VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who set up a council of sixteen prominent senators to advise her young son, Severus Alexander?",
    "answer": "JULIA MAMAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What praetorian prefect of Septimius Severus was murdered by the Praetorian Guard because he was deemed too strict?",
    "answer": "(DOMITUS) ULPIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Greek historian would have also been killed had the emperor not sent him to Bithynia? Mythology:",
    "answer": "CASSIUS DIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose sons overthrew and killed him because he appointed Deiphontes as his successor?",
    "answer": "TEMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Temenus’s sons accidentally killed his sister while fleeing with her?",
    "answer": "PHALCES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom was this sister that was mishandled and killed? Literature:",
    "answer": "HYRNETHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author was probably informed by Greek ktisis literature when composing a historical work that celebrated lesser known heroes called the Origines?",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Cato the Elder extols virtues such as parsimonia, duritia, and industria, and advises selling slaves when they become too old?",
    "answer": "DE AGRI CULTURA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of prose by Cato includes such information on social conventions as the fact that poetry was not a respectable art in Rome, and that any man who engaged in it was wanton?",
    "answer": "SEMI-FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: He says that you, who have been loved often, will never love him. NUMQUAM EUM / SĒ AMĀTŪRUM / AMATŪRAM ESSE [note sīs not sit]",
    "answer": "DĪCIT TĒ, QUĪ / QUAE SAEPE AMĀTUS / AMĀTA SĪS,"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two subjunctives, translate this sentence into Latin: Since he cries so much, it is not clear what we should do.",
    "answer": "QUID AGĀMUS / FACIĀMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: So long as he sees her tomorrow, he will be very happy.",
    "answer": "LAETISSIMUS / VALDĒ LAETUS ERIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Proclaimed emperor in Rhaetia, what praetorian prefect from Narbo first began marching against Bahram II and took over Ctesiphon before mysteriously dying in 284 A.D.?",
    "answer": "CARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where was the predecessor of Carus, Probus, killed in 282 A.D. during a mutiny of his soldiers?",
    "answer": "SIRMIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Carus’s successor, Numerian, was said to have been killed by the praetorian prefect Aper at what city, the future capital of Diocletian’s portion in his tetrarchy?",
    "answer": "NICOMEDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which late author, who had been banished to Curubis at one point in his life, was able to evade Decius’s persecution but not Valerian’s in 258 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(THASCIUS CAECILIUS) CYPRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Cyprian discusses how Christians must treat their brethren who had claimed not to be Christian to avoid the persecutions but came back into the arms of Christians later?",
    "answer": "DE LAPSIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of what African city, his birthplace, was Cyprian bishop?",
    "answer": "CARTHAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Argive twins yoked a wagon to themselves and carried their mother to a temple as part of a festival to Hera?",
    "answer": "CLEOBIS & BITON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After their mother prayed to Hera that her sons be given the best thing human beings could obtain, what unusual fate befell the twins after the festival was complete?",
    "answer": "THEY DIED / THEY FELL ASLEEP (IN THE TEMPLE) NEVER TO WAKE UP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Solon, how many miles did the Argives hoist the chariot before arriving at the temple?",
    "answer": "FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of nurus, socrus, vulgus, manus, and acus, which does not belong because of gender?",
    "answer": "VULGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of vīrus, pelagus, cētus, pectus, and humus, which does not belong because of gender?",
    "answer": "HUMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of porticus, arctus, mōles, aurīga, and mūla, which does not belong because of gender?",
    "answer": "AURĪGA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English this line from Book III of the Aeneid. parce piās scelerāre manūs.",
    "answer": "MITTE, FUGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "When a secret agreement between Hannibal and Philip V was discovered, which Roman admiral, and praetor of 215 B.C., was sent to foment a war against Philip V and keep him preoccupied?",
    "answer": "(M.) VALERIUS LAEVINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "With which league of Greek city-states did Valerius Laevinus successfully negotiate a treaty in 212 B.C., creating a new enemy for Philip V to contend with?",
    "answer": "AETOLIAN LEAGUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "With which king of Pergamum did Valerius Laevinus also successfully negotiate a treaty having him fight alongside the Aetolian League against Philip V?",
    "answer": "ATTALUS I"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was purified by members of the Phytalides before he could enter Athens?",
    "answer": "THESEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At which old woman’s hut did Theseus stay prior to his capturing of the Marathonian Bull?",
    "answer": "HECALE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "With which king of the Abantes did Theseus leave his children prior to his death?",
    "answer": "ELEPHENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the phrases ad augusta per angusta, consuētudō locī observanda est, ignōtī nulla cupīdo, oleum addere camīno, and ultrā posse nēmo obligātur, which one colloquially means “don’t bite off more than you can chew”?",
    "answer": "ULTRĀ POSSE NĒMŌ OBLIGĀTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the phrases in the tossup, which one can colloquially mean “no pain no gain”?",
    "answer": "AD AUGUSTA PER ANGUSTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the phrases in the tossup, which one can colloquially mean “when in Rome, do as the Romans do”?",
    "answer": "CONSUĒTUDŌ LOCĪ OBSERVANDA EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which famous writer of fabulae palliatae was held as first, ahead of Plautus, on Volcacius Sedigitus’ canon of comic poets?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Greek author’s Plokion is Caecilius Statius’ Plocium based on?",
    "answer": "MENANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term describes the farcical aria that the Menandrian monologues were turned into?",
    "answer": "CANTICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who would have returned Orestes, Pylades, and Iphigeneia to Thoas as prisoners had his grandfather not revealed to him that he was the half-brother of Orestes and Iphigeneia, since he was the son of Agamemnon by Chryseїs?",
    "answer": "CHRYSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What object had Orestes, Pylades, and Iphigeneia taken from Thoas when they fled his island?",
    "answer": "A STATUE OF ARTEMIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island, inhabited by Chryses, did they land on?",
    "answer": "ZMINTHE / CHRYSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Josephus, what corrupt curator of Judea instigated the First Jewish Revolt by exacerbating the relationship between Romans and Jews through his openly discriminatory Jewish policies?",
    "answer": "GESSIUS FLORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Due to the onset of the First Jewish Revolt caused by Gessius Florus, what legate from Syria was sent to deal with the Jewish rebels, only to be routed at the battle of Beth Horon?",
    "answer": "CESTIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Romans did eventually subdue the Jewish rebels after the sack of Jerusalem in 70 B.C. What punitive institution did Vespasian impose on all Jews to fund his lavish projects and restoration of the temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus in Rome?",
    "answer": "FISCUS JUDAICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the comparative and superlative forms of egēnus.",
    "answer": "DĪTISSIMUS / DĪVENTISSIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which rhetorical device, excluding all forms of alliteration, can be found in the following lines from Seneca the Younger’s Apocolocyntosis: deformīs hiemps grātōs carpēbat honōrēs dīvitis autumnī, iussōque senescere Bacchō carpēbat rārās serus vindemitor uvās. [personification: hiemps … carpēbat (winter was seizing) / chiasmus: rārās serus vindemitor uvās, / metonymy: Bacchō standing in for wine]",
    "answer": "PERSONIFICATION / CHIASMUS / METONYMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now do the same for the following lines, concerning the Parcae: mirantur pensa sorōrēs: mutātur vilis pretiōsō lana metallō, aurea formōsō descendunt saecula fīlō. SYNCHESIS [aurea formōsō … saecula fīlō] /",
    "answer": "ASYNDETON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The following lines are from Claudius’s funeral dirge, as sung by a professional mourning choir: “Fundite flētus, edite planctūs, resonet tristī clamōre forum.” Give the dominant foot for this meter, which features two short syllables followed by one long syllable.",
    "answer": "ANAPEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin phrase nesciō quis meaning “somebody” stemmed originally from an expression of what use of the subjunctive?",
    "answer": "INDIRECT QUESTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the idiomatic translation of the phrase sānē quam?",
    "answer": "IMMENSELY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Livy into idiomatic Enlgish: mīrum quantum prōfuit.",
    "answer": "HE / IT BENEFITTED TREMENDOUSLY / PRODIGIOUSLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence, “She discovered that she is your first cousin twice removed,” identify all words derived from Latin and specify which Latin word each is derived from.",
    "answer": "REMOVED – FROM MOVEŌ (TO MOVE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Do the same for this sentence: The princess contemplated her advisor’s request.",
    "answer": "REQUEST – FROM QUAERŌ (TO SEEK / ASK FOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Do the same for this sentence: The building, which you see now, was owned by the twelfth king.",
    "answer": "NO WORDS ARE DERIVED FROM LATIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Virgil’s Aeneid, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: Iuppiter, hospitibus nam tē dāre iura loquuntur, hunc laetum Tyriīsque diem Troiāque profectīs esse velīs, nostrōsque huius meminisse minōrēs. Adsit laetitiae Bacchus dator, et bona Iūnō; et vōs, Ō, coetum, Tyriī, celebrāte faventēs. The question: Quōs laetum diem habere decet?",
    "answer": "TYRIŌS (ET PROFECTŌS TROIĀ)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quī in hōc laetō diē adsunt?",
    "answer": "BACCHUS ET IŪNŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quī legēs ā Iove dantur?",
    "answer": "HOSPITĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which satire of Juvenal, the inspiration for a poem by Samuel Johnson, describes how his old friend Umbricius decides to depart from Rome, as the city has become so dangerous and disgusting that it no longer befits honest men to live there?",
    "answer": "RD SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which satire of Juvenal comically ridicules the emperor Domitian, describing his struggle to decide how to cook an enormous fish, and ultimately serves as an attack on corruption?",
    "answer": "TH SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What is the subject of Juvenal’s 15th satire?",
    "answer": "CANNIBALISM (IN EGYPT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Comprised of blocks of lava or other hard stone, what layer of the road was laid with the greatest care as it was the top layer of the road?",
    "answer": "DORSUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the name of the 6-inch bedding of fine concrete made of potsherds and lime which formed the layer underneath the dorsum.",
    "answer": "NUCLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the name of the curbstones which separated the footpaths from the road?",
    "answer": "UMBO / UMBONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A horse of Pluto according to Claudian, a horse of Helios according to Ovid, a horse of Hector according to Homer, and a fictional son of Deucalion whom Odysseus impersonates during his first meeting with Penelope all had what name?",
    "answer": "AETHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Podarge also mothered the horses Phlogaius and Harpagus who served what twin brothers both on earth and on Olympus?",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What horse, despite his mortality, was still able to keep up with his immortal harness-mates Balius and Xanthus, but unfortunately took a spear to the shoulder meant for his master Patroclus? PEDASUS [Iliad XVI.152-4, 467-8] Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, is not true about the adjective vetus: it is not i-stem, it has irregular comparison, it is defective, it is a synonym of pristinus.",
    "answer": "IT IS DEFECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the comparative and superlative forms of vetus.",
    "answer": "VETUSTIOR, VETERRIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the comparative and superlative forms of dexter.",
    "answer": "DEXTERIOR, DEXTIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “strait”?",
    "answer": "STRINGŌ – TO DRAW TIGHT / BIND / TIE TIGHT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “etiolate.”",
    "answer": "STIPŌ – TO PRESS / PACK TOGETHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “etude”? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "STUDEŌ – TO BE EAGER / BE DILIGENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 219 B.C., the first man of what occupation arrived in Rome from Greece?",
    "answer": "SURGEON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Julius Caesar forbade auctioneers and undertakers from what occupation?",
    "answer": "PUBLIC OFFICE / POLITICS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What occupation did Cicero respect and hold on par with medicine?",
    "answer": "ARCHITECTURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After hearing that Chrosroes had deposed the king of Armenia, which Roman emperor from Italica, Spain, quickly set sail in 113 A.D. and captured the Parthian capital two years later?",
    "answer": "TRAJAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was this Parthian capital, one of many, which Trajan sacked?",
    "answer": "CTESIPHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By defeating the Parthians, Trajan expanded the Roman Empire to its largest size, by establishing the eastern boundary of the empire to be along which two rivers? Mythology:",
    "answer": "TIGRIS & EUPHRATES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Hypseus became a love interest of Apollo when he saw her wrestling a lion?",
    "answer": "CYRENE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What granddaughter of Ares became Apollo’s love interest, though she chose the mortal Idas over him?",
    "answer": "MARPESSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What youth from Amyclae and love interest of Apollo did the god tragically kill? Literature:",
    "answer": "HYACINTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, born in the Arcadian city of Megalopolis to Lycortas, witnessed the destruction of Carthage with Scipio Aemilianus in his later life and argued for a pragmatic approach to history, demonstrated in his 40-book Histories?",
    "answer": "POLYBIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Polybius attributes the greatness of Rome to her constitution. What does Polybius consider to be the ideal form of government, a view which Cicero continues in his De Re Publica? [Accept as long as playrs say something to this effect]",
    "answer": "MIXED GOVERNMENT (OF DEMOCRACY, OLIGARCHY, AND AUTOCRACY)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Pseudo-Lucian, how did Polybius die?",
    "answer": "HE FELL OFF A HORSE (AT THE AGE OF 82)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Etruscan author’s satires preach about the deplorability of avarice and the significance of the principle nosce tē ipsum for those ambitious for political success?",
    "answer": "(AULES) PERSIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which close friend of Persius was the one to publish his works posthumously?",
    "answer": "CAESIUS BASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In which satire does Persius attack those who ask the gods only for money?",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, along with her brother, was given by her parents to be raised by Creon of Corinth only to be later sold back to her father Alcmeon, unbeknownst to them all?",
    "answer": "TISIPHONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was Tisiphone’s mother and who was her brother?",
    "answer": "MANTO & AMPHILOCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why was Tisiphone sold off?",
    "answer": "DECIDED TO SELL HER OFF AS A SLAVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the correct form of the adjective ignōtus to agree with the noun epitomēs.",
    "answer": "IGNŌTAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the correct form of the adjective lentus to agree with the noun comētēs.",
    "answer": "LENTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two alternate forms for the ablative singular of comētēs.",
    "answer": "COMĒTĒ / COMĒTĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which late author, who was tortured to death for allegedly conspiring against Theodoric, wrote his most famous work De Consolatione Philosophiae in the form of a Menippean satire?",
    "answer": "(ANICIUS MANLIUS SEVERINUS) BOETHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What prestigious position did Boethius hold in 522 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER OFFICIORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where does Boethius’s Philosophia argue happiness comes from?",
    "answer": "WITHIN ONE’S SELF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between paelex and supellex.",
    "answer": "PAELEX – MISTRESS / CONCUBINE; SUPELLEX - UTENSILS / FURNITURE / GOODS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between gracilis and grāculus.",
    "answer": "GRACILIS - SLENDER / GRACEFUL; GRĀCULUS - JACKDAW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate among harundō, hirundō, and hirūdō.",
    "answer": "HARUNDŌ - SHAFT / REED; HIRUNDŌ – SWALLOW; HIRŪDŌ - LEECH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which tribune, an uncle of Cato the Younger, attempted to end the equestrian monopoly on the quaestio de rebus repetundis before he was assassinated in 91 B.C.?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS DRUSUS THE YOUNGER / (M.) LIVIUS DRUSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which governor of Asia, the uncle of Livius Drusus, attempted to stop the extortions of the publicani, and as a result, was wrongly convicted in the extortion court and sentenced into exile at Smyrna in 92 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(P.) RUTILIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which consul of 91 B.C. gathered opposition to Drusus and is thought to have hired the assassins who killed him?",
    "answer": "(L. MARCIUS) PHILIPPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin phrase accusāre nēmō sē debet, nisi coram deō may be used in court in what circumstance?",
    "answer": "(WHEN) PLEADING THE FIFTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In ancient Rome, on what type of structure would one find the following words: hōrās nōn nūmerō nisi serēnās?",
    "answer": "SUNDIAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Aside from requiescat in pāce and hic iacet sepultus, what three-word Latin phrase may also be found on a tombstone and is abbreviated as A.A.S.?",
    "answer": "ANNŌ AETĀTIS SUAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What led some Roman forces against the Gauls in 225 B.C., traveled to the Delphic Oracle after the Roman defeat at Cannae in 216 B.C., and was the first Roman historiographer?",
    "answer": "(Q.) FABIUS PICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What historian wrote the Historiae Romanae, which covered the period ranging from the end of the Trojan War to the death of Livia?",
    "answer": "(M.) VELLEIUS PATERCULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What later annalist wrote Histories covering the years 90 to 78 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) SISENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle of the 4th century A.D., fought against the Alamanni, was an example of a small, but skilled army triumphing over an overwhelming numerical disadvantage and proved the capability of the future emperor Julian when he took over the throne four years later?",
    "answer": "STRASBOURG / ARGENTORATUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Ammianus Marcellinus, what king of the Alamanni, defeated at Strasbourg, was the epitome of brute strength and temerity in combat yet cowardice in defeat?",
    "answer": "CHNODOMAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Julian’s predecessor was said to have instigated the Alamanni to invade Gaul to deal with what usurper to the imperial throne?",
    "answer": "MAGNENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Euripides, what wife of Erechtheus granted him permission to sacrifice their daughters in order to secure victory against the Eleusinians led by Eumolpus?",
    "answer": "PRAXITHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What earlier daughter of Cecrops, filled with envy by Athena, was turned into a rock by Hermes?",
    "answer": "AGLAURUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What minor goddess loved Cephalus, causing discord with his wife Procris?",
    "answer": "EOS / AURORA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin: While these plans were being made, it was fitting for us to address the people.",
    "answer": "DECĒBAT / OPORTĒBAT NŌS APPELLĀRE POPULUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Without using an infinitive, translate into Latin: She asked you what she should do.",
    "answer": "QUAESĪVIT / PETĪVIT Ā TĒ / ROGĀVIT TĒ QUID FACTŪRA ESSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a relative pronoun, translate into Latin: But if no one else should follow, he said that he would go with the tenth legion alone.",
    "answer": "DIXIT SĒ CUM SŌLĀ DECIMĀ LEGIŌNE ITŪRUM (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Tacitus’ Annales, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: nōbīs in artō et inglorius labor; immōta quippe aut modice lacessita pax, maestae urbis res et princeps proferendī imperī incuriōsus erat. nōn tamen sine ūsū fuerit introspicere illa prīmō aspectū levia ex quīs magnārum saepe rērum mōtus oriuntur. The question: How does Tacitus describe how one, at first glance, might view the events he writes about? TRIVIAL / LIGHT (from: introspicere illa prīmō aspectū levia)",
    "answer": "30"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Despite this, Tacitus then argues what about these events? (from: ex quīs magnārum saepe rērum mōtus oriuntur)",
    "answer": "THEY OFTEN SET INTO MOTION GREAT EVENTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name two examples that Tacitus considers examples of apparently insignificant history? (from: lacessita pax, maestae urbis res et princeps proferendī imperī incuriōsus erat)",
    "answer": "AN EMPEROR NEGLIGENT IN EXPANDING THE EMPIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claiming to be an illegitimate son of Caligula, which Praetorian Prefect spread the rumor that Nero had fled to Egypt, causing the Praetorian Guard to switch their allegiance to Galba in 68 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(C. NYMPHIDIUS) SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the death of Nero, who, co-Praetorian Prefect with Sabinus and close confidant of Nero, did Sabinus force to retire early on in 68 A.D., so he could become sole Praetorian Prefect?",
    "answer": "(OFONIUS) TIGELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Although Sabinus succeeded in removing Tigellinus as co-Praetorian Prefect, whom did Galba choose to replace Tigellinus, causing Sabinus to regret his support for Galba?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS LACO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into idiomatic English: Sunt quī istam nesciō quam pācem māgnopere laudent. THERE ARE THOSE WHO GREATLY PRAISE PEACE, WHATEVER IT IS [A&G 575b] (accept other equivalent colloquialism to “whatever it is”)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into English: Licet gravissimē mihi nocitum sit, tē numquam relinquam.",
    "answer": "I WILL NEVER LEAVE YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into idiomatic English: Omnēs, simul vīrus bibēre mortuīque sunt, ut urbs ā nostrīs cōpiīs caperētur fēcimus.",
    "answer": "WE ALL SAW TO IT THAT THE CITY BE SEIZED BY OUR TROOPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which 1st century A.D. author, who was so poor that he considered moving to Spain, secured a post at Rome with the help of a certain Meliboeus and flattered Nero in his seven eclogues, which are transmitted along with those of Nemesianus?",
    "answer": "(TITUS) CALPURNIUS SICULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Sharing his name with another author, which playwright under Caligula wrote Phasma and Laureolus and featured special effects such as an onstage crucifixion?",
    "answer": "CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Roman tragedian was forced to commit suicide in 34 A.D. because of unflattering allusions to Tiberius in his play Atreus?",
    "answer": "31"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Book VII of the Aeneid is a lot of things, including a display of Virgil’s creativity in inventing weapons. Accompanied by warriors with a boot only on their right foot and armed with blue lead pellets, what son of Vulcan brings men from Gabii and his hometown of Praeneste to support Turnus?",
    "answer": "CAECULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Curiously called Agamemnonius, what man leads troops from Aurunca and Cales armed with leashed javelins, shields, and curved scimitars?",
    "answer": "HALAESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Virgil further describes the soldiers of what son of Telon and the nymph Sebethis, who use corktree bark helmets and throw their spears “in the Teuton fashion,” although what exactly Virgil meant by that is unclear?",
    "answer": "OEBALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What late Republican figure served as proconsul of Gallia Comata but was perhaps most famous for suggesting the title Augustus to the Senate?",
    "answer": "(L. MUNATIUS) PLANCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Plancus held what office in 22 B.C., which was abolished until the appointment of Lucius Vitellius in 47 A.D.?",
    "answer": "CENSOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Suetonius’s De Vita Caesarum, who, the ancestor of Nero, forced Plancus to make way for him in the streets, even though he was only an aedile?",
    "answer": "(L.) DOMITIUS AHENOBARBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The nouns altāria, nōnae, hīberna, and angustiae all belong to what category of words?",
    "answer": "PLŪRĀLIA TANTUM / PLURAL-ONLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a singular-only Latin noun meaning “wheat.”",
    "answer": "TRĪTICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two different plural-only Latin nouns for types of doors.",
    "answer": "VALVAE / FORĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence, “I requested that the scout’s uncle come to the castle at noon,” identify all words derived from Latin.",
    "answer": "REQUEST, SCOUT, UNCLE, CASTLE, NOON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence, “The count and I disagree on whether it takes a village to raise a child,” identify all words derived from Latin.",
    "answer": "COUNT, DISAGREE, VILLAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For four of the words you have identified, give the Latin words, and their meanings, from which each is derived.",
    "answer": "32"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Perhaps an Ancient Roman equivalent to SparkNotes, what work of Roman history, later translated into Greek by Paeanius, covers the time of Romulus to the death of Jovian in 364 A.D., and was written at the request of the emperor Valens as an abridgement of the works of Livy and other historians?",
    "answer": "BREVIARIUM AB URBE CONDITA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who was the author of the Breviarium ab Urbe Condita?",
    "answer": "EUTROPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other, more well-known abridgements of Livy were written around the 4th century A.D., and survive intact to this day, save for just two sections?",
    "answer": "PERIOCHAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who rejects nomos, or manmade law, in favor of physis, or divine law, when she says, “I did not believe your proclamation had such power to enable one who will someday die to override the gods’ ordinances, unwritten and secure. They are not of today and yesterday; they live forever; none knows when first they were. These are the laws whose penalties I would not incur from the gods, through fear of any man’s temper,” as she disobeys her uncle Creon by burying her brother Polyneices?",
    "answer": "ANTIGONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Sophocles’ Antigone, Creon’s anger and misogyny can be seen when he declares that “there are other fields for him to plow” in response to whose question of whether Creon would kill his son’s wife to be?",
    "answer": "ISMENE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Creon’s inflexibility and decision to sentence Antigone to death ultimately leave him in a state of living death, as he is forced to cope with the subsequent deaths of what two loved ones? Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the Latin adjective putus?",
    "answer": "PURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the Latin noun putus?",
    "answer": "BOY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The adjective putus gives us the Latin verb putō, which we commonly define as “to think.” What other meaning can putō have?",
    "answer": "TO TRIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: erudition, rigmarole, corrugate, rouge, route, rowel?",
    "answer": "RIGMAROLE & ROWEL (FROM ROTA – WHEEL)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: ensign, savagery, sergeant, season, seminary, sexton?",
    "answer": "SEASON & SEMINARY (FROM SERŌ – TO JOIN TOGETHER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: umpire, annex, niece, nonchalance, enervate, announce? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "UMPIRE & NONCHALANCE (FROM NŌN – NOT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Initially appointed commander of Upper Germany by Galba in 69 A.D., what senator and general, stationed at Novaesium, was indecisive in both swearing allegiances to either Vitellius or Vespasian?",
    "answer": "HORDEONIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the midst of Hordeonius Flaccus’ inaction in the Batavian rebellion, what overzealous general took inconclusive action against Julius Civilis and was later killed by Julius Classicus and Tutor?",
    "answer": "DILLIUS VOCULA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What commander of the Lower Rhine instigated the rebellion of Julius Civilis? Mythology:",
    "answer": "FONTEIUS CAPITO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "On what island did Nauplius falsely signal to the Greek ships, causing them to crash on rocks?",
    "answer": "CAPHAREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Nauplius’s informed him of Palamedes’ death?",
    "answer": "OEAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Oeax get the information to Nauplius? Literature:",
    "answer": "AND THREW IT IN THE OCEAN CERTAIN THAT IT WOULD REACH NAUPLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Medea, Saturnalia, Iliacon, Catachthonion, Silvae, and De Incendio Urbis were all written by which Roman author who managed to be appointed quaestor before the minimum age by law?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS ANNAEUS) LUCAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term describes the tone with which Lucan asserted his poem against Vergil’s?",
    "answer": "INDIGNATIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What phrase did Quintilian use to describe Lucan?",
    "answer": "34"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The antiquarian Lucius Aelius Stilo and the philosopher Antiochus of Ascalon were both teachers of what prolific Latin author?",
    "answer": "VARRO REATINUS / (M.) TERENTIUS VARRO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To which tragedian is Varro’s De Antiquitate Litterarum dedicated to?",
    "answer": "ACCIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which work of Varro, does he establish key points about Rome’s origin?",
    "answer": "RES HUMANAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Cicero, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: Et quoniam L. Torquātus, meus familiāris ac necessārius, iūdicēs, existimāvit, sī nostram in accūsātiōne suā necessitūdinem familiāritātemque violasset, aliquid sē dē auctōritāte meae dēfensiōnis posse dētrahere, cum huius perīculī prōpulsātiōne coniungam dēfensiōnem officī meī. The question: Whom is Cicero addressing here?",
    "answer": "THE JUDGES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does Cicero consider Lucius Torquatus to be?",
    "answer": "HIS RELATIVE / KIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What could Torquatus do to Cicero’s authority of his defense?",
    "answer": "DETRACT FROM IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "As a child, what son of Ctesius was lured by his Phoenician nurse to the ship of merchants and was sold as a slave to Laertes, for whom he then worked as a swineherd?",
    "answer": "EUMAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What goatherd of Odysseus betrayed his master by bringing weapons to the suitors and was punished by being hung from the rafters?",
    "answer": "MELANTHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Melanthius and his equally treacherous sister Melantho were the children of what loyal, old servant of Odysseus?",
    "answer": "DOLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin noun meaning “threshold” means “denoting an action or event preceding or done in preparation for something fuller or more important” and describes the round which you are in?",
    "answer": "PRELIMINARY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin verb meaning “it is permitted” means “use of free time for enjoyment”?",
    "answer": "LEISURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin verb meaning “to bind” means “a mass meeting of people making a political protest or showing support for a cause”?",
    "answer": "RALLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quaestor in 237 BC, censor in 230 BC, and consul five times, what man had the notable cognomen Verrucosus, meaning “warty,” but is best known for the attrition warfare with Hannibal for which he received the agnomen Cunctator?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) FABIUS MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Where in 217 BC did Hannibal escape Quintus Fabius Maximus through his ingenious use of oxen?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) AGER FALERNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During his first consulship in 233 BC, Quintus Fabius Maximus celebrated a triumph over what Italian tribe living in Cisalpine Gaul?",
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catullus 64 focuses not only on the marriage of Peleus and Thetis, but also, though ekphrasis, on the betrayal and abandonment of what maiden by what hero?",
    "answer": "ARIADNE BY THESEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Shorter but similar in form to an epic, what type of poem is Catullus 64?",
    "answer": "EPYLLION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catullus 64 was one of the longer poems in Catullus’ libellus, which he dedicated to whom?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS NEPOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What name in mythology is shared by a son of Eos who was carried off by Aphrodite to become warden of her shrine and a son of Helios whose tragic death caused his sisters to turn into poplar trees?",
    "answer": "PHAËTHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The latter Phaethon’s sisters supposedly wept what substance upon the death of their brother?",
    "answer": "AMBER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Liguria and friend of Phaethon left his people to mourn among the poplars, being transformed into a swan?",
    "answer": "CYCNUS / CYGNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate idiomatically into English: Cicerō ad patrēs conscriptōs orātiōnem habuit ut causam ageret.",
    "answer": "CICERO DELIVERED A SPEECH TO THE SENATORS TO PLEAD (HIS) CASE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate idiomatically into English: Multā nocte, Caesar mīlitēs hortātus est nē in Germaniam iter facerent.",
    "answer": "NOT TO JOURNEY INTO GERMANY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate idiomatically into English: Apud Marcum, eī, quī rēbus novīs studēbant, consilium cēpērunt.",
    "answer": "CAME UP WITH / HATCHED A PLAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding all forms of alliteration, identify the rhetorical device found in the following phrase from Book 6 of the Aeneid: Illa sōlō fixōs oculōs adversa tenēbat.",
    "answer": "CHIASMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding all forms of alliteration, identify the rhetorical device found in the following phrase from Book 6 of the Aeneid: Mīnōtaurus inest, Veneris monimenta nefandae.",
    "answer": "METONYMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding all forms of alliteration, identify the rhetorical device found in the following phrase from Book 4 of the Aeneid: Ūritur infēlix Dīdō tōtaque vagātur, urbe furens, quālis coniecta cerva sagitta.",
    "answer": "SIMILE / EXTENDED METAPHOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who snatched victory from the jaws of defeat at the battle of Margus River in 285 AD, beating Carinus and paving the way for the creation of the Tetrarchy?",
    "answer": "DIOCLETIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which edict, issued by Diocletian in 302 AD, placed a price ceiling on all things from wheat and barley to bed linens and craftsmen’s wages?",
    "answer": "EDICT ON MAXIMUM PRICES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Against which Persian king did Diocletian and Galerius wage a war, culminating in the capture of Nisibis and the sack of Ctesiphon?",
    "answer": "NARSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "An event deviating greatly from what is expected is called a “black swan,” a reference to a quotation by what Roman author, who gave this as an example of a rare bird?",
    "answer": "JUVENAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Give the entire quotation from Juvenal’s Satires, which starts with rāra and ends with cȳcno.",
    "answer": "RĀRA AVIS IN TERRĪS NIGRŌQUE SIMILLIMA CȲCNŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The English sentence “John and Judy are rara avises” is technically fine, but using you are Latin students! Give the alternative English plural of rara avis that better maintains its Latin origin.",
    "answer": "RARAE AVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, who was said to have been born in Terni, began his political career under Vespasian, became consul suffectus in 97 A.D., delivered Virginius Rufus’ funeral oration, and wrote a biography of his father-in-law Agricola?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS / GAIUS CORNELIUS) TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The description of the punishments suffered by the Christians after the Great Fire of 64 A.D. appears in what historical work of Tacitus?",
    "answer": "ANNALES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "With his friend’s help, Tacitus prosecuted the ex-governor Marius Priscus for his crimes against Africa. Name this friend, who later became the governor of Bithynia.",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER / GAIUS PLINIUS SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Phantasos, Icelos, and Morpheus were all sons of what god, the personification of sleep?",
    "answer": "HYPNOS / SOMNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "All three of Hypnos’s children could appear in dreams, each taking a specific form. What form did Morpheus take?",
    "answer": "HUMANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What forms did Icelos and Phantasos take, respectively?",
    "answer": "ANIMALS; INANIMATE OBJECTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Though lacking a perfect passive participle, what Latin verb has a fourth principal part, when given in dictionary entries, since its future active participle futūrus is used instead?",
    "answer": "SUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What compound of sum means “to be lacking”?",
    "answer": "DĒSUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What compound of sum means “to be in charge of” and takes the dative case?",
    "answer": "PRAESUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to the Roman historian Festus, what office in Roman Republic was considered the highest ranked of all priests though he was a figurehead performing minor religious duties assigned to the king during the Monarchy?",
    "answer": "REX SACRORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What title was fittingly given to the wife of the rex sacrorum?",
    "answer": "REGINA SACRORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify two of the three groups of priests classified under flamines maiores.",
    "answer": "(FLAMEN) DIALIS / MARTIALIS / QUIRINALIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the adjective incarcerātus, say in Latin: I do not know why the caged bird sings.",
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using quaerō, say in Latin: I asked you from where you had received that money.",
    "answer": "Ā TĒ QUAESĪVĪ UNDE ILLAM PECŪNIAM ACCĒPISSĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using rogō, say in Latin: I asked you to buy that for me as quickly as possible.",
    "answer": "TĒ ROGĀVĪ UT ILLUD MIHI QUAM CELERRIMĒ EMERĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What satirist frequently used vocabulary of the body, most often the imagery of the stomach, in his 6 books of satires, and was a good friend of Lucan?",
    "answer": "(AULES) PERSIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Where in Etruria was Persius born?",
    "answer": "VOLTERRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Stoic teacher of Persius served as a great influence on his Satires?",
    "answer": "CORNUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When translated into Latin, the sentence “Messenger, what news do you have for me?” can contain a genitive. Provide the Latin for that genitive word and identify its usage.",
    "answer": "NOVĪ; PARTITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When translated into Latin, the sentence “The messenger walked into the city Athens” can contain a genitive. Provide the Latin for that genitive word and identify its usage.",
    "answer": "ATHĒNĀRUM; APPOSITIONAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When translated into Latin, the sentence “The messenger has a reputation for boldness” contains a genitive. Provide the Latin for that genitive word and identify its usage.",
    "answer": "AUDĀCIAE; OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Called a “beautiful evil” by Hesiod, who was given a human voice by Hephaestus, taught crafts and weaving by Athena, and given charm as well as terrible longing cares by Aphrodite, before being sent by Hermes as a gift to Epimetheus?",
    "answer": "PANDORA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Epimetheus and Pandora had a daughter named Pyrrha who would marry her cousin Deucalion. Who were the Deucalion’s parents?",
    "answer": "PROMETHEUS AND PRONOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The story of Pandora in Hesiod’s Works and Days precedes his telling of the Ages of Man, during which Hesiod laments being a part of which age?",
    "answer": "IRON AGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Alliteratively translate into Latin the phrase “by means of a very bad apple.”",
    "answer": "PŌMŌ PESSIMŌ / PESSIMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Alliteratively translate into Latin the phrase “of an ivory sword.”",
    "answer": "ENSIS EBURNEĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Alliteratively translate into Latin the phrase “by means of a small ship.”",
    "answer": "PUPPĪ PARVĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s experiences at the siege of Numantia led him to observe Rome as an “urbem vēnālem et mātūrē peritūram, sī emptōrem invēnerit,” though he was unable to buy victory when he waged war with the Romans from 112-106 BC?",
    "answer": "JUGURTHA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jugurtha was survived only by his son Oxyntas, of which hardly anything is known except that he participated in what later war?",
    "answer": "THE SOCIAL / MARSIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the two half-brothers of Jugurtha with which he quarreled over control of Numidia. Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "HIEMPSAL & ADHERBAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Predecessor” and “procedure” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CĒDŌ – TO YIELD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Caress” and “charity” are derived from what Latin adjective with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CĀRUS – CARING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Ceiling” and “cerulean” are derived from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CAELUM – SKY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin motto of the Olympic Games?",
    "answer": "CITIUS, ALTIUS, FORTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "As you probably know, the Olympic Games’ motto consists of three comparative adjectives. What state motto consists of one comparative adjective?",
    "answer": "NEW YORK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase that can mean “being without examination or analysis” also contains a comparative adjective? Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "Ā PRIŌRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Calydon, who killed his son Toxeus for jumping over a ditch, failed to sacrifice the first fruits of the harvest to Artemis and was punished for the insult with a giant boar?",
    "answer": "OENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Oeneus eventually killed the monster, although he gave the skin to Atalanta?",
    "answer": "MELEAGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Oeneus’ wife Althaea later killed herself out of guilt for her role in Meleager’s death, causing Oeneus to marry what woman, who bore him Olenias and Tydeus? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "PERIBOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Bloodless offerings such as flowers, wine, and incense were given to one’s Genius or Iuno on what special day?",
    "answer": "(A PERSON’S) BIRTHDAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What color were the garments worn during the celebration?",
    "answer": "WHITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman term describes the day on which a child received his/her name? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "DIES LUSTRICUS / DIES NŌMINUM / NŌMINĀLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, the first to employ alliteration in dactylic hexameter, was ranked last on Volcacius Sedigitus’ list merely because of his earliness?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Because of which author’s earlier work is it believed Ennius must have written on the First Punic War with much concision in his Annales?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) NAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what public records does the title of Ennius’ magnum opus refer to?",
    "answer": "ROUND 2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, born in 26 AD, was said to have purchased the tomb of Vergil and practically worshipped the poet?",
    "answer": "SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Giving credence to the maxim “Quality over quantity,” which of Silius Italicus’ works was the longest yet supposedly worst Latin epic?",
    "answer": "PUNICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Silius Italicus die?",
    "answer": "SUICIDE BY STARVATION TO DEATH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb pōnō, give the future passive infinitive.",
    "answer": "POSITUM ĪRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What do forms of deus can deum be?",
    "answer": "ACC. SG., GEN. PL."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate between the forms pōnentis and pōnentīs.",
    "answer": "PŌNENTĪS – ACC. PL. PRES. ACT. PART."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Iphiclus left Phylace and his newly-wedded wife Laodameia to go Troy, never to see either again, since he perished as soon as he set foot on Trojan soil?",
    "answer": "PROTESILAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the Trojans killed Protesilaus as he arrived at Troy?",
    "answer": "HECTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What brother of Protesilaus assumed control of the Phylacian contingent upon the death of Protesilaus?",
    "answer": "PODARCES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose death at Lorium ended a remarkable reign, one free of any significant uprisings or military campaigns and shorter only to Augustus’ reign during the Principate?",
    "answer": "ANTONINUS PIUS’"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the Principate, which emperor reigned the third longest after Augustus and Antoninus Pius?",
    "answer": "TIBERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Antoninus Pius was the last emperor born in the 1st century AD. Who was the last emperor born in the 1st century BC?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify the case and use of senatōribus in the following sentence: Hīs verbīs dictīs, senātōribus persuādendum erit.",
    "answer": "DATIVE WITH SPECIAL VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate that sentence.",
    "answer": "WITH THESE WORDS SPOKEN, THE SENATORS WILL HAVE TO BE PERSUADED."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Explain why persuādeō takes the dative.",
    "answer": "7"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: Follow me to Sicily, soldiers.",
    "answer": "SEQUIMINI MĒ AD SICILIAM, MĪLITĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: I thought the men who followed me were Gauls.",
    "answer": "SCIŌ VIRŌS, QUĪ MĒ SECŪTĪ ESSENT, GALLŌS ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: Let us follow the leader most worthy of command!",
    "answer": "DŪCEM DIGNISSIMUM IMPERIŌ SEQUĀMUR!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What historian, who composed philosophical dialogues in his youth, turned to history at the age of 30 and devoted himself to a massive historical work of 142 books entitled Ab Urbe Condita?",
    "answer": "(TITUS) LIVIUS / LIVY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Although only 35 books remain of Livy’s work, we possess summaries for most of the lost books. What is the term for these summaries?",
    "answer": "PERIOCHAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Livy encouraged the historiographic interests of what emperor?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: Marcus Antōnius ingens bellum cīvīle commōvit cōgente uxōre Cleopātrā dum cupīditāte muliebrī optat etiam in urbe regnāre. Marcus Antōnius victus est ab Augustō in nāvālī pugnā clarā et illustrī apud Actium, quī locus in Ēpīrō est, ex quā in Aegyptum fūgit et, cum omnēs ad Augustum transīrent, ipse sē interfēcit. Cleopātra sibi aspidem admīsit et venēnō eius extincta est. The question: Quāle proelium erat apud Actium?",
    "answer": "NAVĀLE / CLĀRUM / ILLUSTRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quis coēgit Antōnium ut bellum commoveret?",
    "answer": "CLEOPĀTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quōmodo Cleopātra extincta est?",
    "answer": "ASPIDE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Originally called Strongyle, which of the Cyclades was the site of Butes’s rape of Coronis, the deaths of Otus and Ephialtes, and the birth of Dionysus, although it is more famous for being the location where Dionysus found the mourning Ariadne?",
    "answer": "NAXOS / DIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the sister of the Aloadae, who was kidnapped by pirates and taken to Naxos.",
    "answer": "PANCRATIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the mother of the Aloadae, who was also kidnapped and taken there.",
    "answer": "IMPHIMEDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to legend, what foreign king was buried under the Busentus River by his soldiers in 410 AD, the same year he sacked Rome?",
    "answer": "ALARIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Alaric attempted to siege Rome in 408 and 409 AD, in what city was the emperor Honorius hiding?",
    "answer": "RAVENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What urban prefect had been declared emperor in place of the missing Honorius?",
    "answer": "PRISCUS ATTALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: empress, severance, imperial, parasol, or parapet? NONE (all are derived from parō)",
    "answer": "8"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: reappear, disparage, apparent, apparition, or transparent?",
    "answer": "DISPARAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: parcel, repartee, tripartite participant, or particle? NONE (all are derived from pars)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When one of his bull wandered into the kingdom of Eryx, what hero was forced to wrestle with the Sicilian king Eryx, a match that he handily won?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eryx was the son of Aphrodite by the Argonaut Butes or by which god?",
    "answer": "POSEIDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What descendant of Eryx welcomes Aeneas to Sicily in the Aeneid?",
    "answer": "ACESTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The claim of being his mistress’ slave, the pursuit of love rather than a military career, the stories of Tarpeia and Vertumnus, and the love affair with Cynthia all appear in the elegies of what Umbrian poet?",
    "answer": "(SEXTUS) PROPERTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The fourth book of Propertius’ elegies, unlike the preceding books, do not discuss Propertius’ relationship with Cynthia. Instead, they recount the origins of Roman myths in a manner similar to the Aitia of which Hellenistic poet?",
    "answer": "CALLIMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Propertius also took inspiration from what poet from Cos who wrote the highly acclaimed Demeter?",
    "answer": "PHILITAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Plutarch, what man served as a foil to military commanders by conquering more cities in Greece through eloquence than his advisee, Pyrrhus, did through arms?",
    "answer": "CINEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After the Battle of Heraclea, what aged senator prevented another such “conquest” by persuading his colleagues to unanimously reject the tempting peace terms offered by Cineas?",
    "answer": "APPIUS CLAUDIUS CAECUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Given Rome’s past, it is quite ironic that Cineas likened the Roman senators to an assembly of what?",
    "answer": "KINGS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Amantium īrae amoris integratiōst, Senectus ipsast morbus, and Fortis fortūna adiuvat are all phrases attributed to what Roman playwright?",
    "answer": "TERENCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What phrase of Terence expresses the fact that there is considerable diversity of opinion and thus a difficulty of bringing about agreement?",
    "answer": "QUOT HOMINĒS TOT SENTENTIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What phrase of Terence indicates that something can be understood without any need for explanation, if the listener has enough wisdom or common sense?",
    "answer": "DICTUM SAPIENTĪ SAT EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Euboean was nursed by Gaia to enormous size and eventually attempted to rape Leto as she went to Delphi through Panopeus?",
    "answer": "TITYUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What mother of Tityus did Zeus hide in the earth to shield her from the vengeance of Hera?",
    "answer": "ELARES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of animals ate Tityus’ liver as he was stretched over nine acres?",
    "answer": "VULTURES / SNAKES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does the phrase simul atque mean?",
    "answer": "AS SOON AS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give a synonym of simul atque.",
    "answer": "CUM PRĪMUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does the correlative cum … tum mean?",
    "answer": "BOTH … AND / NOT ONLY … BUT ALSO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pompeius Muscosus, Marcus Aurelius Liber, Publius Aelius Gutta Calpurnianus, and Gaius Apuleius Diocles were all memorialized in inscriptions for their great number of victories in what Roman spectacle?",
    "answer": "CHARIOT-RACING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Described in Book 5 of Virgil’s Aeneid, there were occasionally exhibitions of horsemanship by young men of the nobility in the Circus, when chariot races were not taking place. What were these exhibitions called?",
    "answer": "LUDUS / LUDI TROIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "More exciting to the spectators, though, were the gory venationes, or hunts. Which of the following animals, if any, were not among those slaughtered at these hunts: panthers, bears, lions, elephants, hippopotamuses, or crocodiles? NONE (all were slaughtered)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Putēs eum hominem bonum esse.",
    "answer": "YOU MIGHT THINK THAT HE IS A GOOD MAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Utinam nē meō cibō vescantur!",
    "answer": "WOULD THAT THEY NOT EAT MY FOOD!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Quid nōn facerēs?",
    "answer": "WHAT WERE YOU NOT TO DO?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Silver Age author’s attempt to create an inventory of all the knowledge of man resulted in a 37- book encyclopedic work called the Naturalis Historia?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER / (GAIUS) PLINIUS (SECUNDUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom was the Naturalis Historia dedicated?",
    "answer": "TITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Pliny the Elder is a historical work on the German campaigns? Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "BELLA GERMANIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the infinitives for the verb moveō.",
    "answer": "MOVĒRE, MOVĒRĪ, MOVISSE, MŌTUS ESSE, MŌTŪRUS ESSE, MŌTUM ĪRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Do the same for the verb conor.",
    "answer": "CŌNĀRĪ, CŌNĀTUS ESSE, CŌNĀTŪRUS ESSE, CŌNĀTUM ĪRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Do the same for the verb supersum.",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: temerē?",
    "answer": "RASHLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: pharētra?",
    "answer": "QUIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: iūdicium? Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "TRIAL / JUDGMENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which priest of Dionysus loved a girl in Calydon and asked for help from Dionysus?",
    "answer": "CORESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom was the girl he loved?",
    "answer": "CALLIRRHOË"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was interesting about the fact that Coresus killed himself for Callirrhoë? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "SHE KILLED HERSELF AFTER SEEING HIS DEAD BODY"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At the Battle of Watling Street, Suetonius Paulinus finally put an end to whose revolt in Britain during the reign of Nero?",
    "answer": "BOUDIC(E)A"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What capital city of the Trinovantes did Boudica and her soldiers raze?",
    "answer": "CAMULODUNUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Boudica’s revolt was inspired particularly by the Romans annexation of her territory, which disrespected the will of her husband. Who was her husband? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "PRASUTAGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, born around 82 B.C., was part of the cantores Euphorionis and wrote works including Ephemeris, Chorographia, Bellum Sequanicum, and Argonautae?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS TERENTIUS) VARRO ATACINUS / VARRO OF ATAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the topic of Ephemeris, perhaps a nod to Aratus’ Phaenoemna?",
    "answer": "WEATHER (SIGNS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the name of Varro’s mistress, who is the eponymous title of his collection of erotic poetry?",
    "answer": "ROUND 3"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Romans’ stigma against Oriental women due to memories of Cleopatra forced what daughter of Herod Agrippa I to be abandoned by her lover when he became emperor after his father Vespasian’s death?",
    "answer": "BERENICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Christian woman was the mistress of Commodus?",
    "answer": "MARCIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After her husband’s death, what Eastern woman sought legitimacy to her rule of Egypt through supposed descent from Cleopatra?",
    "answer": "ZENOBIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to gender: sanguis, rugītus, procus, praeses, or rūpes?",
    "answer": "RŪPES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which word from the tossup would be described by the sentence: Sī ūnum habēs, salvus sentis?",
    "answer": "PRAESES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which word from the tossup would be described by the sentence: Pēnelopē multōs habet?",
    "answer": "PROCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Melete, Mneme, and Aeode were the original three members of what group who resided on either Mount Helicon or Mount Parnassus?",
    "answer": "MUSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nine sisters lost to the Muses in a music contest and were transformed into magpies?",
    "answer": "PIERIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What bard also lost to the Muses and was a result was blinded?",
    "answer": "THAMYRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Imperātor, quī sē nōn contineat, exercitum continēre nōn potest.",
    "answer": "IS NOT ABLE TO RESTRAIN THE ARMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The relative clause of characteristic has its origins in another use of the subjunctive and is the origin of yet another use of the subjunctive. Identify both, respectively.",
    "answer": "POTENTIAL; RESULT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Tālis clamor in cūriā factus est ut populus convenīret.",
    "answer": "THAT THE PEOPLE CAME TOGETHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Excluding compound verbs, identify two verbs that often used with ablative of price.",
    "answer": "VERTŌ & MUTŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tantī and magnī can exemplify what analogous use of the genitive?",
    "answer": "INDEFINITE VALUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in Latin: It happened that the king traded his kingdom for a horse.",
    "answer": "12"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pugil, Epistula, Synaristosae, Epicleros, and Plocium were all written by what Insubrian Gaul, considered the best comedic writer by Volcacius Sedigitus?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Most of Caecilius Statius’s writing is extant through the writings of what later author of the Attic Nights?",
    "answer": "AULUS GELLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After what battle of 222 BC was Caecilius Statius brought to Rome?",
    "answer": "CLASTIDIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Driven from Jutland and Schleswig by overpopulation, what two tribes inflicted on Rome a loss of 80,000 men at the Battle of Arausio of 105 BC?",
    "answer": "CIMBRI & TEUTONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the names of the Roman commanders who were humiliated and defeated by the Cimbri and Teutones at Arausio.",
    "answer": "(CN.) MALLIUS (MAXIMUS) & (Q.) (SERVILIUS) CAEPIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Marius eventually defeated the Teutones and Cimbri in 102 and 101 BC, respectively. Name the corresponding battles.",
    "answer": "AQUAE SEXTIAE; VERCELLAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using crēdō and a synonym of ille say in Latin: Surely we’ve trusted that one sailor?",
    "answer": "NONNE ISTĪ ŪNĪ NAUTAE CRĒDIDIMUS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now using a semi-deponent synonym of crēdō, say in Latin: These sailors always trusted us.",
    "answer": "HĪ NAUTAE SEMPER NŌBĪS FĪSĪ SUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now using a semi-deponent verb in both the protasis and apodosis, say in Latin: If these sailors had trusted us, we would have rejoiced.”",
    "answer": "SĪ HĪ NAUTAE NŌBĪS FĪSĪ ESSENT, GAVĪSĪ ESSĒMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Shakespeare’s A Comedy of Errors was inspired by what play of Plautus, which tells the story of two twins who meet each other for the first time as adults in the city of Epidamnus?",
    "answer": "MENAECHMI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What play of Plautus contains the only extant passages of the Carthaginian language?",
    "answer": "POENULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What play of Plautus concerns the slave Phronesium, who cheats her three lovers?",
    "answer": "TRUCULENTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Anoerestus and Concolitanus led the Gallic assault against the Romans but were defeated by Gaius Atilius Regulus and Lucius Aemilius Papus at what battle of 225 BC?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) CAPE TELAMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which tribune of 232 BC’s land redistribution policies alarmed the Gauls into attacking the Romans?",
    "answer": "(C.) FLAMINIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Flaminius had a habit of supporting populist policies despite becoming a senator. In fact, which tribune of 218 BC’s law prohibiting senators and their sons from performing transactions was Flaminius the only senator to support?",
    "answer": "(Q.) CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood, fully parse the verb form portābāre. nd PERS. SG. IMPERF. PASS. INDIC.",
    "answer": "13"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood, fully parse the verb form portāverē. rd PERS. PL. PERF. ACT. INDIC.",
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood, fully parse the verb form māvīs. nd PERS. SG. PRES. ACT. INDIC.",
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythical thief could change the color and form of stolen objects—an ability he put to good use when he stole a helmet from Amyntor’s armory and carried off the cattle of Eurytus?",
    "answer": "AUTOLYCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who won Eurytus’ daughter Iole in an archery contest, did Autolycus blame for this theft?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Daedalion was the father of Autolycus by Hermes?",
    "answer": "CHIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, a Sabine who had a rocky political career, followed in the footsteps of Coelius Antipater in rejecting the annalistic tradition and instead, wrote monographs titled Bellum Iugurthinum and Bellum Catilinae?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SALLUST(IUS) (CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the year of Sallust’s birth.",
    "answer": "86 BC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sallust’s Historiae, an unfinished treatise covering the years 78 to 67 BC, consists of how many books?",
    "answer": "FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Based on its derivation, what does the word “sortilege” mean?",
    "answer": "READING / DIVINATION BY LOTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Based on its derivation, what does the word “amanuensis” mean? SECRETARY/SCRIBE (accept any similar job requiring primarily use of one’s hands)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Based on its origins, what is a “Maecenas”?",
    "answer": "PATRON (OF THE ARTS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The usurper Leucus seized upon what man’s absence during the Trojan War, seducing and killing his wife Meda and driving him from Crete upon his return?",
    "answer": "IDOMENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What father of Palamedes had instigated this usurpation?",
    "answer": "NAUPLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Cretan had been Idomeneus’ second-in-command at Troy and survived the war, although his subsequent fate is unknown?",
    "answer": "MERIONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author began his career in law, having studied under Arellius Fuscus and Porcius Latro, but later abandoned his legal career to write works like Ibis, Epistulae ex Ponto, Tristia, and Amores?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) OVID(IUS NASO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of his works, for the most part, contains letters from various heroines to their lovers?",
    "answer": "HEROIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In letters 16-21, there are 3 pairs of lovers for which both the male and female wrote. Name one such pair.",
    "answer": "14"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following abbreviations, if any, would not be inscribed on a tombstone: D.M., H.J.S., NONE (all belong)",
    "answer": "R.I.P., S.T.T.L.?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give both the Latin and English for the abbreviation D.M.",
    "answer": "DĪS MANIBUS – TO THE SPIRITS OF THE DEAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give both the Latin and English for the abbreviation S.T.T.L.",
    "answer": "SIT TERRA TIBI LEVIS – MAY THE EARTH REST LIGHTLY ON YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nurse of Myrrha helped her lay with Cinyras and shares her name with a daughter of Ares who possessed a magical girdle?",
    "answer": "HIPPOLYTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the mother of Myrrha?",
    "answer": "CENCHREÏS / METHARME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Besides Cinyras with either Myrrha or Metharme, what couple may have been the parents of Adonis?",
    "answer": "PHOENIX & ALPHESIBOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "According to Vitruvius, what Roman siege weapon, its precursor the Greek oxybeles, resembled large crossbows and would hurl large rocks to destroy enemy walls?",
    "answer": "BALLISTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The onager was a Roman catapulta named for its resemblance to what kind of animal?",
    "answer": "DONKEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What catapulta was named for its resemblance to an animal the Romans considered a type of fish?",
    "answer": "SCORPIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Julius Caesar, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: Haec cīvitas longē plūrimum tōtius Galliae equitātū valet magnāsque habet copiās peditum Rhēnumque, ut sūprā dēmonstrāvimus, tangit. In eā cīvitāte duo dē principātū inter sē contendēbant, Indutiomarus et Cingetorix. The question: The state which Caesar describes here borders what geographical feature?",
    "answer": "THE RHINE RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what two military aspects does this state excel?",
    "answer": "INFANTRY & CAVALRY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What were Indutiomarus and Cingetorix fighting for? Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "RULE OVER THE STATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence “Solōne dūce, Athēnae insulā potitae est,” identify both uses of the ablative.",
    "answer": "ABSOLUTE & WITH DEPONENT VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word meaning “skilled” can take both the ablative and the genitive?",
    "answer": "PERĪTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Verbs like memini often take the genitive. What synonym of memini involves an ablative word?",
    "answer": "MEMORIĀ TENĒRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the principle parts of the Latin deponent verb meaning “to forget.”",
    "answer": "15"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the principle parts of the Latin verb meaning either “to complain.”",
    "answer": "QUEROR, QUERĪ, QUESTUS SUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the principle parts of the Latin deponent verb meaning “to promise.” Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "POLLICEOR, POLLICĒRĪ, POLLICITUS SUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Minos vanished while chasing a mouse and was later found drowned in a vat of honey by the seer Poyleidus, who then resurrected him?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Minos had earlier learned from an oracle that strange events were afoot in Crete and the man who could find the aptest simile to describe them would find his son. To what did Polyeidus compare a calf which was changing color daily from white to red to black?",
    "answer": "STAGES OF A RIPENING MULBERRY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some say that it was not Polyeidus, but rather what man who revived Glaucus? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "ASCLEPIUS / AESCULAPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gannicus, Castus, Crixus, and Oenamaus were four Gallic gladiators that led a major slave uprising with what Thracian man?",
    "answer": "SPARTACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Spartacus was trained at the gladiator school of what man?",
    "answer": "LENTULUS BATIATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of gladiator was Spartacus? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "MURMILLO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, born in Madura, married his best friend’s widowed mother Pudentilla?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) APULEIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was that best friend of his?",
    "answer": "PONTIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of his was considered a reworking of Peri Kosmou and is one of the earlier times writers have tried to incorporate the technical natural sciences into Latin?",
    "answer": "SEMIFINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of Amherst College, Dartmouth College, Hunter College, Indiana University Bloomington, and University of Chicago, which contains a subjunctive within its Latin motto.",
    "answer": "UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the institutions listed in the toss up, which one contains a participle within its motto?",
    "answer": "DARTMOUTH COLLEGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the institutions listed in the toss up, which one contains a subjective genitive in its motto?",
    "answer": "HUNTER COLLEGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle of the 2nd Punic War proved decisive, for it prevented Hasdrubal from joining forces with Hannibal and it buoyed Roman hopes three years after the winning commander Publius Cornelius Scipio the Elder lost to Hannibal at Ticinus River and just one year after the disaster at Cannae?",
    "answer": "DERTOSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Both Roman commanders at Dertosa were killed in battle against Hannibal in 211 BC?",
    "answer": "UPPER BAETIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Two years later, Publius Cornelius Scipio the Younger would avenge his father’s death at Upper Baetis by winning what battle?",
    "answer": "CARTHAGO NOVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was driven from his homeland of Elis because he sided with a stranger against his father in a dispute concerning payment for cleaning some incredibly filthy stables?",
    "answer": "PHYLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To where did Phyleus go and later become king?",
    "answer": "DULICHIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because the Spartan king Tyndareus forgot to sacrifice to her once, Aphrodite made three of his daughters be unfaithful to their husbands. Which of these daughters abandoned her husband Echemus and shacked up with Phyleus?",
    "answer": "TIMANDRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, part of an avant-garde literary circle that developed in the Late Republic, hailed from Bresica in Cisalpine Gaul, accompanied Catullus on an expedition to Bithynia in 57 BC, and wrote of the incestuous love between Myrrha and Cinryas in Zmyrna?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS HELVIUS) CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Catullus, how many years did it take Cinna to compose Zmyrna?",
    "answer": "NINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom, a literary critic and later consul of 40 BC, did Cinna address a Propempticon?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) ASINIUS POLLIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Spectātum veniunt et veniunt ut spectentur.",
    "answer": "THEY COME TO SEE AND TO BE SEEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What part of speech is the first word of that quote, and from what author is that quote taken?",
    "answer": "SUPINE; OVID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Cum Perseus Medūsam vicisset, monstrum ipsum vīsū horribilem vultum vīdit.",
    "answer": "THE VERY MONSTER SAW A FACE HORRIBLE TO SEE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Pliny the Younger, what woman had a double canine in her right jaw, symbolizing good luck, though it may not have seemed so the moment she told her assassin Anicetus to smite the womb, with which she gave birth to her vile son?",
    "answer": "AGRIPPINA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name two ways her son Nero related to his predecessor Claudius.",
    "answer": "GRANDNEPHEW / STEPSON / SON-IN-LAW (OF CLAUDIUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What freedwoman from Asia Minor did Nero take as his mistress, to his mother’s disapproval?",
    "answer": "(CLAUDIA) ACTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 5, line 451 of the Aeneid, what case and use besides the nominative subject are exemplified by the phrase it clamor caelō?",
    "answer": "DATIVE OF DIRECTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Staying with datives, use a double dative to say in Latin: This bridge will especially be of use to Caesar.",
    "answer": "HĪC PONS ŪSUĪ CAESARĪ MAXIMĒ ERIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate and identify the use of the dative in this sentence: Hostis mīlitī scūtum arripuit.",
    "answer": "THE ENEMY SNATCHED THE SHIELD FROM THE SOLDIER; SEPARATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What son of Zeus and Aex recommended to the gods that they take the forms of animal to escape Typhon, but is more famous for teaming up with Hermes to steal back the sinews of Zeus from Typhon?",
    "answer": "(AEGI)PAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a somewhat random turn of events, the form Aegipan took to escape Typhon was half-goat and half what animal?",
    "answer": "FISH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To retrieve the sinews of Zeus, Hermes and Aegipan went to the Corycian Cave in Cilicia, where the sinews were being guarded by what dragon-woman?",
    "answer": "DELPHYNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who was prosecuted by Sejanus, gave a voice to the subservient social classes of Rome in stories such as the tale of the Flautist named Princeps and famously established the promythion and epimythion as regular structural elements of the fable?",
    "answer": "PHAEDRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what meter did Phaedrus write his fables?",
    "answer": "IAMBIC SENARII"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Phaedrus is indebted to what Greek author for much of the material of his fables?",
    "answer": "AESOP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: tent, contemplation, tentacle, discontent, ostensible, and contemporary?",
    "answer": "TENT & OSTENSIBLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The noun “tense” and the adjective “tense” are derived from two different Latin words, from which two of the words in the tossup are derived. Identify these two English words, respectively.",
    "answer": "CONTEMPORARY; DISCONTENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The words “temper” and “tempter” are derived from two different Latin words, one of which is the derivation of a word in the tossup. Of these two options, give the Latin word from which no words in the tossup are derived.",
    "answer": "18"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two irregular verbs, say in Latin: I do not doubt that Caesar wants to go to Rome.",
    "answer": "NŌN DUBITŌ QUĪN CAESAR RŌMAM ĪRE VĒLIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: I did not doubt that Caesar had wanted to go to Rome.",
    "answer": "NŌN DUBITĀVĪ (-BAM) QUĪN CAESAR RŌMAM ĪRE VOLUISSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: Thetis wept when she had discovered that her son, who had killed many Trojans, would not live much longer.",
    "answer": "MULTŌ DIŪTIUS NŌN VICTŪRUM, THETIS LĀCRIMĀVIT (-BAT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Eos and Astraeus, who was sometimes represented in art with snake tails in place of feet, saved the inhabitants of Megalopolis from a Spartan attack and destroyed the Persians at Salamis?",
    "answer": "BOREAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name all four children of Boreas and Oreithyia.",
    "answer": "ZETES, CALAÏS, CLEOPATRA, CHIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Athenian king was the father of Oreithyia?",
    "answer": "ERECHTHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What future participant in the Ides of March, in a similar fashion to Duilius at Mylae, defeated the seafaring Veneti in 56 B.C. by fashioning hooks to long poles during Caesar’s Gallic campaigns?",
    "answer": "DECIMUS BRUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what town was Decimus Brutus almost besieged and defeated by Marc Antony in 43 B.C.?",
    "answer": "MUTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At what village in northern Italy had Marc Antony’s army been attacked by the armies of Hirtius and Pansa, precipitating his failure to capture Mutina?",
    "answer": "FORUM GALLORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Virgil, which I will twice as prose, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: “īte,” ait “ēgregiās animās, quae sanguine nōbīs hanc patriam pepererē suō, decorāte suprēmīs mūneribus, maestamque Evandrī prīmus ad urbem mittātur Pallas, quem nōn virtūtis egentem abstulit atra dies et fūnere mersit acerbō.” The question: Ubī vir nōn virtūtis egens accipiētur?",
    "answer": "IN (MAESTĀ) URBE EVANDRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quibus eundum est?",
    "answer": "ĒGREGIĪS ANIMĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ā quā Pallas ablātus est?",
    "answer": "ATRĀ DIĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which later Roman author, born around 480 A.D and consul in 510 A.D., became magister officiorum in 522 A.D. under Theodoric, but having been charged with treason and imprisoned, wrote De Consolatione Philosophiae?",
    "answer": "(ANICIUS MANLIUS SEVERINUS) BOETHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The dialogues in the De Consolatione Philosophiae are written in what form, which was inspired by a 3rd century B.C. Cynic writer from Gadara?",
    "answer": "19"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The position of magister officiorum was later filled by Boethius’ kinsman, who was born at Squillace around 490 A.D., and wrote a Chronica from Adam to 519 A.D., a history on the Goths as well as established a monastery at Vivarium. Name this relative.",
    "answer": "(FLAVIUS MAGNUS AURELIUS) CASSIODORUS (SENATOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two synonyms of the Latin deponent verb veneror.",
    "answer": "(AD)ŌRŌ / COLŌ / ADOLEO / VEREOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two synonyms of the Latin verb exspectō.",
    "answer": "SPĒRŌ / OPPERIOR / PRAESTŌLOR / MANEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two synonyms of the Latin verb crīmen.",
    "answer": "FACINUS / SCELUS / DĒDECUS / CULPA / VITIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Hermes and native of Opus was left by Heracles to guard the man-eating mares of Diomedes and was himself eaten?",
    "answer": "ABDERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Iberian was beloved by Heracles and was said to have been the first to devise a helmet?",
    "answer": "CORYTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the Greek chieftains, described in the Iliad as the second most handsome after Achilles, is also considered to have been a lover of Heracles?",
    "answer": "NIREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: polliceor : pollicēmini :: _______ : ēste. (N.B. to moderator: pronounce the long mark on ēste!)",
    "answer": "EDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two distinct forms of sum that can be its 1 st person singular imperfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "ESSEM & FOREM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The sentence “I hope that we are the winners” can be translated into Latin using a subjunctive rather than an indirect statement. When doing so, what two forms of sum would be present?",
    "answer": "FORE & SIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman consul, in one of the first battles of the Third Macedonian War, was defeated by Perseus near Larissa in 171 BC?",
    "answer": "(P. LICINIUS) CRASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What consular successor of Crassus, who shares the name of an ill-fated commander at Numantia 33 years later, similarly failed on the Macedonian front against Perseus?",
    "answer": "(HOSTILIUS) MANCINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What consul, after marching around Mt. Olympus for 11 days, scare Perseus into abandoning his entire frontier line in 169 BC?",
    "answer": "(Q. MARCIUS) PHILIPPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What which Roman author discusses the analgesic effects of willow bark, the cardinal signs of inflammation, and the surgical removal of cataracts in his eight-book encyclopecia De Medicina?",
    "answer": "(AULUS CORNELIUS) CELSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Celsus’ work originally contained six artes, but only the portion on medicine is extant. Name three of the five other artes Celsus is said to have treated in his encyclopedia.",
    "answer": "AGRICULTURE, MILITARY (ART), PHILOSOPHY, ORATORY, JURISPRUDENCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Celsus’ encyclopedic approach of the artes takes after the Disciplinarum Libri IX of what earlier Roman author? (Prompt on “Varro”) Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "VARRO OF REATE / (MARCUS TERENTIUS) VARRO REATINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: harundō?",
    "answer": "REED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: hirundō?",
    "answer": "SWALLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: hirūdō?",
    "answer": "LEECH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin word meaning “mutilated” means “to reduce in extent or quantity or impose a restriction on”?",
    "answer": "CURTAIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of the same word is “a woman's gown or outer petticoat”?",
    "answer": "KIRTLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning do we derive “curb”? Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "CURVUS – CURVED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 5 of Vergil’s Aeneid, what old Sicilian mandefeats Dares to win the boxing match at the funeral games of Anchises?",
    "answer": "ENTELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before the fight, Entellus forgoes using the gloves of what man?",
    "answer": "ERYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the archery contest, what brother of Pandarus successfully shot the dove, only to be shown-up by Acestes, whose arrow burst into flames? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "EURYTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Cassius Longinus, Asinius Pollio, Valens, Stilicho, and Aetius all had what in common?",
    "answer": "THEY SHARED THE TITLE “LAST OF THE ROMANS”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name all three “Founders of Rome.”",
    "answer": "ROMULUS, CAMILLUS, MARIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Name all three winners of the spolia opima, and the man whom Augustus refused to award it to. Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "ROMULUS, COSSUS, MARCELLUS; CRASSUS THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What epic poem, the most successful of Prudentius’s works, describes duels between Faith and Idolatry, Chastity and Lust, and Patience and Anger?",
    "answer": "PSYCHOMACHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Prudentius is a series of hymns that honor Christian martyrs?",
    "answer": "PERISTEPHANON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In his Contra Symmachum, Prudentius takes the side of what man in the dispute over the Altar of Victory?",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Possibly exclaimed during a consular election, translate into Latin: I’m sick and tired of hearing about your wretched letters!",
    "answer": "MĒ AUDIENDĪ DĒ TUĪS MISERĪS EPISTULĪS PIGET TAEDETQUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a genitive, translate into Latin: Though he was a merciful god, nevertheless he condemned the treacherous nymph to death.",
    "answer": "TAMEN INFIDĒLEM NYMPHĒN CAPITIS DAMNĀVIT (DAMNĀBAT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a genitive, translate into Latin: The ants marched eight by eight into the river of honey to more easily find food.",
    "answer": "QUŌ FACILIUS CIBUM INVENĪRENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claiming to be the son of Caligula, which Praetorian Prefect convinced the Praetorian Guard to betray Nero and later attempted to usurp the throne from Galba?",
    "answer": "NYMPHIDIUS SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom did Nymphidius Sabinus succeed as Praetorian Prefect in 65 AD as a result of his implication in the Pisonian Conspiracy?",
    "answer": "FAENIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Nero’s death, Sabinus forced the resignation of Tigellinus. Whom did Galba appoint to replace Tigellinus, causing Sabinus unease?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS LACO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though the words “illicit,” “solicit,” and “complicit” seem similar, they are derived from three different Latin words. Give the Latin words and their meanings from which each is derived, respectively.",
    "answer": "COMPLICIT, FROM PLECTŌ – TO PLAIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "A word often confused with “illicit” is “elicit,” which is derived from yet another Latin word. Give that Latin noun and its meaning.",
    "answer": "DĒLICIAE – SWEETHEART"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What derivative of dēliciae, would not describe Certamen players, since it means “a person having a superficial interest in an art or a branch of knowledge”?",
    "answer": "DILETTANTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What son of Minos and Pasiphae was warned by an oracle that one of his children would kill him so he sold two of his children to Nauplius?",
    "answer": "CATREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which daughter of Catreus was impregnated by Hermes after she slipped and fell on fresh hides while running away from him?",
    "answer": "APEMOSYNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which brother of Apemosyne, not believing that she had been raped by Hermes, kicked her to death?",
    "answer": "22"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author studied under the rhetorician Papirius Fabianus, went to Egypt in 26 A.D. in the entourage of his uncle, and discusses the detachment of the sage from worldly concerns in the essays of the Dialogi?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE YOUNGER / LUCIUS ANNAEUS SENECA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom, a prefect in charge of the distribution of the food supply and possibly a relative of Seneca’s wife, does Seneca dedicate De Brevitate Vitae?",
    "answer": "PAULINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which seven-book work of Seneca, addressed to Aebutius Liberalis, discusses philanthropy and its maintenance of social harmony?",
    "answer": "DE BENIFICIIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an antonym of prīdem.",
    "answer": "NŪPER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an antonym of diū.",
    "answer": "PAULISPER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an antonym of repentē.",
    "answer": "PAULĀTIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claudius Gothicus, Aurelian, Probus, and Valens are just a few of the many emperors born in what Roman province, heavily populated by troops defending the Danube?",
    "answer": "PANNONIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "From what neighboring region divided into two provinces did the likes of Constantine, Licinius, and Jovian hail?",
    "answer": "MOESIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Until the reign of Trajan, only one emperor was born outside of Italy. Name this emperor.",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which Greek chieftain at Troy, a son of Peteüs, was second only to Nestor in marshalling chariots and foot soldiers and led 50 ships from Athens?",
    "answer": "MENESTHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two sons of Ares and Astyoche led 30 ships from Orchomenus to Troy?",
    "answer": "ASCALAPHUS AND IALMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Heracles and Astyoche led 9 ships from Rhodes to Troy?",
    "answer": "TLEPOLEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In Latin, an object eliciting emotion is normally the object of propter or ob, while the motive influencing the mind of the person acting is found in what case with what use?",
    "answer": "ABLATIVE OF CAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate and identify the uses of the ablative found in this sentence: Aliīs āmissīs, spē nītī malumus.",
    "answer": "ABSOLUTE & WITH SPECIAL VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate and identify the uses of the accusative found in this sentence: Laesus crūra et honōre, gladiātor spem sōlam habuit.",
    "answer": "23"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A native of Gaza in Palestine, what author was considered the first significant Christian poet and wrote a history of the Old Testament and Rome coming down to the destruction of the Roman Empire, the Apocalypse, and the Last Judgment entitled Carmen Apologeticum?",
    "answer": "COMMODIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What lawyer was born at Cirta and wrote a work entitled Octavius, which refuted the attacks on Christianity by Fronto?",
    "answer": "MINUCIUS FELIX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What teacher of rhetoric, born in Sicca Veneria in Africa, was the teacher of Lactantius and wrote a work in 7 books entitled Adversus Nationes whose chief mission was the show the error of Neoplatonism?",
    "answer": "ARNOBIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What aedile published a legal manual of phrases and forms of procedure and posted a calendar in the forum of dies fasti and nefasti in 304 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) FLAVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to two contradicting tradition, Flavius either stole the manuscript from or worked together to compose it with what nobleman and ex-censor?",
    "answer": "APPIUS CLAUDIUS CAECUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In another plebeian victory, what law, passed after 293 B.C., extended the legislation of the Lex Publilia of 339 B.C. to elections, requiring the auctoritas partum to precede electoral operations?",
    "answer": "LEX MAENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Propertius, which I will read twice as prose, and answer the questions that follow in English: ō ūtīnam hībernae dūplicentur tempōra brūmae, et sit iners tardīs nāvita Vergiliīs, nec tibi Tyrrhēna solvātur fūnis harēna, nēve inimīca meās ēlevet aura precēs et mē dēfixum vacuā patiātur in orā crūdēlem infestā saepe vōcāre manū! The question: With what does the author supposedly threaten his lover?",
    "answer": "WITH HIS DANGEROUS HANDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What time of the year does the poet wish were longer?",
    "answer": "WINTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What does the poet hope will not happen to his prayers?",
    "answer": "THAT THEY BE BLOWN AWAY BY HOSTILE BREEZES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, whom Aelius Verus calls his Vergil, wrote a moving poem about the death of the 6-year old slave girl Erotion and numerous short, witty poems expressing adulation for patrons and the emperor Domitian?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS VALERIUS) MARTIAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name an author whom Martial calls one of his auctores.",
    "answer": "LENTULUS GAETULICUS / DOMITIUS MARSUS / ALBINOVANUS PEDO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name another.",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Lycurgus wore only a bearskin and brought only an axe on the voyage of the Argonauts when his grandfather hid his armor, but was still chosen to row beside Heracles due to his youthful strength?",
    "answer": "ANCAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this doting grandfather of Ancaeus?",
    "answer": "ALEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By what animal was this Ancaeus killed?",
    "answer": "BOAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 2 of Virgil’s Aeneid, Creusa speaks the following lines: quid tantum insanō iuvat indulgēre dolorī, o dulcis coniunx? non haec sine numine divum ēveniunt; nec te comitem hinc portāre Creusam fas, aut ille sinit superī regnator Olympi. This is the source of the phrase “nil sine numine” found on the seal of what state?",
    "answer": "COLORADO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Oklahoma also draws inspiration from Virgil for its motto, which is found in lines 145-146 of what work and book number of another of Virgil’s works?",
    "answer": "GEORGICS, BOOK 1"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Many other states draw inspiration from Cicero. Which state’s motto is based on a quote by Caecilius Statius in Cicero’s De Senectute?",
    "answer": "NORTH DAKOTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In retaliation for attacks on Cornelius Gallus around the First Cataract of the Nile, what prefect of Egypt led a punitive expedition as far as Nabata against the Queen of Ethiopia circa 25 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) PETRONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By what title was the Queen of Ethiopia known to the Romans?",
    "answer": "CANDACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 22 B.C., where did Ethiopian envoys meet Augustus to negotiate Rome’s border along the Nile?",
    "answer": "SAMOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "When Ovid wrote the Fasti, he referred to the Fasti Praenestini of what author, who was the tutor of Lucius and Gaius Caesar and the greatest grammarian of the Augustan Age?",
    "answer": "VERRIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the title of Verrius Flaccus’ work about difficult or obsolete terms?",
    "answer": "DE VERBORUM SIGNIFICATU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Although the original text of the De Verborum Significatu has been lost, we possess an abridgement produced by what grammarian of the second and third Centuries?",
    "answer": "(SEXTUS POMPEIUS) FESTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the person, number, tense, voice, and mood for the verb form commorās. nd PERSON SG. PLUP. ACT. INDICATIVE",
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood where applicable, what forms of the same verb could monēre be?",
    "answer": "PRES. ACT. INFINITIVE & PRES. PASS. IMPERATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the 2nd person plural future active imperative of that verb.",
    "answer": "MONĒTŌTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Euaemon led forty ships to Troy, where he cast his lot to duel Hector but was not chosen, and later received a chest abandoned by Aeneas, which drove him to madness?",
    "answer": "EURYPYLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To cure his madness, the Delphic Oracle directed him to Patrae, then being forced to atone for the actions of what couple, who slept together in a shrine?",
    "answer": "MELANNIPUS & COMAETHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eurypylus cured his madness and became king by propitiating the Patraeans with an image of what god, which he had found within his chest?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Dīcitur comitia trēs hōrās dīlāta esse dum lex ferrī posset.",
    "answer": "UNTIL THE LAW SHOULD BE ABLE TO BE PASSED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Rōmae fuērunt quoad Metellus in prōvinciam prōfectus est.",
    "answer": "THEY WERE AT ROME UNTIL METELLUS SET OUT FOR THE PROVINCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Haec non rectē identitem fēcī dōnec mē ēmendāvistī. Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "UNTIL YOU CORRECTED ME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb takes the accusative when it means to “foresee” and takes the dative when it means “to make provisions for”?",
    "answer": "PRŌVIDEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb takes the accusative when it means to “ask advice of” and takes the dative when it means “to pay attention to”?",
    "answer": "CONSULŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin compound of faciō has two objects, one in the dative and the other in the accusative?",
    "answer": "PRAEFICIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For a second conjugation verb meaning “to betroth,” give the 3rd person singular pluperfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "SPOPONDISSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For a second conjugation verb meaning “to bite,” give the same form.",
    "answer": "MOMORDISSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Keeping all else the same, provide turn both spopondisset and momordisset to the passive. Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "SPONSUS ESSET; MORSUS ESSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Also called Dictynna, what Cretan goddess, a daughter of Zeus and Carme, was pursued by Minos and attempted to leap into the sea, but was caught in the net of a fisherman?",
    "answer": "BRITOMARTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does the name “Dictynna” mean?",
    "answer": "LADY OF THE NETS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Britomartis was worshipped on the island of Aegina under what name? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "APHAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What barracks emperor was recognized by the senate but defeated in battle by Aemilianus in 253 A.D.?",
    "answer": "TREBONIANUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where had Aemilianus defeated Trebonianus Gallus to gain the throne?",
    "answer": "INTERAMNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Gallus officially ruled with him as co-Augustus? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "26"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, chosen bishop in 248 A.D., survived one persecution, but not the other leading to his eventual death September 14th 258 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(THASCIUS CAECILIUS) CYPRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Cyprian's works details his own conversion and the corruption of the Roman government?",
    "answer": "AD DONATUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which of his works does Cyprian speak of unifying the Catholic Church?",
    "answer": "DE ECCLESIASTE UNITATE CATHOLICA / DE ECCLESIAE CATHOLICAE UNITATE"
  },
   {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Pȳthia dīxit sē fāta nēscīre sed orācūlis crēdere?",
    "answer": "FATE/DESTINY BUT BELIEVED THE ORACLES."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Puella vult scīre num heroa ventūrum esset.",
    "answer": "THE GIRL WANTS TO KNOW WHETHER THE HERO WILL RETURN."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Spēramus nōs victurōs esse, sed sōla Pȳthia scit.",
    "answer": "I HOPE THAT WE WILL WIN, BUT ONLY THE PYTHIA/ORACLE KNOWS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sisters had many defining features, such as huge boar-like tusks, hands of bronze, gold wings, and heads entwined with snakes?",
    "answer": "THE GORGONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was given two vials of Gorgon blood by Athena for use in healing?",
    "answer": "ASCLEPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Athena also gave two drops of Gorgon blood to what Athenian king?",
    "answer": "ERICHTHONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What novus homo, born in Tusculum in 234 BC, distinguished his political life with his distaste for everything Greek, solidified his literary reputation with historical and agricultural prowess, and immortalized his name with the phrase Ceterum, censeo Carthaginem esse delendam, which is popularly abridged to Carthago delenda est!",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Cato’s full name?",
    "answer": "MARCUS PORCIUS CATO MAIOR/CENSOR(IUS)/SAPIENS/PRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cato’s De Agri Cultura prominently features what vegetable, which is the modern genus of cabbage, broccoli, cauliflower, choy sum, rutabaga, turnips, mustard, and wild mustard?",
    "answer": "BRASSICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive “jaunty,” “genie,” and, “genteel”?",
    "answer": "GENUS—KIND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive “frond”?",
    "answer": "FRONS—LEAF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive “lettuce”?",
    "answer": "LAC—MILK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What kind of conditional is found in the following sentence: Sī nōn tam temerē ēgisset, vicissēmus.",
    "answer": "PAST CONTRARY TO FACT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate that sentence.",
    "answer": "IF HE HAD NOT ACTED SO RASHLY, WE WOULD HAVE WON."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now, translate this one: Cum improbus puer adsit, talia fiunt.",
    "answer": "SUCH THINGS HAPPEN WHEN A WICKED BOY IS PRESENT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What province, first invaded by Caesar, was Agricola the governor of from 77 to 85 CE?",
    "answer": "BRITTANIA/BRITAIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Agricola's first act as governor was to defeat the Ordovices and thereby complete the conquest of Wales. What predecessor of Agricola began the conquest of Wales?",
    "answer": "FRONTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor recalled Agricola in 85 allegedly because he was jealous of Agricola's successes?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "We all know our chickpea-faced pal, Cicero. We all know that Cicero’s full 3-word name is Marcus Tullius Cicero. The cognomen, Cicero, is derived from cicer, referring to what type vegetable? CHICKPEA (or GARBANZO BEAN)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Plutarch informs us that he was called this because one of his ancestors had a cleft lip and/or grew chickpeas as a profession. Sadly Cicero, Illinois does not grow chickpeas. However, the town of Cicero does encompass the Corey Steel Company in its jurisdiction. With that in mind, in which specific speech of Cicero, does Cicero ask his opponent Catiline if there was not one Roman youth to whom he “has not handed out steel for audacious crime?”",
    "answer": "IN CATILINAM I"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what day was this speech given?",
    "answer": "NOVEMBER 8"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, according to early Roman accounts, consented to marry the Libyan king Iarbas but secretly ordered a funeral pyre to be built and killed herself upon it?",
    "answer": "DIDO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dido’s first husband was Sychaeus, who was also related to her in what way?",
    "answer": "HE WAS HER UNCLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Vergil’s Aeneid, what action of Iarbas causes Jupiter to have Mercury urge Aeneas to leave Dido?",
    "answer": "HE PRAYS TO (HIS FATHER) JUPITER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In boarding schools, students are often provided for by the school staff due to the students’ distance from home. What Latin phrase describes the legal responsibility bestowed upon these schools to act on behalf of parents?",
    "answer": "IN LOCO PARENTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What similar Latin phrase meaning “parent of the country” describes the power of the state to intervene to protect children, under circumstances of abuse or negligence of the child?",
    "answer": "PARENS PATRIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase, literally meaning “holding the place” describes one temporarily fulfilling the duties of another, such as a substitute teacher?",
    "answer": "LOCUM TENENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor was appointed by the Senate in 96 CE, promised to never execute a Senator without a trial, but nevertheless failed to control the army?",
    "answer": "NERVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom did Nerva indifferently exile early in his reign for conspiring for the throne?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) CALPURNIUS CRASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Praetorian Prefect induced the guards to lay siege to Nerva’s palace to execute Petronius Secundus, the lead conspirator against Domitian?",
    "answer": "CASPERIUS AELIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: facerēs is to facis as ______ is to vīs.",
    "answer": "VELLĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: volō is to velle as patior is to ______.",
    "answer": "PATĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: tollō is to sustulī as afferō is to ______.",
    "answer": "ATTULĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What young relative of Odysseus pretended to have earned the enmity of Odysseus by speaking out against his treacherous murder of Palamedes, and thus won the Trojans’ trust?",
    "answer": "SINON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas remarks that Sinon’s cunning and false tears had overcome the men who had not been subdued what two much stronger Greek warriors? ACHILLES and DIOMEDES",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas’ recounts later in his story that whose mighty trunk lay on the shores of Pergamum, a headless corpse without a name?",
    "answer": "PRIAM’S"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle of the early Roman Republic was commemorated by a parade of horses and a temple to Castor and Pollux, despite the fact that it was a draw between Rome and the Latin League in 496 BC?",
    "answer": "BATTLE OF LAKE REGILLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "This battle was sparked because Rome signed a treaty with what city in 509 BCE that indicated Rome controlled Latium?",
    "answer": "CARTHAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What early Plebeian leader negotiated the treaty that followed this battle so skillfully that Rome gained equal status to the Latin League?",
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word can mean “hero,” “husband,” or “man”?",
    "answer": "VIR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What less common definition of the Latin word amīcus is a derivative of the Latin verb discō?",
    "answer": "DISCIPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What less common definition of the Latin word exuviae is a future active imperative?",
    "answer": "MEMENTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the correct form of the word “ribbon” if the following English sentence were to be translated into Latin: The girls understood that on Saturnalia, their hair should be fastened with ribbons.",
    "answer": "VITTĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Vittae, since they relate to the human body, can often also be found with a passive verb and what type of accusative?",
    "answer": "SYNECHDOCHICAL/RESPECT/SPECIFICATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word meaning “thigh” notably takes this accusative in a dramatic scene in Book V of Caesar’s De Bello Gallico?",
    "answer": "FĒMUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What office was made sacrosanct after the second secession of the Plebeians in 449 BCE?",
    "answer": "TRIBUNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did it mean in ancient Roman for a group of people to be sacrosanct?",
    "answer": "ARMS COULD NOT BE USED AGAINST THEM WITHIN THE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Plebeian-favoring consuls of 449 BCE passed the legislation that enacted this?",
    "answer": "VALERIUS POTITUS AND HORATIUS BARBATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose physical features—that is, his uncut hairs, fiery eyes, and dirty mantle—complement the ferruginea cumba by which he would convey passengers to the Underworld?",
    "answer": "CHARON’S"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two primordial deities were the parents of Charon?",
    "answer": "EREBUS AND NYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Across what two rivers did Charon bring his passengers?",
    "answer": "ACHERON AND STYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Achilles, Aegisthus, Ajax Mastigophorus, Andromeda, Danae, Equus Troianus, Hermiona, and Tereus are all plays written by what author, the father of Latin literature?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS ANDRONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What two plays from those listed in the toss up share their name with plays written by Gnaeus Naevius?",
    "answer": "DANAE, EQUUS TROIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work in Saturnian Meter is Andronicus’s magnum opus?",
    "answer": "5"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, and answer in Latin the questions that follow: Eheu, amice! Hesterna gaudia brevī tempōre mē ē negotiō rapuerunt. Hesterna gaudia meam errābundam mentem quae dē morte uxoris Quintiliae lacrimat edūxērunt. Hesterna gaudia meum calamum, perfixum in meīs carminibus, in mensam depulerunt, dum levitāte cerae cum tē ludēbam. The question: Quis in mensam dēpulsus est?",
    "answer": "(MEUS) CALAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quam diū hesterna gaudia narratorem rapuerunt?",
    "answer": "BREVĪ TEMPŌRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Qualem mentem hesterna gaudia edūxērunt?",
    "answer": "ERRĀBUNDAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who am I? I’m popularly considered the father of Church song, I was elected to be bishop of Milan without having been baptized, and I wrote a lot of treatises on virgins, widows, and Christian faith?",
    "answer": "SAINT AMBROSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "My De Officiis Ministrorum draws heavily in style and purpose from the De Officiis of what earlier author?",
    "answer": "CICERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "While I was the father of Church song, what other author invented the Latin hymn?",
    "answer": "ROUND II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pothinus and Achillas were ordered by Ptolemy to kill what man that stumbled on to the shores of Egypt after losing the battle of Pharsalus?",
    "answer": "POMPEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general’s second and third lines of defense armed with stabbing spears won the day against Pompey’s larger army at Pharsalus?",
    "answer": "CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What famous two-word Latin phrase did Caesar utter after this battle?",
    "answer": "HOC VOLUERUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the six English words are derived from the same Latin root: apprehension, adhesion, malady, movable, ditty?",
    "answer": "MALADY & MOVABLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the six English words are derived from the same Latin root: donate, decision, season, traitor, silhouette, series?",
    "answer": "DONATE & TRAITOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the six English words are derived from the same Latin root: innocent, ennui, otiose, malice, odoriferous, odious?",
    "answer": "ENNUI & ODIOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was killed either because he was married when he should have been celibate, because he made love before a sanctuary of Apollo, or because he struck a wooden object that was sacred to Neptune?",
    "answer": "LAOCOÖN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some accounts, like the one by Quintus Smyrnaeus, state that Laocoön met his downfall not because he struck the Trojan Horse, but because he wanted the Trojans to do what with it?",
    "answer": "BURN IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas is told by his mother that which deity sent the serpents to kill Laocoön?",
    "answer": "MINERVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though originally used for the dative of purpose, the ending -ū became the ablative ending of what verbal abstract of the fourth declension that is commonly introduced by fās, nefās, and opus?",
    "answer": "SUPINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Opus est is an impersonal verb that introduces what type of subjunctive?",
    "answer": "RESULT CLAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Many impersonal verbs often introduce what type of infinitive, such as the one in the sentence “Licetne mihi ad latrīnam īre?”",
    "answer": "SUBJECTIVE INFINITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author neglected to mention his puella for the first 55 lines of his first poem, even mentioning his patron Messalla before his lover, Delia, in his elegiac tribute to rusticity?",
    "answer": "TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tibullus’s mistress was named Delia in his poems. According to Apuleius, what is Delia’s real name?",
    "answer": "PLANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In his elegies, Tibullus also mentions having relations with a puer delicatus – a term referring to a young boy bought for the sexual satisfaction of his master. The 12-year-old boy toy featured in Tibullus’s work is known by what name?",
    "answer": "MARATHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two Titans did not participate in the Titanomachy, and thus continued their original functions under the rule of Zeus? OCEANUS and HELIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Oceanus’ wife Tethys and what other Titaness were particularly revered by the Olympians?",
    "answer": "THEMIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Themis was an earth-goddess, as was what other Titaness?",
    "answer": "RHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that following in Latin: Nulla est enim natio, quam pertimescamus, nullus rex, qui bellum populo Romano facere possit. Omnia sunt externa unius virtute terra marique pacata; domesticum bellum manet, intus insidiae sunt, intus inclusum periculum est, intus est hostis. The question: Quis terram mareque domuit? VIRTUS UNIUS or UNUS (VIR)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quale est periculum?",
    "answer": "(INTUS) INCLUSUM (EST)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quis ab bellis regum nunc liberantur?",
    "answer": "ROMANUS (POPULUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was declared a usurper in 308 AD at the Conference of Carnuntum by Diocletian, Galerius, and his father Maximian?",
    "answer": "MAXENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, the Caesar of the West appointed by Diocletian just before his retirement, did Maxentius initially usurp?",
    "answer": "SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While Maxentius was trying to one-by-one defeat members of the tetrarchy, what future emperor was training the army of his father Constantius Chlorus in Britain for battle?",
    "answer": "8"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "According to the Lexicon Rēcentis Latinitātis what in modern times would be called an aleātorium?",
    "answer": "CASINO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What famous structure would be called Aedes Alba?",
    "answer": "WHITE HOUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What event in certain sports would be called retis violatio?",
    "answer": "A GOAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "SpongeBob is often punctuated by insipid, yet eloquent, comments. What author employed a similar style to his prodigious pile of papyrus scrolls, totaling some 12,200 lines of Latin that are deemed collectively as the worst poem of all Latin literature?",
    "answer": "SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Other authors are known for writing a lot of rubbish. One of these trash writers, Volusius, is viciously attacked by what eloquent author who deems Volusius’ works as cacata carta?",
    "answer": "CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Some writers wrote intentionally simplistic and trite books. What author was commissioned by the emperor Valens to compose one such simplistic work, the Breviarium Ab Urbe Condita, an abridgement of Livy’s history of Rome?",
    "answer": "EUTROPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What king of Pontus send his general Archelaus to Greece in 88 BCE to fight Sulla besieging Athens?",
    "answer": "MITHRIDATES VI (THE GREAT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle in 86 BCE did scythe chariots not help Archelaus in defeating Sulla?",
    "answer": "CHAERONEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle in 86 BCE did Sulla build trenches and drive Archelaus’s chariots back into his phalanx?",
    "answer": "ORCHOMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase, a precept that must be applied intelligently, advises us to generalize from one example?",
    "answer": "AB ŪNŌ DISCE OMNĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase cautions us that it is easy to fall, but once fallen, difficult to make one’s way back up?",
    "answer": "FACILE DĒSCENSUS AVERNŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase attributed to Suetonius describes the oxymoronic yet necessary balance between caution and action?",
    "answer": "FESTĪNĀ LENTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, perhaps in league with the demagogue Menestheus, because he privately feared that the famous king might induce the Scyrians to offer him their country, treacherously murdered Theseus by pushing him off a cliff?",
    "answer": "LYCOMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Theseus had gone to Scyrus because he inherited estates there from what grandfather of his?",
    "answer": "SCYRIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to other accounts, Theseus had been carried off by storms and forced to land at Scyrus while sailing to what island ruled by his brother-in-law Deucalion?",
    "answer": "CRETE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What two prominent authors, one a prominent 2nd century tragedian, the other an epic Roman poet, both died in a similar manner: on a voyage to Greece?",
    "answer": "TERENCE AND VERGIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under what man did Terence supposedly come as a slave to Rome?",
    "answer": "TERENTIUS LUCANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Terence and Vergil, along with Horace and Lucan, are all prominently featured in the De Poetis chapter of what major work by Suetonius?",
    "answer": "DE VIRIS ILLUSTRIBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify a declinable Latin word that has the same form in only the accusative and ablative cases.",
    "answer": "EGŌ/TŪ/SUI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify a declinable Latin word that has the same form in the nominative and ablative singular.",
    "answer": "GENŪ/GELŪ/CORNŪ/VERŪ/PECŪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify the Latin monoptote that describes a time of day.",
    "answer": "MANĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose younger brother Promachus and father would meet their deaths in a gruesome fashion, the first through plotted murder, and the second by drinking bull’s blood, all because of the enmity of Pelias?",
    "answer": "JASON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did Jason’s mother do upon hearing witnessing these injustices?",
    "answer": "SHE KILLED HERSELF WITH A SWORD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Upon hearing what rumor had Pelias dared to murder Jason’s father and younger brother?",
    "answer": "THE SHIP HAD GONE DOWN WITH ALL ITS CREW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman general, although more famous for his son Pompey Magnus, is credited with ending the Social War by taking the Italian strongholds at Corfinium and Asculum?",
    "answer": "POMPEIUS STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What two political enemies of 63 BCE served together under Strabo in the Social War?",
    "answer": "CICERO AND CATILINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what year immediately following the social war did Strabo serve as consul with Sulla?",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Quāre esse amīcī nēquimus?",
    "answer": "WHY CAN’T WE BE FRIENDS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Ūtīnam mea amīca esse vēlit!",
    "answer": "IF ONLY SHE WOULD WISH TO BE MY FRIEND!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Eheu! Sunt quī esse me bonī amicī non cupiant.",
    "answer": "ALAS, THERE ARE THOSE WHO DO NOT WISH TO BE MY GOOD FRIENDS!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek writer serves as the obvious influence for Vergil when he was writing the Aeneid?",
    "answer": "HOMER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek writer serves as the obvious influence for Vergil when he was writing the Eclogues?",
    "answer": "THEOCRITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek writer serves as the obvious influence for Vergil when he was writing the Georgics?",
    "answer": "HESIOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The moderators did not know where they were going.",
    "answer": "MODERĀTŌRĒS NĒSCĪVĒRUNT QUŌ ĪRENT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The moderators whom we choose might also be teachers.",
    "answer": "MODERĀTORĒS, QUŌS LEGIMUS, MAGISTRĪ SINT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The moderators must be lauded by us for their efforts.",
    "answer": "ROUND III"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Hyginus, who was less faithful at her daughter’s death than anger at Oeax’s advance report that his daughter was bringing home Priam’s daughter Cassandra as a concubine?",
    "answer": "CLYTEMNESTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "It is for this reason that Hyginus remarks that Oeax thus avenged what unjust action of Agamemnon?",
    "answer": "AGAMEMNON’S CONDEMNATION OF (HIS BROTHER) PALAMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Though she bore such great resentment towards him for his role in their daughter’s death, Clytemnestra seemed to have had no such hatred for Agamemnon when he violently killed what man, her first husband?",
    "answer": "TANTALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Descendant of Messapus and self-proclaimed Homer of Latin, what author glorified lavish eating, introduced an early and rough version of hexameter to Latin literature, and was a follower of Euhemerus, according to Cicero?",
    "answer": "ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Fulvius Nobilior took Ennius with him on his military campaign to Ambracia, what former patron of Ennius was like “oh no you didn’t?”",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Ennius technically began the tradition of Roman satire, although official credit for beginning the genre is given to a later author? SOTA (or SATURAE)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin into English: Cornelius ab amplissimo senātōre portāre aquam usque ad flumen Tiberim iussus est.",
    "answer": "SENATOR TO CARRY WATER ALL THE WAY TO THE TIBER RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Latin into English: Non est dubium quin nemo sciat cūr Cornēlius tam pavidus sit.",
    "answer": "KNOWS WHY CORNELIUS IS SO AFRAID."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into Latin: Cornelius is afraid because he thinks that he will fall into the Tiber River.",
    "answer": "SĒ CASŪRUM ESSE IN FLŪMEN TIBERIM PUTAT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose apparent willingness to provide information to his captors may have been due in part to disgruntlement over the fact that his brother Deiphobus had won their quarrel over the right to marry Helen after Paris’ death?",
    "answer": "12"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the fall of Troy, Helenus traveled with Neoptolemus, and provided him with what useful piece of advice?",
    "answer": "TO RETURN HOME BY LAND (AND NOT SEA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where did Neoptolemus and Helenus settle upon leaving Troy?",
    "answer": "EPEIRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Used when describing Aeneas and Rumor in the Aeneid, what third conjugation Latin verb can mean “to hide” or to “sheath one’s sword” though it also has the more common meaning “to found”?",
    "answer": "CONDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Another such verb with a less common meaning is claudō. Beside “to close,” what else can claudō mean?",
    "answer": "TO LIMP, STUMBLE, FALTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The adverb multō means “by much” and is a common ablative of degree of difference. What, however, does the verb multō mean? TO PUNISH",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Fans of the HBO series, Game of Thrones, are curious to find out if Danaerys Targaryen and Jon Snow will finally cross paths in the upcoming season. While a potential relationship between the mother of dragons and her nephew should seem weird to most, Roman historians know to think otherwise. What Roman Emperor, imitating the way of the Pharaohs, pursued intimate relationships with his sisters, being especially fond of Drusilla?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS CORNELIUS) LENTULUS GAETULICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, “the great protégé of Aurunca” drove his steeds of satire to pen 30 poems of satire, thus establishing the genre with which Ennius had flirted?",
    "answer": "LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two contemporary tragedians were lumped in Lucilius’s laundry list of lampooneries? ACCIUS and PACUVIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was Lucilius’s mistress?",
    "answer": "COLLYRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in the following sentence: Timet nē mox mendax esse ducātur. FEARING",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in this sentence: Dīcō eī hominem quī semel mendax esset semper mendācem esse cogitum īrī.",
    "answer": "RELATIVE CLAUSE OF CHARACTERISTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in this sentence: Tam stultus est ut verō mea verba non crēdat. RESULT",
    "answer": "13"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Defeats near Cyzicus and Nicaea preceded what Emperor’s final defeat at Issus in 194 AD?",
    "answer": "HIS NECK (IT WAS BLACK)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author in his quotation “possunt quia posse videntur” tells that that the appearance of power bestows power itself?",
    "answer": "VIRGIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author ominously writes “post equitem sedet atra cūra,” telling us that nobody is free of anxiety?",
    "answer": "HORACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author calls to attention the irreversible results of time in his quotation “tempus, edax rērum”?",
    "answer": "OVID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "It was no doubt that the presence of what sexual force enabled Erebus and Nyx, fellow offspring of Chaos, to unite and bring forth the beings Aether and Hemera?",
    "answer": "EROS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Around this time, Ge also singlehandedly produced three offspring. Name them.",
    "answer": "URANUS, PONTUS, OUREA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Later Greek accounts denoted Eros not as an offspring of Chaos but rather as the youthful son of Aphrodite. The poet Olen, however, claimed that what deity was the mother of Eros?",
    "answer": "EILEITHYIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the dative is found in the following sentence: Quamquam non credendum est, gladatōri se grātificarī putant?",
    "answer": "SPECIAL VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What use of the accusative is often used loosely by authors as in this sentence from Horace: Huic errōri simile errōrem insanīre?",
    "answer": "COGNATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What use of the dative, used by poets, is found in the following sentence: Placitōne etiam pugnābis amōrī?",
    "answer": "WITH VERBS OF CONTENDING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What capable military commander was known as the, “the last of the Romans”, for his victory at the Catalaunian Plains?",
    "answer": "PETRONIUS MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "His ears beaten with texts of archaic Latin and body beaten by Orbilius, what author hopped onto the literary scene around 41 BC with the Epodes, where he declared that he possessed the spirit of Archilochus?",
    "answer": "HORACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hailing from the border between Apulia and Lucania, Horace was born in the same city as the famous 16th century, Italian botanist, Bartolomeo Maranta. What was the name of the Roman city?",
    "answer": "VENUSIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In what Latin work does Horace write est brevitate opus, ut currat sentential neu se inpediat verbis lassas onerantibus aures, et sermone opus est modo tristi, saepe iocoso, defendente vicem modo rhetoris atque poetae, interdum urbani, parcentis viribus atque extenuantis eas consulto?",
    "answer": "SERMONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to following passage, which I will read twice, and answer in English the question that follows: Sōllemne est mihi, dōmine, omnia dē quibus dubitō ad tē rēferre. Quis enim potest melius vel cunctātiōnem meam regere vel ignorantium instruere? Cognitiōnibus dē Christianīs interfuī numquam: ideō nesciō quid et quātenus aut punīrī soleat aut quaerī. The question: Why doesn’t the speaker know how to punish Christians?",
    "answer": "HE NEVER ATTENDED TRIALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom is it customary that all questions be addressed?",
    "answer": "THE MASTER/RULER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why does speaker write to the ruler?",
    "answer": "THE RULER IS MOST CAPABLE OF ADDRESSING ISSUES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before he saw Pallas’ belt vaunting from Turnus’ waist, Achilles would have granted Turnus’ request to die at the house of what man?",
    "answer": "DAUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What object, bestowed upon him by Vulcan, did Daunus pass on to Turnus?",
    "answer": "AN UNBREAKABLE SWORD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How were Daunus and Perseus related?",
    "answer": "THEY WERE HALF BROTHERS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word derived from the Latin word meaning “to bear” means “slow to act” or “tardy”?",
    "answer": "DILATORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word derived from the Latin word meaning “to measure” means “corresponding in size, extent, amount, or degree”?",
    "answer": "COMMENSURATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word derived from a Latin word for a type of vehicle means “exaggeration by means of often ludicrous distortion of parts or characteristics”?",
    "answer": "CARICATURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Satura Tota Nostra Est declares satire to be of wholly Roman origin – a bold, dubiously patriotic assertion for what author to make in Book 10 of his Institutio Oratoria?",
    "answer": "QUINTILIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quintilian served as what satirist’s tutor?",
    "answer": "PERSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Harvard Lampoon, founded in 1876, is Harvard’s principal satirical magazine. Their motto, Vanitas, both puns Harvard University’s motto, Veritas, and harkens back to the phrase vanitas vanitatum omnia vanitas found in what work by Jerome?",
    "answer": "VULGATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Triumviri Rei Publicae Constituendae Consulari Potestate were legally recognized by what law of 43 BC?",
    "answer": "CONFERENCE OF TARENTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the difference in meaning between the Latin correlatives vel…vel and aut…aut?",
    "answer": "AUT…AUT STRESSES ONE OR THE OTHER OF TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What does the Latin phrase ne…quidem mean?",
    "answer": "NOT EVEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What does the Latin phrase quin etiam mean?",
    "answer": "SEMIFINALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term, deemed a necessity to convict many criminal cases, denotes the knowledge and intent of wrongdoing by a guilty party, and literally means “a guilty mind”?",
    "answer": "MENS REA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin legal term denotes that ignorance of the law is not a viable plea of innocence?",
    "answer": "IGNORANTIA LEGIS NEMINEM EXCUSAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin legal term describes the subjective state of mind of the guilty party?",
    "answer": "ANIMUS NOCENDI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Books XI and XXIV of the Odyssey, what place is described respectively as the place which clean-heeled Achilles marched away from with great strides, and as “the abode of souls whose work is done”? THE FIELDS OF ASPHODEL (prompt on UNDERWORLD)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What semi-legendary place believed to be in the Atlantic was the residence of those who were reincarnated thrice, and judged to be pure enough to be in Elysium all three times?",
    "answer": "FORTUNATE ISLES / ISLES OF THE BLESSED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to accounts after Homer, Achilles did not stay in the Fields of Asphodel, but instead was sent to the Isles of the Blessed, where he married what woman?",
    "answer": "MEDEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author gives credence to the story that Nero started the fire at Rome and depicts Tiberius as harsh and repulsive in his old age as he covers the period from the death of Augustus?",
    "answer": "TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This work was, of course, Tacitus’ Annales, and was left unfinished due to his untimely death. Which fourth century AD pagan historian continued this work later on?",
    "answer": "AMMIANUS MARCELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Tacitus, which utilized an earlier work by Pliny the Elder, is a short geographic-ethnographic treatise with political roots and motives?",
    "answer": "GERMANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claudius described what figure of early Roman history to have been an Etruscan mercenary who worked for Caelius Vibenna?",
    "answer": "17"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun commonly used by Cicero as a pejorative prescribed to the Catilinarian Conspirators is also often used by philosophical authors when describing the state of humanity or when trying to denote the difference between men, animal, and deus, which are usages separate from the Latin word vir?",
    "answer": "HOMO/HOMINES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While homo is in contrast to animal and deus, what two words are vir in contrast to?",
    "answer": "MULIER/FEMINA & LIBERI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another common Ciceronian word is iste. Besides occasionally having a pejorative connotation, what else can iste denote about something that ille cannot?",
    "answer": "PHYSICAL PROXIMITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What culture hero from Arcadia brought the Greek pantheon to his new home and instituted the Lupercalia about sixty years before the start of the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "EVANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Besides introducing the Greek pantheon, Evander also introduced to the Italians what useful invention of Palamedes?",
    "answer": "GREEK ALPHABET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Evander was related to Aeneas through which Titan?",
    "answer": "ATLAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The screams of six thousand Samnite prisoners could be heard as who addressed the Senate at the Temple of Bellona in 82 BC?",
    "answer": "SULLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What law enabled Sulla to be dictator for life and gave him almost unlimited power?",
    "answer": "LEX VALERIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Sulla’s epitaph, “I have always rewarded my friends with good, my enemies with evil” well summarizes his reign after assuming the dictatorship of Rome. An example of this policy in full effect was when Sulla executed what legate of his for running for the consulship against his orders?",
    "answer": "QUINTUS LUCRETIUS OFELLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because of other accounts of the same period, most notably that written by Sallust, which portray the antagonist in a more sympathetic light, even going so far as to excuse him of any involvement at all, it is sometimes believed that what work of Latin Literature was political propaganda designed to solidify Cicero's position in the political sphere rather than a factual account of the events of 63 BC? IN CATILINAM",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where was the first speech delivered? TEMPLE OF JUPITER STATOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which oration did Cicero claim that the city should rejoice because it had been saved from a bloody rebellion and present evidence that all of Catiline's accomplices confessed to their crimes. THIRD",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two semi-deponent verbs, translate the following sentence into Latin: I was informed that the soldiers, who were accustomed to carry baggage, would arrive a little before dawn.",
    "answer": "SOLERENT, PAULO ANTE PRIMA LUCE PERVENTUROS ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin: Who was there that dared to stop them from crossing the narrow river?",
    "answer": "ANGUSTA FLUMEN AUDERET?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a deponent verb, translate this sentence into Latin: If the troops should not arrive in the evening, whom are we to trust?",
    "answer": "SI COPIAE VESPERI NON PERVENIANT, QUO/QUIBUS FIDAMUS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Seen most commonly with adjectives like magnus and summus and thus mostly confined to expressions of number, what rather infrequent use of the genitive is much less common than its counterpart in the ablative case?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE OF DESCRIPTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Why would the expression “a king of wit,” when translated into Latin not be considered a genitive of description?",
    "answer": "IT LACKS AN ADJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Unlike the genitive of description, the ablative of description does not necessarily need an adjective. An alternative would be a modifier in what case?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A poem on weather signs in the manner of Aratus, a historical poem on the 58 B.C. campaign against Ariovistus, and a translation of the Argonautica by Apollonius of Rhodes were all written by what author?",
    "answer": "VARRO ATACINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the title of the work on the campaign against Ariovistus in 58 B.C.?",
    "answer": "BELLUM SEQUANICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In addition to the works previously mentioned in the tossup. Varro of Atax also wrote erotic poetry to his beloved. What was her name?",
    "answer": "LEUCADIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "A siege by Sulla during the Social War, three battles during the Second Punic War, and the death of Augustus were all events in Roman history that occurred at what city in Campania?",
    "answer": "NOLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "As referenced earlier, Hannibal failed to take the city of Nola three times during the Second Punic War. What Roman commander repelled all three of these attacks?",
    "answer": "MARCUS CLAUDIUS MARCELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Around the same time that Marcellus defended the final siege of Nola, what Roman admiral landed at Apollonia with the intention of keeping Philip V in check?",
    "answer": "VALERIUS LAEVINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following poetic passage, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the questions that follow in English: Quae fueram magnis olim patefacta triumphis, ianua Patriciae vota Pudicitiae, cuius inaurati celebrarunt limina currus, captorum lacrimis umida supplicibus, nunc ego, nocturnis potorum saucia rixis, pulsata indignis saepe queror manibus, et mihi non desunt turpes pendere corollae semper et exclusi signa iacere faces. The question: Give two reasons why the door is now complaining. (accept two from list of four):",
    "answer": "HANDS//HAS UGLY GARLANDS ON ITSELF//HAS TORCHES ON ITSELF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the door once used for?",
    "answer": "TRIUMPHS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What opposing values has the door experience in its existence?",
    "answer": "CHASTITY AND LUST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: rosus eras is to rodes as _______ is to vesceris.",
    "answer": "NO FORM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: habēam is to habitī sint as liquem is to ________.",
    "answer": "LIQUATI SIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: queri is to questas essetis as quire is to _______.",
    "answer": "QUIVISSETIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who railed at Agamemnon for taking Briseis from Achilles, and advised the soldiery to go home instead of remaining at Troy to make Agamemnon rich?",
    "answer": "THERSITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who beat Thersites for his insolence?",
    "answer": "ODYSSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Thersites insulted Achilles for weeping over the Amazonian queen Penthesileia, Achilles killed him on the spot. This murder led to a dispute among the Greeks, and Achilles had to sacrifice to Apollo, Artemis, and Leto on what island before he could return to battle?",
    "answer": "LESBOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: reticeo?",
    "answer": "BE SILENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: vadimonia?",
    "answer": "BAIL/SECURITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: ganeo?",
    "answer": "GLUTTON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, during the persecutions of Diocletian, was forced to abandon his teaching post in Bithynia, but was later chosen by Constantine to tutor his son Crispus in Gaul?",
    "answer": "LACTANTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which 7 book work of Lactantius, dedicated to Constantine, does he discuss the Christian theology, the final judgement, as well as anti-paganism and philosophy?",
    "answer": "DIVINE INSTITUTIONS/DIVINAE INSTITUTIONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Lactantius was the pupil of what earlier Christian poet who sought to refuse claims of Christians bringing calamity onto the Roman Empire in his Adversus Nationes?",
    "answer": "ARNOBIUS (OF SICCA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Achilles was able to wound the Mysian king Telephus because what son of Iphiclus had snatched away Telephus’ shield?",
    "answer": "PROTESILAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Telephus later begged Achilles to heal him of his wound, which Achilles willingly did in exchange for Telephus’ aid in guiding the Greeks to Troy. Afterwards, the Greeks asked Telephus to join them in fighting against the Trojans, but he refused, citing what reason?",
    "answer": "HE WAS PRIAM’S SON-IN-LAW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Telephus would fight on the Trojan side?",
    "answer": "EURYPYLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: conserve, deserve, observe, preserve, reserve?",
    "answer": "DESERVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning is the English word “lawsuit” derived?",
    "answer": "SEQUOR-FOLLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning is the English word “surly” derived?",
    "answer": "SENEX-OLD MAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What scholar of the Late Republic, a praetor of 58 BC and friend of Cicero, was portrayed in medieval times as a magician, diviner, and occultist, perhaps because of Jerome’s comment that he was a “Pythagoricus et magus”? NIGIDIUS FIGULUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Even in Roman times, his skills as a diviner were well known. Figulus is said to have foretold the greatness of what emperor on the day of his birth? AUGUSTUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Silver Age author would include a portrayal of Figulus uttering dire prophecies, based in part on astrological readings? LUCAN",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The women certainly told you what they would have done.",
    "answer": "FEMINAE CERTE TIBI DIXERUNT QUID FACTURAE FUISSENT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: He said that he had asked the man who was present what had happened.",
    "answer": "DIXIT SE AB VIRO QUI ADESSET QUID ACCIDISSET ROGAVISSE."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a compound of eo, translate the following sentence into Latin: Had the Romans been defeated by the Gauls, we would have been unable to behold a triumph wonderful to see.",
    "answer": "MIRABILEM VISU ASPICERE NEQUIVISSEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During the Third Macedonian War, what Illyrian chieftain made the unwise decision to abandon the Roman side and ally himself with Perseus?",
    "answer": "GENTHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Genthius may have been persuaded to switch sides after what early victory of Perseus in B2. After he finally surrendered to the Romans in 168 BC, Perseus was forced to live out the rest of his life imprisoned in what small country town?",
    "answer": "ALBA FUCENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Under what circumstances do questions within indirect statements not have their verbs in the subjunctive?",
    "answer": "(WHEN THEY ARE) RHETORICAL QUESTIONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what case is the subject of the infinitive of a rhetorical question?",
    "answer": "ACCUSATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of infinitive has its subject in the nominative case?",
    "answer": "22"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between ferveo and foveo.",
    "answer": "TO GLOW & TO CHERISH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between premo and promo.",
    "answer": "TO PRESS & TO BRING OUT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between purgo and pergo.",
    "answer": "TO CLEANSE AND TO PROCEED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king and seer tried in vain to prevent his sons Adrastus and Amphius from going to the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "MEROPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other child of Merops also died young after committing suicide shortly after marriage?",
    "answer": "CLEITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though he had four children, Merops only had one grandchild. Who was this grandson, to whom he taught the art of prophecy?",
    "answer": "AESACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A right tentatively used by Claudius and then later more frequently by the Flavians, the ability to appoint any individual to the senate by decree was known as what?",
    "answer": "ADLECTIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the reign of Domitian, the process of using adlectio reemerged many times throughout the Empire. In order to prevent opposition against the Emperor, what Phrygian freedman used adlectio to pack the Senate with as many followers of Commodus as he could?",
    "answer": "CLEANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cleander became infamous for auctioning offices to the highest bidder. How many consulships is Cleander said to have sold in one day?",
    "answer": "TWENTY-FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which neoteric poet wrote a propemticon to Asinius Pollio in 56 B.C., but was better known for narrating the incestuous love of Myrrha for her father Cinyras?",
    "answer": "CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which neoteric poet and follower of the Atticist movement wrote a grief filled epicedion over the untimely death of his wife Quintillia, but is more known for the eponymous epyllion of the heroine who was loved by Jupiter and persecuted by Juno?",
    "answer": "(LICINIUS) CALVUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Which neoteric poet from Cisalpine Gaul wrote on a Cretan myth of the goddess Dictynna and was known among his comrades as the Latin Siren?",
    "answer": "VALERIUS CATO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of Michigan, Kentucky, Idaho, Missouri, and North Carolina, which states do not have an imperative in their Latin mottoes?",
    "answer": "KENTUCKY AND NORTH CAROLINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of Vermont, Colorado, Virginia, District of Columbia, and Kentucky, which, if any, contain a verb in their Latin mottoes?",
    "answer": "VERMONT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Among Connecticut, Alabama, Michigan, New Mexico, and both of South Carolina’s mottoes, how many verb forms, including participals and infinitives, are there in total?",
    "answer": "TEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who fathered by his wife Enarete several of the most powerful rulers of their time, namely Cretheus, Athamas, Sisyphus, Salmoneus, and Perieres?",
    "answer": "AEOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Elis is sometimes regarded as a son of Aeolus, though he is more frequently called a son of Zeus?",
    "answer": "AETHLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of his did Aeolus kill for committing incest?",
    "answer": "CANACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After only reigning for a meager eight months, what emperor was found dead in his tent at Dadastana?",
    "answer": "JOVIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jovian only became emperor after another man refused. What advisor, and Praetorian Prefect of the East, was initially chosen to succeed Julian the Apostate?",
    "answer": "SECUNDUS SALUTIUS / SALLUSTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In an effort to make a hasty peace with the Persians, Jovian gave away a lot of land to what Sassanid king?",
    "answer": "SHAPUR II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following English words, if any, is derived from the same Latin word as mauve: meager, taupe, marshmallow, mallet, manger?",
    "answer": "MARSHMALLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb is “manger” derived?",
    "answer": "MANDŌ, MANDERE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb mandō, mandāre means “to give a compliment”?",
    "answer": "COMMEND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Quamvis scelerati illi fuissent, sunt vere tui parentes.",
    "answer": "THEY ARE INDEED YOUR PARENTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Etsī caret mātūritāte, tamen hic discipulus, alacer multa discere, nōn est malum.",
    "answer": "EAGER TO LEARN MANY THINGS, IS NOT BAD."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Licet omnēs tibi terrōrēs perīculaque impendeant, ne pertimueris!",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In the face of the unhaulting spread of vice, what author refuses to conform to the rationalistic tradition of satire by adopting the use of indignation to convey the fury of his disgust within his 16 satires?",
    "answer": "JUVENAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Juvenal often makes note of his disgust of the widespread moral corruption around him that in his third Satire, Juvenal tells the story of what friend of his who abandons Rome, for life there has become too dangerous for honest men?",
    "answer": "UMBRICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "There was no doubt that Juvenal’s works may have offended many, but the final straw came for him when he offended the emperor’s favorite and was sent to spend his final place in what land?",
    "answer": "EGYPT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "That she was called, at her shrine at Athens, the eldest of the Fates, and that she taught the workings of the planets to Hermes are traces in the Greek tradition of what deity’s Asiatic role as an all-knowing queen of heaven?",
    "answer": "APHRODITE’S"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What minor goddess has no myth beyond being called one of the Fates or a daughter of Zeus?",
    "answer": "TYCHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What female death spirits, who personified only the inevitability of death, and unlike the Erinyes had no retributive duties, are occasionally identified with the Fates as the bringers of death?",
    "answer": "KERES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Plautus includes Sosicles reuniting with his brother after being separated and raised in different households?",
    "answer": "MENAECHMI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In which play by Plautus does the eponymous character swindle Periphanes so that his master Strippocles can purchase the two girls he loves?",
    "answer": "EPIDICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to stock character names in Atellan Farce, what does Plautus’ nomen connote about his appearance?",
    "answer": "FLAT FOOTED/BIG EARED (MACCUS IS HIS NOMEN)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin motto of Harvard is, of course, veritas, the third declension noun that means “truth.” Give the definition of the other Latin word that has also has a form “veritas.”",
    "answer": "TO FEAR/RESPECT/REVERE (VEREOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two meanings can the Latin word flet have?",
    "answer": "IT WEEPS, LET IT BLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What three meanings can the Latin word nemus have?",
    "answer": "GROVE, LET US SWIM, & WE WEAVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following poetic passage, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the question that follows in English: Abstineas, Mors atra, precor: non hic mihi mater Quae legat in maestos ossa perusta sinus, Non soror, Assyrios cineri quae dedat odores Et fleat effusis ante sepulcra comis, Delia non usquam; quae me cum mitteret urbe, Dicitur ante omnes consuluisse deos. Illa sacras pueri sortes ter sustulit: illi Rettulit e trinis omina certa puer. The question: In order to convince death to keep his hands away, the poet begs for mercy by pointing out the absence of what three people?",
    "answer": "HIS MOTHER, HIS SISTER, DELIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two actions are described as happening thrice in this passage?",
    "answer": "AND THE BOY ASCRIBING GOOD OMENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Where was the poet when Delia consulted the gods?",
    "answer": "OUTSIDE OF THE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At age twenty-two, I was a consul of Rome in 348 BC. I was an ardent supporter of the Lex Ogulnia of 300 BC. During my hundred-year lifespan, I held the consulship an astounding six times. Probably my most famous act, I earned my cognomen after a raven helped me defeat a giant Gaul in single combat. Who am I? ",
    "answer": "FLYING IN FRONT OF GAUL’S FACE/EYES / OBSTRUCTING HIS VIEW)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What emperor later erected a statue of Corvus in his Forum?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Shortly after the Greeks first disembarked from their ships, Achilles battled against and killed what king of Colonae, who had been granted invulnerability to weapons by his father Poseidon?",
    "answer": "CYCNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Achilles successfully kill Cycnus?",
    "answer": "HE STRANGLED HIM WITH THE THRONGS OF HIS HELMET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Another Cycnus, although aided by his father Ares, lost in battle to what Greek hero?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  }
  
  

]
